<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE spec SYSTEM "xmlspec.dtd">
<!-- edited with XMLSpy v2006 rel. 3 sp1 (http://www.altova.com) by Ben Caldwell (W3C) -->
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="techs-merge.xslt"?>
<spec status="final" w3c-doctype="wgnote" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
	<header>
		<title>Techniques for <abbr expansion="Web Content Accessibility Guidelines">WCAG</abbr> 2.0</title>
		<subtitle>Techniques and Failures for Web Content Accessibility Guidelines 2.0</subtitle>
		<w3c-designation>WCAG20-TECHS</w3c-designation>
		<w3c-doctype>W3C Working Group Note</w3c-doctype>
		<pubdate>
			<day>11</day>
			<month>March</month>
			<year>2014</year>
		</pubdate>
		<publoc>
			<!--<loc href="http://www.w3.org/WAI/GL/2014/WD-WCAG20-TECHS-20140304/">http://www.w3.org/WAI/GL/2014/WD-WCAG20-TECHS-20140304/</loc>-->
			<loc href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2014/NOTE-WCAG20-TECHS-20140311/">http://www.w3.org/TR/2014/NOTE-WCAG20-TECHS-20140311/</loc>
		</publoc>
		<altlocs>
			<loc href="complete.html">Single file version</loc>
			<loc href="complete-diff.html">Single file diff-marked version showing revisions since 5 September 2013</loc>
			<loc href="/WAI/WCAG20/versions/techniques/">Alternate Versions of Techniques for WCAG 2.0</loc>
		</altlocs>
		<latestloc>
			<loc href="http://www.w3.org/TR/WCAG20-TECHS/">http://www.w3.org/TR/WCAG20-TECHS/</loc>
			<!--<loc href="http://www.w3.org/WAI/GL/WCAG20-TECHS/">http://www.w3.org/WAI/GL/WCAG20-TECHS/</loc>-->
		</latestloc>
		<prevlocs>
			<!--<loc href="http://www.w3.org/WAI/GL/2014/WD-WCAG20-TECHS-20140107/">http://www.w3.org/WAI/GL/2014/WD-WCAG20-TECHS-20140107/</loc>-->
			<loc href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2013/NOTE-WCAG20-TECHS-20130905/">http://www.w3.org/TR/2013/NOTE-WCAG20-TECHS-20130905/</loc>
		</prevlocs>
		<authlist>
			<author role="current">
				<name>Michael Cooper</name>
				<affiliation>W3C</affiliation>
			</author>
			<author role="current">
				<name>Andrew Kirkpatrick</name>
				<affiliation>Adobe Systems Inc.</affiliation>
			</author>
			<author role="current">
				<name>Joshue O Connor</name>
				<affiliation>NCBI Centre for Inclusive Technology (CFIT)</affiliation>
			</author>
			<author role="past">
				<name>Loretta Guarino Reid</name>
				<affiliation>(until May 2013 while at Google, Inc.)</affiliation>
			</author>
			<author role="past">
				<name>Gregg Vanderheiden</name>
				<affiliation>(until May 2013 while at Trace R&amp;D Center, University of
					Wisconsin-Madison)</affiliation>
			</author>
			<author role="past">
				<name>Ben Caldwell</name>
				<affiliation>(until September 2010 while at Trace R&amp;D Center, University of
					Wisconsin-Madison)</affiliation>
			</author>
			<author role="past">
				<name>Wendy Chisholm</name>
				<affiliation>(until July 2006 while at W3C)</affiliation>
			</author>
			<author role="past">
				<name>John Slatin</name>
				<affiliation>(until June 2006 while at Accessibility Institute, University of Texas at
					Austin)</affiliation>
			</author>
		</authlist>
		<status>
			<p><emph>This section describes the status of this document at the time of its publication. Other documents may supersede this document. A list of current W3C publications and the latest revision of this technical report can be found in the <loc href="http://www.w3.org/TR/">W3C technical reports index</loc> at <loc href="http://www.w3.org/TR/">http://www.w3.org/TR/</loc>.</emph></p>
			<p>This is a <phrase role="final">Working Group Note</phrase><phrase role="ext-review">Public Editors' Draft of</phrase> "Techniques for WCAG 2.0". These techniques are produced by the <loc href="http://www.w3.org/WAI/GL/">Web Content Accessibility Guidelines Working Group</loc> to provide guidance about how to conform to the <loc href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2008/REC-WCAG20-20081211/">Web Content Accessibility Guidelines (WCAG) 2.0 Recommendation</loc>. Techniques are referenced from <loc href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2013/NOTE-UNDERSTANDING-WCAG20-20130905/">Understanding WCAG 2.0</loc> and <loc href="http://www.w3.org/WAI/WCAG20/quickref/20130905/">How to Meet WCAG 2.0</loc>. Please note that the contents of this document are informative (they provide guidance), and not normative (they do not set requirements for conforming to WCAG 2.0).</p>
			<p>WCAG 2.0 Techniques was <loc href="http://www.w3.org/TR/WCAG20-TECHS/">previously published on 11 December 2008</loc> as a Working Group Note and updated 14 October 2010, 3 January 2012, and 5 September 2013. This new version updates the support information provided for WCAG 2.0. Note that WCAG 2.0 itself remains unchanged, only the informative support materials have been updated. Primary changes include additional WAI-ARIA techniques, and clarifications based on input from the public and translators. <phrase role="ext-review">The purpose of this draft is to collect public feedback on proposed changes since the <loc href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2013/NOTE-WCAG20-TECHS-20130905/">WCAG 2.0 Techniques Working Group Note of 5 September 2013</loc>. The Working Group intends to publish an updated Note once feedback from this review has been incorporated. <emph role="bold">The existing Techniques document remains in place as a W3C Note</emph> while this separate draft update is under review and the WCAG Working Group addresses comments. The Working Group is still discussing whether it is appropriate to use various aria attributes to provide text alternatives for images without providing an alt attribute. <loc href="ARIA10" linktype="aria">ARIA10: Using aria-labelledby to provide a text alternative for non-text content</loc> is included to invite public comment and help the working group come to a conclusion about this technique as well as related items (e.g. <loc href="F65" linktype="failure">F65</loc>). Examples within ARIA10 demonstrate situations where it might be desirable just to use aria-labelledby with no alt attribute. We solicit feedback on this example and on the general issue. </phrase> The changes are highlighted in the <loc href="complete-diff">diff-marked version</loc>.</p>
			<p><phrase role="ext-review">Comments on this draft are due <emph role="bold">on or before 14 February 2014</emph>.</phrase> The Working Group requests that any comments be made using the provided <loc href="http://www.w3.org/WAI/WCAG20/comments/">online comment form</loc>. If this is not possible, comments can also be sent to <loc href="mailto:public-comments-wcag20@w3.org">public-comments-wcag20@w3.org</loc>. The <loc href="http://lists.w3.org/Archives/Public/public-comments-wcag20/">archives for the public comments list</loc> are publicly available. Comments received on this document may be addressed in future versions of this document, or in another manner. <!--The Working Group does not plan to make formal responses to comments. -->Archives of the <loc href="http://lists.w3.org/Archives/Public/w3c-wai-gl/">WCAG WG mailing list discussions</loc> are also publicly available, and future work undertaken by the Working Group may address comments received on this document.</p>
			<p>Materials from the public to assist in documenting techniques are particularly welcomed. Please use the <loc href="http://www.w3.org/WAI/GL/WCAG20/TECHS-SUBMIT/">Techniques Submission Form</loc> to submit techniques. </p>
			<p>This document has been produced as part of the W3C <loc href="http://www.w3.org/WAI/">Web Accessibility Initiative</loc> (WAI). The goals of the WCAG Working Group are discussed in the <loc href="http://www.w3.org/WAI/GL/new-charter-2000.html">WCAG Working Group charter</loc>. The WCAG Working Group is part of the <loc href="http://www.w3.org/WAI/Technical/Activity">WAI Technical Activity</loc>.</p>
			<p> Publication as a <phrase role="final">Working Group Note</phrase><phrase role="ext-review">Public Editors' Draft</phrase> does not imply endorsement by the W3C Membership. This is a draft document and may be updated, replaced or obsoleted by other documents at any time. It is inappropriate to cite this document as other than work in progress. </p>
			<p>This document was produced by a group operating under the <loc href="http://www.w3.org/Consortium/Patent-Policy-20040205/">5 February 2004 W3C Patent Policy</loc>. W3C maintains a <loc role="disclosures" href="http://www.w3.org/2004/01/pp-impl/35422/status">public list of any patent disclosures</loc> made in connection with the deliverables of the group; that page also includes instructions for disclosing a patent. An individual who has actual knowledge of a patent which the individual believes contains <loc href="http://www.w3.org/Consortium/Patent-Policy-20040205/#def-essential">Essential Claim(s)</loc> must disclose the information in accordance with <loc href="http://www.w3.org/Consortium/Patent-Policy-20040205/#sec-Disclosure">section 6 of the W3C Patent Policy</loc>. </p>
		</status>
		<abstract>
			<p id="abstract-general-intro">This <emph>Techniques for WCAG 2.0</emph> document provides guidance for web content authors and evaluators on meeting <loc href="http://www.w3.org/TR/WCAG20/">Web Content Accessibility Guidelines (WCAG) 2.0</loc> <bibref ref="WCAG20"/> success criteria. It is part of a series of documents published by the W3C Web Accessibility Initiative (WAI) to support WCAG 2.0. For an introduction to WCAG, supporting technical documents, and educational material, see <loc href="http://www.w3.org/WAI/intro/wcag">Web Content Accessibility Guidelines (WCAG) Overview</loc>.</p>
			<p><phrase id="abstract-techniques-informative">Techniques are informative—that means they are not required. The basis for determining conformance to WCAG 2.0 is the success criteria from the <loc href="http://www.w3.org/TR/WCAG20/">WCAG 2.0 standard</loc>—not the techniques.</phrase> <phrase id="abstract-techniques-understanding"><emph role="bold">For important information about techniques, please see the <loc href="understanding-techniques" linktype="understanding">Understanding Techniques for WCAG Success Criteria</loc> section of Understanding WCAG 2.0.</emph></phrase></p>
			<p id="abstract-not-standalone"><emph>Techniques for WCAG 2.0</emph> is not intended to be used as a stand-alone document. Instead, it is expected that content authors will usually use <loc href="http://www.w3.org/WAI/WCAG20/quickref/">How to Meet WCAG 2.0: A customizable quick reference</loc> to read the WCAG success criteria, and follow links from there to specific topics in Understanding WCAG 2.0 and to specific techniques.</p>
		</abstract>
		<langusage>
			<language id="en-US"/>
		</langusage>
		<revisiondesc>
			<p>
				<loc href="/WAI/GL/WCAG20/change-history.html">History of Changes to WCAG 2.0 Working Drafts</loc>
			</p>
		</revisiondesc>
	</header>
	<front>
		<div1 id="intro">
			<head>Introduction to <emph>Techniques for WCAG 2.0</emph></head>
			<p use-id="abstract-general-intro"/>
			<p>WCAG 2.0 itself is a stable document that does not change. This <emph>Techniques for WCAG 2.0</emph> document is updated periodically, about once a year, to cover more current best practices and changes in technologies and tools.</p>
			<p><phrase use-id="abstract-techniques-informative"/>.</p>
			<note>
				<p>W3C cautions against requiring W3C's sufficient techniques. The only thing that should be required is meeting the WCAG 2.0 success criteria. To learn more, see:</p>
				<ulist>
					<item>
						<p><loc href="http://www.w3.org/WAI/WCAG20/wcag2faq.html#techsnot">What would be the negative consequences of allowing <emph>only</emph> W3C's published techniques to be used for conformance to WCAG 2.0?</loc> in the WCAG 2 FAQ</p>
					</item>
					<!--
							<item>
								<p>
									<loc href="http://www.w3.org/2013/02/stdref">Normative References to W3C Standards</loc>
									<span class="quiet">[@@ Ian asks that we not point to this for now.]</span>
								</p>
							</item>
							-->
				</ulist>
			</note>
			<p use-id="abstract-not-standalone"/>
			<p><phrase use-id="abstract-techniques-understanding"/></p>
		</div1>
	</front>
	<body>
		<xi:include href="general-tech-src.xml" xpointer="general"/>
		<xi:include href="html-tech-src.xml" xpointer="html"/>
		<xi:include href="css-tech.xml" xpointer="css"/>
		<xi:include href="script-tech-src.xml" xpointer="client-side-script"/>
		<xi:include href="server-tech-src.xml" xpointer="server-side-script"/>
		<xi:include href="SMIL-tech-src.xml" xpointer="smil"/>
		<xi:include href="plain-text-tech-src.xml" xpointer="text"/>
		<xi:include href="ARIA-tech-src.xml" xpointer="aria"/>
		<xi:include href="flash-tech-src.xml" xpointer="flash"/>
		<xi:include href="silverlight-tech-src.xml" xpointer="silverlight"/>
		<xi:include href="pdf-tech-src.xml" xpointer="pdf"/>
		<xi:include href="failure-tech-src.xml" xpointer="failures"/>
	</body>
	<back>
		<!-- BBC - This is the master list. Some of these refs also appear in the Understanding Doc. -->
		<inform-div1 id="references">
			<head>References</head>
			<blist>
				<bibl id="CSS1" key="CSS1">"Cascading Style Sheets, level 1," B. Bos, H. Wium Lie, eds., W3C Recommendation 17 Dec 1996, revised 11 Jan 1999. Available at <loc href="http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-CSS1/">http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-CSS1/</loc>.</bibl>
				<bibl id="CSS2" key="CSS2">"Cascading Style Sheets, level 2," B. Bos, H. Wium Lie, C. Lilley, and I. Jacobs, eds., W3C Recommendation 12 May 1998. Available at <loc href="http://www.w3.org/TR/CSS2/">http://www.w3.org/TR/CSS2/</loc>.</bibl>
				<bibl id="CSS21" key="CSS21">"Cascading Style Sheets, level 2 revision 1,"  B. Bos, T. Çelik,  I. Hickson,   H. Wium Lie, eds., W3C Candidate Recommendation 25 February 2004.  Available at:  <loc href="http://www.w3.org/TR/CSS21/">http://www.w3.org/TR/CSS21/</loc>
				</bibl>
				<bibl id="CSS3" key="CSS3">
					<titleref href="http://www.w3.org/Style/CSS/current-work">[CSS 2.1 and CSS 3] Roadmap</titleref>, CSS WG's table of modules and publication dates.</bibl>
				<bibl id="FLASH" key="FLASH">"Flash", Adobe Systems. Available at <loc href="http://www.adobe.com/devnet/swf.html">http://www.adobe.com/devnet/swf.html</loc>.</bibl>
				<bibl id="HTML4" key="HTML4">"HTML 4.01 Specification," D. Raggett, A. Le Hors, I. Jacobs, eds.,  W3C Recommendation 24 December 1999. Available at <loc href="http://www.w3.org/TR/html401/">http://www.w3.org/TR/html401/</loc>
				</bibl>
				<bibl id="PDF" key="PDF">"PDF", Adobe Systems. Available at <loc href="http://www.adobe.com/devnet/pdf.html">http://www.adobe.com/devnet/pdf.html</loc>.</bibl>
				<bibl id="WCAG20" key="WCAG20">"Web Content Accessibility Guidelines 2.0,"  B. Caldwell, M Cooper, L Guarino Reid, and G. Vanderheiden, eds., W3 Recommendation 12 December 2008, <loc href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2008/REC-WCAG20-20081211/">http://www.w3.org/TR/2008/REC-WCAG20-20081211</loc>.  The latest version of WCAG 2.0 is available at <loc href="http://www.w3.org/TR/WCAG20/">http://www.w3.org/TR/WCAG20/</loc>.
				</bibl>
				<bibl id="XHTML1" key="XHTML1">"XHTML 1.0 The Extensible HyperText Markup Language (Second Edition)," S. Pemberton, et al.,  W3C Recommendation 26 January 2000, revised 1 August 2002. Available at:  <loc href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/">http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/</loc>.</bibl>
			</blist>
		</inform-div1>
	</back>
</spec>
