<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="ARIA13">
   <short-name>Using aria-labelledby to name regions and landmarks</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>Technologies that support <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
              href="http://www.w3.org/TR/wai-aria/">Accessible Rich Internet Applications (WAI-ARIA)</loc>. </p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="content-structure-separation-programmatic"
                         relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <ua-issues>
      <ua-issue name="" version="">
         <p>See <specref ref="wai-aria_ua_support"/> for general information on user agent support.</p>
      </ua-issue>
   </ua-issues>
   <description>
      <p>The purpose of this technique is to provide names for regions of a page that can be read by assistive technology.  The <att>aria-labelledby</att> attribute provides a way to associate an section of the page marked up as a region or landmarks with text that is on the page that labels it.
</p>
      <p>Landmark roles (or "landmarks") programmatically identify sections of a page. Landmarks help assistive technology (AT) users orient themselves to a page and help them navigate easily to various sections of a page.
</p>
      <p>Like <att>aria-describedby</att>, <att>aria-labelledby</att> can accept multiple ids to point to other regions of the page using a space separated list. It is also limited to ids for defining these sets.
</p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Identify a landmark with on-page text</head>
         <description>
            <p>Below is an example of <att>aria-labelledby</att> used on a complementary Landmark. The region of the document to which the heading pertains could be marked with the <att>aria-labelledby</att> property containing the value of the <att>id</att> for the header.</p>
            <codeblock xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[<p role="complementary" aria-labelledby="hdr1">
 <h1 id="hdr1">
    Top News Stories
 </h1>
</p>]]></codeblock>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Identification for Application landmarks</head>
         <description>
            <p>The following code snippet for application landmarks with static prose. If you have a regional landmark of type application and static descriptive text is available, then on the application landmark, include an aria-describedby reference to associate the application and the static text as shown here:</p>
            <codeblock xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[<div role="application" aria-labelledby="p123" aria-describedby="info">
<h1 id="p123">Calendar<h1>
<p id="info">
This calendar shows the game schedule for the Boston Red Sox.
</p>
<div role="grid">
....
</div>]]></codeblock>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p> 
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.w3.org/TR/wai-aria-practices/">WAI-ARIA Authoring Practices 1.1</loc>
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> 
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.w3.org/TR/html-aapi/#accessible-name-and-description-calculation">HTML to Platform Accessibility APIs Implementation Guide: Accessible Name and Description Calculation</loc>
               </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </see-also>
   </resources>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="ARIA10"/>
      <relatedtech idref="ARIA6"/>
      <relatedtech idref="ARIA9"/>
      <relatedtech idref="ARIA16"/>
      <relatedtech idref="ARIA7"/>
      <relatedtech idref="G92"/>
      <relatedtech idref="H45"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Examine each element with attribute <code><![CDATA[role=region]]></code> or with a <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.w3.org/TR/wai-aria/roles#landmark_roles">landmark role</loc>, where an <code><![CDATA[aria-labelledby]]></code> attribute is also present.
</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Check that the value of the <code><![CDATA[aria-labelledby]]></code> attribute is the <code><![CDATA[id]]></code> of an element on the page. 
</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Check that the text of the element with that <code><![CDATA[id]]></code> accurately labels the section of the page.
</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>#2 and #3 are true.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
