testing git sync
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="ARIA20" diff="add">
				<short-name>Using aria-describedby for link purpose</short-name>
				<applicability>
					<p>Technologies that support <loc href="http://www.w3.org/TR/wai-aria/">Accessible Rich Internet Applications (WAI-ARIA)</loc>. </p>
					
                            
                        </ulist>
					</ua-issue>
				</ua-issues>
				<description>
					<p>With the <att>aria-describedby</att> attribute, authors can use a visible text element on the page as a label for a focusable element (a form control or a link). For example, a "read more..." link could be associated with the text of the heading of the preceding section to make the purpose of the link unambiguous (see example 1).</p>
		
                    <p>When associating target text with a focusable element with the help of <att>aria-describedby</att>, the target text element is given an ID which is referenced in the value of the <att>aria-describedby</att> attribute of the focusable element.</p>
                    <p>It is also possible to reference several text elements on the page to provide a more detailed description for a focusable element. Each of the text elements used must be given a unique ID which is referenced as a string of IDs (IDREF) in the value of the <att>aria-describedby</att> attribute. The description text should then be concatenated following the order of IDs in the value of the <att>aria-describedby</att> attribute.</p>
                    <p>When applied on links, <att>aria-describedby</att> can be used to identify the purpose of a link that may be readily apparent for sighted users, but less obvious for screen reader users.</p>
					<p>From the perspective of a web author, <att>aria-describedby</att> references target text exactly like <att>aria-labelledby</att>. However, unlike <att>aria-labelledby</att>, the <att>aria-describedby</att> attribute allows the link text AND the supplementary text to be read by assistive technology. This is a great advantage over <att>aria-labelledby</att> which, by default, replaces the link text, and without special attention, leaves a non-sighted user without any reasonable way of knowing what is in the actual anchor link text.</p>
                    
				</description>
				<examples>
					<eg-group>
						<head>Providing additional information for links</head>
						<description>
							<p>This example should replace the "read more" link text at the end of the teaser text with the content of the <el>h2</el> heading referenced by <att>aria-labelledby</att>.</p>
						<codeblock xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[<h2 id="headline">Stock market makes dramatic recovery</h2>

<p>After a day of heavy trading, all major market report significant imporvements</p>
   <a href="news.html" aria-describedby="headline">Read more...</a></p>]]></codeblock>
                            </description>
                    </eg-group>
                    
					                    
				
                </examples>
				<resources>
					<see-also>
						<ulist>
							
						</ulist>
					</see-also>
				</resources>
<related-techniques>
				</related-techniques>
				<tests>
					<procedure>
						<p>For each link that has an <att>aria-describedby</att> attribute:</p>
                        <olist>
							<item>
								<p>Check that each ID in the value of the <att>aria-describedby</att> attribute matches an ID of a text element used as part of the link purpose.</p>
							</item>
							<item>
								<p>Check that the value of the <att>aria-describedby</att> combined with the link text provides the purpose of the link.</p>
							</item>
						</olist>
					</procedure>
					<expected-results>
						<ulist>
							<item>
								<p>#1 is true.</p>
							</item>
						</ulist>
					</expected-results>
				</tests>
			</technique>          
