<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<guidelines lang="en">
   <understanding>
      <name>Introduction to Understanding WCAG 2.1</name>
      <file href="intro"/>
   </understanding>
   <understanding>
      <name>Understanding Techniques for WCAG Success Criteria</name>
      <file href="understanding-techniques"/>
   </understanding>
   <principle id="perceivable">
      <version>WCAG20</version>
      <num>1</num>
      <name> Perceivable </name>
      <content>
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Information and user interface components must be presentable to users in ways they
            can perceive.
         </p>
      </content>
      <guideline id="text-alternatives">
         <num>1.1</num>
         <name>Text Alternatives</name>
         <content>
            <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Provide text alternatives for any non-text content so that it can be changed into
               other forms people need, such as large print, braille, speech, symbols or simpler
               language.
            </p>
         </content>
         <file href="text-alternatives"/>
         <success-criterion id="non-text-content">
            <num>1.1.1</num>
            <name>Non-text Content</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All <a>non-text content</a> that is presented to the user has a <a>text alternative</a> that serves the equivalent purpose, except for the situations listed below.
   </p>
               <dl xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      
                  <dt>Controls, Input</dt>
      
                  <dd>
         
                     <p>If non-text content is a control or accepts user input, then it has a <a>name</a> that describes its purpose. (Refer to <a href="#name-role-value">Success Criterion 4.1.2</a> for additional requirements for controls and content that accepts user input.)
         </p>
         
                  </dd>
      
                  <dt>Time-Based Media</dt>
      
                  <dd>
         
                     <p>If non-text content is time-based media, then text alternatives at least provide descriptive
            identification of the non-text content. (Refer to <a href="#time-based-media">Guideline 1.2</a> for additional requirements for media.)
         </p>
         
                  </dd>
      
                  <dt>Test</dt>
      
                  <dd>
         
                     <p>If non-text content is a test or exercise that would be invalid if presented in <a>text</a>, then text alternatives at least provide descriptive identification of the non-text
            content.
         </p>
         
                  </dd>
      
                  <dt>Sensory</dt>
      
                  <dd>
         
                     <p>If non-text content is primarily intended to create a <a>specific sensory experience</a>, then text alternatives at least provide descriptive identification of the non-text
            content.
         </p>
         
                  </dd>
      
                  <dt>
                     <a>CAPTCHA</a>
                  </dt>
      
                  <dd>
         
                     <p>If the purpose of non-text content is to confirm that content is being accessed by
            a person rather than a computer, then text alternatives that identify and describe
            the purpose of the non-text content are provided, and alternative forms of CAPTCHA
            using output modes for different types of sensory perception are provided to accommodate
            different disabilities.
         </p>
         
                  </dd>
      
                  <dt>Decoration, Formatting, Invisible</dt>
      
                  <dd>
         
                     <p>If non-text content is <a>pure decoration</a>, is used only for visual formatting, or is not presented to users, then it is implemented
            in a way that it can be ignored by <a>assistive technology</a>.
         </p>
         
                  </dd>
      
               </dl>
            </content>
            <level>A</level>
            <file href="non-text-content"/>
         </success-criterion>
      </guideline>
      <guideline id="time-based-media">
         <num>1.2</num>
         <name>Time-based Media</name>
         <content>
            <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Provide alternatives for time-based media.</p>
         </content>
         <file href="time-based-media"/>
         <success-criterion id="audio-only-and-video-only-prerecorded">
            <num>1.2.1</num>
            <name>Audio-only and Video-only (Prerecorded)</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For <a>prerecorded</a>
                  <a>audio-only</a> and prerecorded <a>video-only</a> media, the following are true, except when the audio or video is a <a>media alternative for text</a> and is clearly labeled as such:
   </p>
               <dl xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      
                  <dt>Prerecorded Audio-only</dt>
      
                  <dd>
         
                     <p>An <a>alternative for time-based media</a> is provided that presents equivalent information for prerecorded audio-only content.
         </p>
         
                  </dd>
      
                  <dt>Prerecorded Video-only</dt>
      
                  <dd>
         
                     <p>Either an alternative for time-based media or an audio track is provided that presents
            equivalent information for prerecorded video-only content.
         </p>
         
                  </dd>
      
               </dl>
            </content>
            <level>A</level>
            <file href="audio-only-and-video-only-prerecorded"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="captions-prerecorded">
            <num>1.2.2</num>
            <name>Captions (Prerecorded)</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
                  <a>Captions</a> are provided for all <a>prerecorded</a>
                  <a>audio</a> content in <a>synchronized media</a>, except when the media is a <a>media alternative for text</a> and is clearly labeled as such.
   </p>
            </content>
            <level>A</level>
            <file href="captions-prerecorded"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="audio-description-or-media-alternative-prerecorded">
            <num>1.2.3</num>
            <name>Audio Description or Media Alternative (Prerecorded)</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An <a>alternative for time-based media</a> or <a>audio description</a> of the <a>prerecorded</a>
                  <a>video</a> content is provided for <a>synchronized media</a>, except when the media is a <a>media alternative for text</a> and is clearly labeled as such.
   </p>
            </content>
            <level>A</level>
            <file href="audio-description-or-media-alternative-prerecorded"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="captions-live">
            <num>1.2.4</num>
            <name>Captions (Live)</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
                  <a>Captions</a> are provided for all <a>live</a>
                  <a>audio</a> content in <a>synchronized media</a>.
   </p>
            </content>
            <level>AA</level>
            <file href="captions-live"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="audio-description-prerecorded">
            <num>1.2.5</num>
            <name>Audio Description (Prerecorded)</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
                  <a>Audio description</a> is provided for all <a>prerecorded</a>
                  <a>video</a> content in <a>synchronized media</a>.
   </p>
            </content>
            <level>AA</level>
            <file href="audio-description-prerecorded"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="sign-language-prerecorded">
            <num>1.2.6</num>
            <name>Sign Language (Prerecorded)</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
                  <a>Sign language interpretation</a> is provided for all <a>prerecorded</a>
                  <a>audio</a> content in <a>synchronized media</a>.
   </p>
            </content>
            <level>AAA</level>
            <file href="sign-language-prerecorded"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="extended-audio-description-prerecorded">
            <num>1.2.7</num>
            <name>Extended Audio Description (Prerecorded)</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Where pauses in foreground audio are insufficient to allow <a>audio descriptions</a> to convey the sense of the video, <a>extended audio description</a> is provided for all <a>prerecorded</a>
                  <a>video</a> content in <a>synchronized media</a>.
   </p>
            </content>
            <level>AAA</level>
            <file href="extended-audio-description-prerecorded"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="media-alternative-prerecorded">
            <num>1.2.8</num>
            <name>Media Alternative (Prerecorded)</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An <a>alternative for time-based media</a> is provided for all <a>prerecorded</a>
                  <a>synchronized media</a> and for all prerecorded <a>video-only</a> media.
   </p>
            </content>
            <level>AAA</level>
            <file href="media-alternative-prerecorded"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="audio-only-live">
            <num>1.2.9</num>
            <name>Audio-only (Live)</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An <a>alternative for time-based media</a> that presents equivalent information for <a>live</a>
                  <a>audio-only</a> content is provided.
   </p>
            </content>
            <level>AAA</level>
            <file href="audio-only-live"/>
         </success-criterion>
      </guideline>
      <guideline id="adaptable">
         <num>1.3</num>
         <name>Adaptable</name>
         <content>
            <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Create content that can be presented in different ways (for example simpler layout)
               without losing information or structure.
            </p>
         </content>
         <file href="adaptable"/>
         <success-criterion id="info-and-relationships">
            <num>1.3.1</num>
            <name>Info and Relationships</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Information, <a>structure</a>, and <a>relationships</a> conveyed through <a>presentation</a> can be <a>programmatically determined</a> or are available in text.
   </p>
            </content>
            <level>A</level>
            <file href="info-and-relationships"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="meaningful-sequence">
            <num>1.3.2</num>
            <name>Meaningful Sequence</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When the sequence in which content is presented affects its meaning, a <a>correct reading sequence</a> can be <a>programmatically determined</a>.
   </p>
            </content>
            <level>A</level>
            <file href="meaningful-sequence"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="sensory-characteristics">
            <num>1.3.3</num>
            <name>Sensory Characteristics</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Instructions provided for understanding and operating content do not rely solely on
      sensory characteristics of components such as shape, color, size, visual location, orientation,
      or sound.
   </p>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">For requirements related to color, refer to <a href="#distinguishable">Guideline 1.4</a>.</p>
            </content>
            <level>A</level>
            <file href="sensory-characteristics"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="orientation">
            <num>1.3.4</num>
            <name>Orientation</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Content does not restrict its view and operation to a single display orientation, such as portrait or landscape, unless a specific display orientation is <a>essential</a>.</p>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Examples where a particular display orientation may be essential are a bank check, a piano application, slides for a projector or television, or virtual reality content where content is not necessarily restricted to landscape or portrait display orientation.</p>
            </content>
            <level>AA</level>
            <file href="orientation"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="identify-input-purpose">
            <num>1.3.5</num>
            <name>Identify Input Purpose</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The purpose of each input field collecting information about the user can be <a>programmatically determined</a> when:</p>
               <ul xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
                  <li>The input field serves a purpose identified in the <a href="#input-purposes">Input Purposes for User Interface Components section</a>; and</li>
                  <li>The content is implemented using technologies with support for identifying the expected meaning for form input data.</li>
               </ul>
            </content>
            <level>AA</level>
            <file href="identify-input-purpose"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="identify-purpose">
            <num>1.3.6</num>
            <name>Identify Purpose</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In content implemented using markup languages, the purpose of <a>User Interface Components</a>, icons, and <a>regions</a> can be <a>programmatically determined</a>.</p>
            </content>
            <level>AAA</level>
            <file href="identify-purpose"/>
         </success-criterion>
      </guideline>
      <guideline id="distinguishable">
         <num>1.4</num>
         <name>Distinguishable</name>
         <content>
            <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Make it easier for users to see and hear content including separating foreground from
               background.
            </p>
         </content>
         <file href="distinguishable"/>
         <success-criterion id="use-of-color">
            <num>1.4.1</num>
            <name>Use of Color</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Color is not used as the only visual means of conveying information, indicating an
      action, prompting a response, or distinguishing a visual element.
   </p>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">This success criterion addresses color perception specifically. Other forms of perception are covered in <a href="#adaptable">Guideline 1.3</a> including programmatic access to color and other visual presentation coding.</p>
            </content>
            <level>A</level>
            <file href="use-of-color"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="audio-control">
            <num>1.4.2</num>
            <name>Audio Control</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">If any audio on a Web page plays automatically for more than 3 seconds, either a <a>mechanism</a> is available to pause or stop the audio, or a mechanism is available to control audio
      volume independently from the overall system volume level.
   </p>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Since any content that does not meet this success criterion can interfere with a user's
      ability to use the whole page, all content on the Web page (whether or not it is used
      to meet other success criteria) must meet this success criterion. See <a href="#cc5">Conformance Requirement 5: Non-Interference</a>.
   </p>
            </content>
            <level>A</level>
            <file href="audio-control"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="contrast-minimum">
            <num>1.4.3</num>
            <name>Contrast (Minimum)</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The visual presentation of <a>text</a> and <a>images of text</a> has a <a>contrast ratio</a> of at least 4.5:1, except for the following:
   </p>
               <dl xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      
                  <dt>Large Text</dt>
      
                  <dd>
         
                     <p>
                        <a>Large-scale</a> text and images of large-scale text have a contrast ratio of at least 3:1;
         </p>
         
                  </dd>
      
                  <dt>Incidental</dt>
      
                  <dd>
         
                     <p>Text or images of text that are part of an inactive <a>user interface component</a>, that are <a>pure decoration</a>, that are not visible to anyone, or that are part of a picture that contains significant
            other visual content, have no contrast requirement.
         </p>
         
                  </dd>
      
                  <dt>Logotypes</dt>
      
                  <dd>
         
                     <p>Text that is part of a logo or brand name has no contrast requirement.</p>
         
                  </dd>
      
               </dl>
            </content>
            <level>AA</level>
            <file href="contrast-minimum"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="resize-text">
            <num>1.4.4</num>
            <name>Resize text</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Except for <a>captions</a> and <a>images of text</a>, <a>text</a> can be resized without <a>assistive technology</a> up to 200 percent without loss of content or functionality.
   </p>
            </content>
            <level>AA</level>
            <file href="resize-text"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="images-of-text">
            <num>1.4.5</num>
            <name>Images of Text</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">If the technologies being used can achieve the visual presentation, <a>text</a> is used to convey information rather than <a>images of text</a> except for the following:
   </p>
               <dl xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      
                  <dt>Customizable</dt>
      
                  <dd>
         
                     <p>The image of text can be <a>visually customized</a> to the user's requirements;
         </p>
         
                  </dd>
      
                  <dt>Essential</dt>
      
                  <dd>
         
                     <p>A particular presentation of text is <a>essential</a> to the information being conveyed.
         </p>
         
                  </dd>
      
               </dl>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Logotypes (text that is part of a logo or brand name) are considered essential.</p>
            </content>
            <level>AA</level>
            <file href="images-of-text"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="contrast-enhanced">
            <num>1.4.6</num>
            <name>Contrast (Enhanced)</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The visual presentation of <a>text</a> and <a>images of text</a> has a <a>contrast ratio</a> of at least 7:1, except for the following:
   </p>
               <dl xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      
                  <dt>Large Text</dt>
      
                  <dd>
         
                     <p>
                        <a>Large-scale</a> text and images of large-scale text have a contrast ratio of at least 4.5:1;
         </p>
         
                  </dd>
      
                  <dt>Incidental</dt>
      
                  <dd>
         
                     <p>Text or images of text that are part of an inactive <a>user interface component</a>, that are <a>pure decoration</a>, that are not visible to anyone, or that are part of a picture that contains significant
            other visual content, have no contrast requirement.
         </p>
         
                  </dd>
      
                  <dt>Logotypes</dt>
      
                  <dd>
         
                     <p>Text that is part of a logo or brand name has no contrast requirement.</p>
         
                  </dd>
      
               </dl>
            </content>
            <level>AAA</level>
            <file href="contrast-enhanced"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="low-or-no-background-audio">
            <num>1.4.7</num>
            <name>Low or No Background Audio</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For <a>prerecorded</a>
                  <a>audio-only</a> content that (1) contains primarily speech in the foreground, (2) is not an audio
      <a>CAPTCHA</a> or audio logo, and (3) is not vocalization intended to be primarily musical expression
      such as singing or rapping, at least one of the following is true:
   </p>
               <dl xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      
                  <dt>No Background</dt>
      
                  <dd>
         
                     <p>The audio does not contain background sounds.</p>
         
                  </dd>
      
                  <dt>Turn Off</dt>
      
                  <dd>
         
                     <p>The background sounds can be turned off.</p>
         
                  </dd>
      
                  <dt>20 dB</dt>
      
                  <dd>
         
                     <p>The background sounds are at least 20 decibels lower than the foreground speech content,
            with the exception of occasional sounds that last for only one or two seconds.
         </p>
         
                     <p class="note">Per the definition of "decibel," background sound that meets this requirement will
            be approximately four times quieter than the foreground speech content.
         </p>
         
                  </dd>
      
               </dl>
            </content>
            <level>AAA</level>
            <file href="low-or-no-background-audio"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="visual-presentation">
            <num>1.4.8</num>
            <name>Visual Presentation</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the visual presentation of <a>blocks of text</a>, a <a>mechanism</a> is available to achieve the following:
   </p>
               <ul xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
                  <li>Foreground and background colors can be selected by the user.</li>   
                  <li>Width is no more than 80 characters or glyphs (40 if CJK).</li>   
                  <li>Text is not justified (aligned to both the left and the right margins).</li>   
                  <li>Line spacing (leading) is at least space-and-a-half within paragraphs, and paragraph spacing is at least 1.5 times larger than the line spacing.</li>   
                  <li>Text can be resized without assistive technology up to 200 percent in a way that does not require the user to scroll horizontally to read a line of text <a>on a full-screen window</a>.</li>   
               </ul>
            </content>
            <level>AAA</level>
            <file href="visual-presentation"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="images-of-text-no-exception">
            <num>1.4.9</num>
            <name>Images of Text (No Exception)</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
                  <a>Images of text</a> are only used for <a>pure decoration</a> or where a particular presentation of <a>text</a> is <a>essential</a> to the information being conveyed.
   </p>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Logotypes (text that is part of a logo or brand name) are considered essential.</p>
            </content>
            <level>AAA</level>
            <file href="images-of-text-no-exception"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="reflow">
            <num>1.4.10</num>
            <name>Reflow</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Content can be presented without loss of information or functionality, and without requiring scrolling in two dimensions for:</p>
               <ul xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
                  <li>Vertical scrolling content at a width equivalent to 320 <a>CSS pixels</a>;</li>
                  <li>Horizontal scrolling content at a height equivalent to 256 <a>CSS pixels</a>.</li>
               </ul>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Except for parts of the content which require two-dimensional layout for usage or meaning.</p>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">320 CSS pixels is equivalent to a starting viewport width of 1280 CSS pixels wide at 400% zoom. For web content which is designed to scroll horizontally (e.g., with vertical text), 256 CSS pixels is equivalent to a starting viewport height of 1024 CSS pixels at 400% zoom.</p>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Examples of content which requires two-dimensional layout are images required for understanding (such as maps and diagrams), video, games, presentations, data tables (not individual cells), and interfaces where it is necessary to keep toolbars in view while manipulating content. It is acceptable to provide two-dimensional scrolling for such parts of the content.</p>
            </content>
            <level>AA</level>
            <file href="reflow"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="non-text-contrast">
            <num>1.4.11</num>
            <name>Non-text Contrast</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The visual <a>presentation</a> of the following have a <a>contrast ratio</a> of at least 3:1 against adjacent color(s):</p>
               <dl xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      						
                  <dt>User Interface Components</dt>
      						
                  <dd>Visual information required to identify <a>user interface components</a> and <a>states</a>, except for inactive components or where the appearance of the component is determined by the user agent and not modified by the author;</dd>
      						
                  <dt>Graphical Objects</dt>
      						
                  <dd>Parts of graphics required to understand the content, except when a particular presentation of graphics is <a>essential</a> to the information being conveyed.</dd>
      						
               </dl>
            </content>
            <level>AA</level>
            <file href="non-text-contrast"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="text-spacing">
            <num>1.4.12</num>
            <name>Text Spacing</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In content implemented using markup languages that support the following <a>text</a> 
                  <a>style properties</a>, no loss of content or functionality occurs by setting all of the following and by changing no other style property:</p>
               <ul xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
                  <li>Line height (line spacing) to at least 1.5 times the font size;</li>
                  <li>Spacing following paragraphs to at least 2 times the font size;</li>
                  <li>Letter spacing (tracking) to at least 0.12 times the font size;</li>
                  <li>Word spacing to at least 0.16 times the font size.</li>
               </ul>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Exception: Human languages and scripts that do not make use of one or more of these text style properties in written text can conform using only the properties that exist for that combination of language and script.</p>
            </content>
            <level>AA</level>
            <file href="text-spacing"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="content-on-hover-or-focus">
            <num>1.4.13</num>
            <name>Content on Hover or Focus</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Where receiving and then removing pointer hover or keyboard focus triggers additional content to become visible and then hidden, the following are true:</p>
               <dl xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

                  <dt>Dismissible</dt>
                  <dd>A <a>mechanism</a> is available to dismiss the additional content without moving pointer hover or keyboard focus, unless the additional content communicates an <a>input error</a> or does not obscure or replace other content;</dd>

                  <dt>Hoverable</dt>
                  <dd>If pointer hover can trigger the additional content, then the pointer can be moved  over the additional content without the additional content disappearing;</dd>

                  <dt>Persistent</dt>
                  <dd>The additional content remains visible until the hover or focus trigger is removed, the user dismisses it, or its information is no longer valid.</dd>

               </dl>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Exception: The visual presentation of the additional content is controlled by the user agent and is not modified by the author.</p>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Examples of additional content controlled by the user agent include browser tooltips created through use of the HTML <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/html/dom.html#the-title-attribute">
                     <code>title</code> attribute</a>.</p>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Custom tooltips, sub-menus, and other nonmodal popups that display on hover and focus are examples of additional content covered by this criterion.</p>
            </content>
            <level>AA</level>
            <file href="content-on-hover-or-focus"/>
         </success-criterion>
      </guideline>
   </principle>
   <principle id="operable">
      <version>WCAG20</version>
      <num>2</num>
      <name>Operable </name>
      <content>
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">User interface components and navigation must be operable.</p>
      </content>
      <guideline id="keyboard-accessible">
         <num>2.1</num>
         <name>Keyboard Accessible</name>
         <content>
            <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Make all functionality available from a keyboard.</p>
         </content>
         <file href="keyboard-accessible"/>
         <success-criterion id="keyboard">
            <num>2.1.1</num>
            <name>Keyboard</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All <a>functionality</a> of the content is operable through a <a>keyboard interface</a> without requiring specific timings for individual keystrokes, except where the underlying
      function requires input that depends on the path of the user's movement and not just
      the endpoints.
   </p>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">This exception relates to the underlying function, not the input technique. For example,
      if using handwriting to enter text, the input technique (handwriting) requires path-dependent
      input but the underlying function (text input) does not.
   </p>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">This does not forbid and should not discourage providing mouse input or other input
      methods in addition to keyboard operation.
   </p>
            </content>
            <level>A</level>
            <file href="keyboard"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="no-keyboard-trap">
            <num>2.1.2</num>
            <name>No Keyboard Trap</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">If keyboard focus can be moved to a component of the page using a <a>keyboard interface</a>, then focus can be moved away from that component using only a keyboard interface,
      and, if it requires more than unmodified arrow or tab keys or other standard exit
      methods, the user is advised of the method for moving focus away.
   </p>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Since any content that does not meet this success criterion can interfere with a user's
      ability to use the whole page, all content on the Web page (whether it is used to
      meet other success criteria or not) must meet this success criterion. See <a href="#cc5">Conformance Requirement 5: Non-Interference</a>.
   </p>
            </content>
            <level>A</level>
            <file href="no-keyboard-trap"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="keyboard-no-exception">
            <num>2.1.3</num>
            <name>Keyboard (No Exception)</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All <a>functionality</a> of the content is operable through a <a>keyboard interface</a> without requiring specific timings for individual keystrokes.
   </p>
            </content>
            <level>AAA</level>
            <file href="keyboard-no-exception"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="character-key-shortcuts">
            <num>2.1.4</num>
            <name>Character Key Shortcuts</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">If a <a>keyboard shortcut</a> is implemented in content using only letter (including upper- and lower-case letters), punctuation, number, or symbol characters, then at least one of the following is true:</p>
               <dl xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   
                  <dt>Turn off</dt>
                  <dd>A <a>mechanism</a> is available to turn the shortcut off;</dd>
      						
                  <dt>Remap</dt>
                  <dd>A mechanism is available to remap the shortcut to include one or more non-printable keyboard keys (e.g., Ctrl, Alt);</dd>

                  <dt>Active only on focus</dt>
                  <dd>The keyboard shortcut for a <a>user interface component</a> is only active when that component has focus.</dd>
    
               </dl>
            </content>
            <level>A</level>
            <file href="character-key-shortcuts"/>
         </success-criterion>
      </guideline>
      <guideline id="enough-time">
         <num>2.2</num>
         <name>Enough Time</name>
         <content>
            <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Provide users enough time to read and use content.</p>
         </content>
         <file href="enough-time"/>
         <success-criterion id="timing-adjustable">
            <num>2.2.1</num>
            <name>Timing Adjustable</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For each time limit that is set by the content, at least one of the following is true:</p>
               <dl xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      
                  <dt>Turn off</dt>
      
                  <dd>
         
                     <p>The user is allowed to turn off the time limit before encountering it; or</p>
         
                  </dd>
      
                  <dt>Adjust</dt>
      
                  <dd>
         
                     <p>The user is allowed to adjust the time limit before encountering it over a wide range
            that is at least ten times the length of the default setting; or
         </p>
         
                  </dd>
      
                  <dt>Extend</dt>
      
                  <dd>
         
                     <p>The user is warned before time expires and given at least 20 seconds to extend the
            time limit with a simple action (for example, "press the space bar"), and the user
            is allowed to extend the time limit at least ten times; or
         </p>
         
                  </dd>
      
                  <dt>Real-time Exception</dt>
      
                  <dd>
         
                     <p>The time limit is a required part of a real-time event (for example, an auction),
            and no alternative to the time limit is possible; or
         </p>
         
                  </dd>
      
                  <dt>Essential Exception</dt>
      
                  <dd>
         
                     <p>The time limit is <a>essential</a> and extending it would invalidate the activity; or
         </p>
         
                  </dd>
      
                  <dt>20 Hour Exception</dt>
      
                  <dd>
         
                     <p>The time limit is longer than 20 hours.</p>
         
                  </dd>
      
               </dl>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">This success criterion helps ensure that users can complete tasks without unexpected
      changes in content or context that are a result of a time limit. This success criterion
      should be considered in conjunction with <a href="#on-focus">Success Criterion 3.2.1</a>, which puts limits on changes of content or context as a result of user action.
   </p>
            </content>
            <level>A</level>
            <file href="timing-adjustable"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="pause-stop-hide">
            <num>2.2.2</num>
            <name>Pause, Stop, Hide</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For moving, <a>blinking</a>, scrolling, or auto-updating information, all of the following are true:
   </p>
               <dl xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      
                  <dt>Moving, blinking, scrolling</dt>
      
                  <dd>
         
                     <p>For any moving, blinking or scrolling information that (1) starts automatically, (2)
            lasts more than five seconds, and (3) is presented in parallel with other content,
            there is a mechanism for the user to <a>pause</a>, stop, or hide it unless the movement, blinking, or scrolling is part of an activity
            where it is <a>essential</a>; and
         </p>
         
                  </dd>
      
                  <dt>Auto-updating</dt>
      
                  <dd>
         
                     <p>For any auto-updating information that (1) starts automatically and (2) is presented
            in parallel with other content, there is a mechanism for the user to pause, stop,
            or hide it or to control the frequency of the update unless the auto-updating is part
            of an activity where it is essential.
         </p>
         
                  </dd>
      
               </dl>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">For requirements related to flickering or flashing content, refer to <a href="#seizures-and-physical-reactions">Guideline 2.3</a>.
   </p>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Since any content that does not meet this success criterion can interfere with a user's
      ability to use the whole page, all content on the Web page (whether it is used to
      meet other success criteria or not) must meet this success criterion. See <a href="#cc5">Conformance Requirement 5: Non-Interference</a>.
   </p>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Content that is updated periodically by software or that is streamed to the user agent
      is not required to preserve or present information that is generated or received between
      the initiation of the pause and resuming presentation, as this may not be technically
      possible, and in many situations could be misleading to do so.
   </p>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">An animation that occurs as part of a preload phase or similar situation can be considered
      essential if interaction cannot occur during that phase for all users and if not indicating
      progress could confuse users or cause them to think that content was frozen or broken.
   </p>
            </content>
            <level>A</level>
            <file href="pause-stop-hide"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="no-timing">
            <num>2.2.3</num>
            <name>No Timing</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Timing is not an <a>essential</a> part of the event or activity presented by the content, except for non-interactive
      <a>synchronized media</a> and <a>real-time events</a>.
   </p>
            </content>
            <level>AAA</level>
            <file href="no-timing"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="interruptions">
            <num>2.2.4</num>
            <name>Interruptions</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Interruptions can be postponed or suppressed by the user, except interruptions involving
      an <a>emergency</a>.
   </p>
            </content>
            <level>AAA</level>
            <file href="interruptions"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="re-authenticating">
            <num>2.2.5</num>
            <name>Re-authenticating</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When an authenticated session expires, the user can continue the activity without
      loss of data after re-authenticating.
   </p>
            </content>
            <level>AAA</level>
            <file href="re-authenticating"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="timeouts">
            <num>2.2.6</num>
            <name>Timeouts</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Users are warned of the duration of any <a>user inactivity</a> that could cause data loss, unless the data is preserved for more than 20 hours when the user does not take any actions.</p>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Privacy regulations may require explicit user consent before user identification has been authenticated and before user data is preserved. In cases where the user is a minor, explicit consent may not be solicited in most jurisdictions, countries or regions. Consultation with privacy professionals and legal counsel is advised when considering data preservation as an approach to satisfy this success criterion.</p>
            </content>
            <level>AAA</level>
            <file href="timeouts"/>
         </success-criterion>
      </guideline>
      <guideline id="seizures-and-physical-reactions">
         <num>2.3</num>
         <name>Seizures and Physical Reactions</name>
         <content>
            <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Do not design content in a way that is known to cause seizures or physical reactions.</p>
         </content>
         <file href="seizures-and-physical-reactions"/>
         <success-criterion id="three-flashes-or-below-threshold">
            <num>2.3.1</num>
            <name>Three Flashes or Below Threshold</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
                  <a>Web pages</a> do not contain anything that flashes more than three times in any one second period,
      or the <a>flash</a> is below the <a>general flash and red flash thresholds</a>.
   </p>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Since any content that does not meet this success criterion can interfere with a user's
      ability to use the whole page, all content on the Web page (whether it is used to
      meet other success criteria or not) must meet this success criterion. See <a href="#cc5">Conformance Requirement 5: Non-Interference</a>.
   </p>
            </content>
            <level>A</level>
            <file href="three-flashes-or-below-threshold"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="three-flashes">
            <num>2.3.2</num>
            <name>Three Flashes</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
                  <a>Web pages</a> do not contain anything that <a>flashes</a> more than three times in any one second period.
   </p>
            </content>
            <level>AAA</level>
            <file href="three-flashes"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="animation-from-interactions">
            <num>2.3.3</num>
            <name>Animation from Interactions</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
                  <a>Motion animation</a> triggered by interaction can be disabled, unless the animation is <a>essential</a> to the functionality or the information being conveyed.</p>
            </content>
            <level>AAA</level>
            <file href="animation-from-interactions"/>
         </success-criterion>
      </guideline>
      <guideline id="navigable">
         <num>2.4</num>
         <name>Navigable</name>
         <content>
            <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Provide ways to help users navigate, find content, and determine where they are.</p>
         </content>
         <file href="navigable"/>
         <success-criterion id="bypass-blocks">
            <num>2.4.1</num>
            <name>Bypass Blocks</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A <a>mechanism</a> is available to bypass blocks of content that are repeated on multiple <a>Web pages</a>.
   </p>
            </content>
            <level>A</level>
            <file href="bypass-blocks"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="page-titled">
            <num>2.4.2</num>
            <name>Page Titled</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
                  <a>Web pages</a> have titles that describe topic or purpose.
   </p>
            </content>
            <level>A</level>
            <file href="page-titled"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="focus-order">
            <num>2.4.3</num>
            <name>Focus Order</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">If a <a>Web page</a> can be <a>navigated sequentially</a> and the navigation sequences affect meaning or operation, focusable components receive
      focus in an order that preserves meaning and operability.
   </p>
            </content>
            <level>A</level>
            <file href="focus-order"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="link-purpose-in-context">
            <num>2.4.4</num>
            <name>Link Purpose (In Context)</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The <a>purpose of each link</a> can be determined from the link text alone or from the link text together with its
      <a>programmatically determined link context</a>, except where the purpose of the link would be <a>ambiguous to users in general</a>.
   </p>
            </content>
            <level>A</level>
            <file href="link-purpose-in-context"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="multiple-ways">
            <num>2.4.5</num>
            <name>Multiple Ways</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">More than one way is available to locate a <a>Web page</a> within a <a>set of Web pages</a> except where the Web Page is the result of, or a step in, a <a>process</a>.
   </p>
            </content>
            <level>AA</level>
            <file href="multiple-ways"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="headings-and-labels">
            <num>2.4.6</num>
            <name>Headings and Labels</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Headings and <a>labels</a> describe topic or purpose.
   </p>
            </content>
            <level>AA</level>
            <file href="headings-and-labels"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="focus-visible">
            <num>2.4.7</num>
            <name>Focus Visible</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Any keyboard operable user interface has a mode of operation where the keyboard focus
      indicator is visible.
   </p>
            </content>
            <level>AA</level>
            <file href="focus-visible"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="location">
            <num>2.4.8</num>
            <name>Location</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Information about the user's location within a <a>set of Web pages</a> is available.
   </p>
            </content>
            <level>AAA</level>
            <file href="location"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="link-purpose-link-only">
            <num>2.4.9</num>
            <name>Link Purpose (Link Only)</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A <a>mechanism</a> is available to allow the purpose of each link to be identified from link text alone,
      except where the purpose of the link would be <a>ambiguous to users in general</a>.
   </p>
            </content>
            <level>AAA</level>
            <file href="link-purpose-link-only"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="section-headings">
            <num>2.4.10</num>
            <name>Section Headings</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
                  <a>Section</a> headings are used to organize the content.
   </p>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">"Heading" is used in its general sense and includes titles and other ways to add a
      heading to different types of content.
   </p>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">This success criterion covers sections within writing, not <a>user interface components</a>. User Interface components are covered under <a href="#name-role-value">Success Criterion 4.1.2</a>.
   </p>
            </content>
            <level>AAA</level>
            <file href="section-headings"/>
         </success-criterion>
      </guideline>
      <guideline id="input-modalities">
         <num>2.5</num>
         <name>Input Modalities</name>
         <content>
            <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Make it easier for users to operate functionality through various inputs beyond keyboard.</p>
         </content>
         <file href="input-modalities"/>
         <success-criterion id="pointer-gestures">
            <num>2.5.1</num>
            <name>Pointer Gestures</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All <a>functionality</a> that uses multipoint or path-based gestures for operation can be operated with a <a>single pointer</a> without a path-based gesture, unless a multipoint or path-based gesture is <a>essential</a>.</p>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">This requirement applies to web content that interprets pointer actions (i.e. this does not apply to actions that are required to operate the user agent or assistive technology).</p>
            </content>
            <level>A</level>
            <file href="pointer-gestures"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="pointer-cancellation">
            <num>2.5.2</num>
            <name>Pointer Cancellation</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For <a>functionality</a> that can be operated using a <a>single pointer</a>, at least one of the following is true:</p>
               <dl xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   
                  <dt>No Down-Event</dt>
                  <dd>The <a>down-event</a> of the pointer is not used to execute any part of the function;</dd>
      						
                  <dt>Abort or Undo</dt>
                  <dd>Completion of the function is on the <a>up-event</a>, and a <a>mechanism</a> is available to abort the function before completion or to undo the function after completion;</dd>
      						
                  <dt>Up Reversal</dt>
                  <dd>The up-event reverses any outcome of the preceding down-event;</dd>
      						
                  <dt>Essential</dt>
                  <dd>Completing the function on the down-event is <a>essential</a>.</dd>
      						
               </dl>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Functions that emulate a keyboard or numeric keypad key press are considered essential.</p>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">This requirement applies to web content that interprets pointer actions (i.e. this does not apply to actions that are required to operate the user agent or assistive technology).</p>
            </content>
            <level>A</level>
            <file href="pointer-cancellation"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="label-in-name">
            <num>2.5.3</num>
            <name>Label in Name</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For <a>user interface components</a> with <a>labels</a> that include <a>text</a> or <a>images of text</a>, the <a>name</a> contains the text that is presented visually.</p>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">A best practice is to have  the text of the label at the start of the name.</p>
            </content>
            <level>A</level>
            <file href="label-in-name"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="motion-actuation">
            <num>2.5.4</num>
            <name>Motion Actuation</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
                  <a>Functionality</a> that can be operated by device motion or user motion can also be operated by <a>user interface components</a> and responding to the motion can be disabled to prevent accidental actuation, except when:</p>
               <dl xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   
                  <dt>Supported Interface</dt>
                  <dd>The motion is used to operate functionality through an <a>accessibility supported</a> interface;</dd>
   
                  <dt>Essential</dt>
                  <dd>The motion is <a>essential</a> for the function and doing so would invalidate the activity.</dd>
   
               </dl>
            </content>
            <level>A</level>
            <file href="motion-actuation"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="target-size">
            <num>2.5.5</num>
            <name>Target Size</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The size of the <a>target</a> for <a>pointer inputs</a> is at least 44 by 44 <a>CSS pixels</a> except when:</p>
               <dl xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
	                 <dt>Equivalent</dt> 
                  <dd>The target is available through an equivalent link or control on the same page that is at least 44 by 44 CSS pixels;</dd>
	                 <dt>Inline</dt> 
                  <dd>The target is in a sentence or block of text;</dd>
	                 <dt>User Agent Control</dt> 
                  <dd>The size of the target is determined by the user agent and is not modified by the author;</dd>
	                 <dt>Essential</dt> 
                  <dd>A particular presentation of the target is <a>essential</a> to the information being conveyed.</dd>
               </dl>
            </content>
            <level>AAA</level>
            <file href="target-size"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="concurrent-input-mechanisms">
            <num>2.5.6</num>
            <name>Concurrent Input Mechanisms</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Web content does not restrict use of input modalities available on a platform except where the restriction is <a>essential</a>, required to ensure the security of the content, or required to respect user settings.</p>
            </content>
            <level>AAA</level>
            <file href="concurrent-input-mechanisms"/>
         </success-criterion>
      </guideline>
   </principle>
   <principle id="understandable">
      <version>WCAG20</version>
      <num>3</num>
      <name> Understandable </name>
      <content>
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Information and the operation of the user interface must be understandable.</p>
      </content>
      <guideline id="readable">
         <num>3.1</num>
         <name>Readable</name>
         <content>
            <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Make text content readable and understandable.</p>
         </content>
         <file href="readable"/>
         <success-criterion id="language-of-page">
            <num>3.1.1</num>
            <name>Language of Page</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The default <a>human language</a> of each <a>Web page</a> can be <a>programmatically determined</a>.
   </p>
            </content>
            <level>A</level>
            <file href="language-of-page"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="language-of-parts">
            <num>3.1.2</num>
            <name>Language of Parts</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The <a>human language</a> of each passage or phrase in the content can be <a>programmatically determined</a> except for proper names, technical terms, words of indeterminate language, and words
      or phrases that have become part of the vernacular of the immediately surrounding
      text.
   </p>
            </content>
            <level>AA</level>
            <file href="language-of-parts"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="unusual-words">
            <num>3.1.3</num>
            <name>Unusual Words</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A <a>mechanism</a> is available for identifying specific definitions of words or phrases <a>used in an unusual or restricted way</a>, including <a>idioms</a> and <a>jargon</a>.
   </p>
            </content>
            <level>AAA</level>
            <file href="unusual-words"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="abbreviations">
            <num>3.1.4</num>
            <name>Abbreviations</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A <a>mechanism</a> for identifying the expanded form or meaning of <a>abbreviations</a> is available.
   </p>
            </content>
            <level>AAA</level>
            <file href="abbreviations"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="reading-level">
            <num>3.1.5</num>
            <name>Reading Level</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When text requires reading ability more advanced than the <a>lower secondary education level</a> after removal of proper names and titles, <a>supplemental content</a>, or a version that does not require reading ability more advanced than the lower
      secondary education level, is available.
   </p>
            </content>
            <level>AAA</level>
            <file href="reading-level"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="pronunciation">
            <num>3.1.6</num>
            <name>Pronunciation</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A <a>mechanism</a> is available for identifying specific pronunciation of words where meaning of the
      words, in context, is ambiguous without knowing the pronunciation.
   </p>
            </content>
            <level>AAA</level>
            <file href="pronunciation"/>
         </success-criterion>
      </guideline>
      <guideline id="predictable">
         <num>3.2</num>
         <name>Predictable</name>
         <content>
            <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Make Web pages appear and operate in predictable ways.</p>
         </content>
         <file href="predictable"/>
         <success-criterion id="on-focus">
            <num>3.2.1</num>
            <name>On Focus</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When any <a>user interface component</a> receives focus, it does not initiate a <a>change of context</a>.
   </p>
            </content>
            <level>A</level>
            <file href="on-focus"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="on-input">
            <num>3.2.2</num>
            <name>On Input</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Changing the setting of any <a>user interface component</a> does not automatically cause a <a>change of context</a> unless the user has been advised of the behavior before using the component.
   </p>
            </content>
            <level>A</level>
            <file href="on-input"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="consistent-navigation">
            <num>3.2.3</num>
            <name>Consistent Navigation</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Navigational mechanisms that are repeated on multiple <a>Web pages</a> within a <a>set of Web pages</a> occur in the <a>same relative order</a> each time they are repeated, unless a change is initiated by the user.
   </p>
            </content>
            <level>AA</level>
            <file href="consistent-navigation"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="consistent-identification">
            <num>3.2.4</num>
            <name>Consistent Identification</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Components that have the <a>same functionality</a> within a <a>set of Web pages</a> are identified consistently.
   </p>
            </content>
            <level>AA</level>
            <file href="consistent-identification"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="change-on-request">
            <num>3.2.5</num>
            <name>Change on Request</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
                  <a>Changes of context</a> are initiated only by user request or a <a>mechanism</a> is available to turn off such changes.
   </p>
            </content>
            <level>AAA</level>
            <file href="change-on-request"/>
         </success-criterion>
      </guideline>
      <guideline id="input-assistance">
         <num>3.3</num>
         <name>Input Assistance</name>
         <content>
            <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Help users avoid and correct mistakes.</p>
         </content>
         <file href="input-assistance"/>
         <success-criterion id="error-identification">
            <num>3.3.1</num>
            <name>Error Identification</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">If an <a>input error</a> is automatically detected, the item that is in error is identified and the error
      is described to the user in text.
   </p>
            </content>
            <level>A</level>
            <file href="error-identification"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="labels-or-instructions">
            <num>3.3.2</num>
            <name>Labels or Instructions</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
                  <a>Labels</a> or instructions are provided when content requires user input.
   </p>
            </content>
            <level>A</level>
            <file href="labels-or-instructions"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="error-suggestion">
            <num>3.3.3</num>
            <name>Error Suggestion</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">If an <a>input error</a> is automatically detected and suggestions for correction are known, then the suggestions
      are provided to the user, unless it would jeopardize the security or purpose of the
      content.
   </p>
            </content>
            <level>AA</level>
            <file href="error-suggestion"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="error-prevention-legal-financial-data">
            <num>3.3.4</num>
            <name>Error Prevention (Legal, Financial, Data)</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For <a>Web pages</a> that cause <a>legal commitments</a> or financial transactions for the user to occur, that modify or delete <a>user-controllable</a> data in data storage systems, or that submit user test responses, at least one of
      the following is true:
   </p>
               <dl xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
                  <dt>Reversible</dt>
                  <dd>Submissions are reversible.</dd>
                  <dt>Checked</dt>
                  <dd>Data entered by the user is checked for input errors and the user is provided an opportunity to correct them.</dd>
                  <dt>Confirmed</dt>
                  <dd>A mechanism is available for reviewing, confirming, and correcting information before finalizing the submission.</dd>
               </dl>
            </content>
            <level>AA</level>
            <file href="error-prevention-legal-financial-data"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="help">
            <num>3.3.5</num>
            <name>Help</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
                  <a>Context-sensitive help</a> is available.
   </p>
            </content>
            <level>AAA</level>
            <file href="help"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="error-prevention-all">
            <num>3.3.6</num>
            <name>Error Prevention (All)</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For <a>Web pages</a> that require the user to submit information, at least one of the following is true:
   </p>
               <dl xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
                  <dt>Reversible</dt>
                  <dd>Submissions are reversible.</dd>
                  <dt>Checked</dt>
                  <dd>Data entered by the user is checked for input errors and the user is provided an opportunity to correct them.</dd>
                  <dt>Confirmed</dt>
                  <dd>A mechanism is available for reviewing, confirming, and correcting information before finalizing the submission.</dd>
               </dl>
            </content>
            <level>AAA</level>
            <file href="error-prevention-all"/>
         </success-criterion>
      </guideline>
   </principle>
   <principle id="robust">
      <version>WCAG20</version>
      <num>4</num>
      <name> Robust </name>
      <content>
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Content must be robust enough that it can be interpreted by a wide variety of user
            agents, including assistive technologies.
         </p>
      </content>
      <guideline id="compatible">
         <num>4.1</num>
         <name>Compatible</name>
         <content>
            <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Maximize compatibility with current and future user agents, including assistive technologies.</p>
         </content>
         <file href="compatible"/>
         <success-criterion id="parsing">
            <num>4.1.1</num>
            <name>Parsing</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In content implemented using markup languages, elements have complete start and end
      tags, elements are nested according to their specifications, elements do not contain
      duplicate attributes, and any IDs are unique, except where the specifications allow
      these features.
   </p>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Start and end tags that are missing a critical character in their formation, such
      as a closing angle bracket or a mismatched attribute value quotation mark are not
      complete.
   </p>
            </content>
            <level>A</level>
            <file href="parsing"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="name-role-value">
            <num>4.1.2</num>
            <name>Name, Role, Value</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For all <a>user interface components</a> (including but not limited to: form elements, links and components generated by scripts),
      the <a>name</a> and <a>role</a> can be <a>programmatically determined</a>; states, properties, and values that can be set by the user can be <a>programmatically set</a>; and notification of changes to these items is available to <a>user agents</a>, including <a>assistive technologies</a>.
   </p>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">This success criterion is primarily for Web authors who develop or script their own
      user interface components. For example, standard HTML controls already meet this success
      criterion when used according to specification.
   </p>
            </content>
            <level>A</level>
            <file href="name-role-value"/>
         </success-criterion>
         <success-criterion id="status-messages">
            <num>4.1.3</num>
            <name>Status Messages</name>
            <content>
               <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In content implemented using markup languages, <a>status messages</a> can be <a>programmatically determined</a> through <a>role</a> or properties such that they can be presented to the user by <a>assistive technologies</a> without receiving focus.</p>
            </content>
            <level>AA</level>
            <file href="status-messages"/>
         </success-criterion>
      </guideline>
   </principle>
   <understanding>
      <name>Understanding Conformance</name>
      <file href="conformance"/>
   </understanding>
   <understanding>
      <name>How to Refer to WCAG 2.1 from Other Documents</name>
      <file href="refer-to-wcag"/>
   </understanding>
   <understanding>
      <name>Documenting Accessibility Support for Uses of a Web Technology</name>
      <file href="documenting-accessibility-support"/>
   </understanding>
   <understanding>
      <name>Understanding Metadata</name>
      <file href="understanding-metadata"/>
   </understanding>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-abbreviation</id>
      <name>abbreviation</name>
      <name>abbreviations</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">shortened form of a word, phrase, or name where the abbreviation has not become part
      of the language
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">This includes initialisms and acronyms where:</p>
   
         <ol xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      
            <li>
         
               <p>
                  <strong>initialisms</strong> are shortened forms of a name or phrase made from the initial letters of words or
            syllables contained in that name or phrase
         </p>
         
               <p class="note">Not defined in all languages.</p>
         
               <p class="example">SNCF is a French initialism that contains the initial letters of the <span lang="fr">Socit Nationale des Chemins de Fer</span>, the French national railroad.
         </p>
         
               <p class="example">ESP is an initialism for extrasensory perception.</p>
         
            </li>
      
            <li>
         
               <p>
                  <strong>acronyms</strong> are abbreviated forms made from the initial letters or parts of other words (in a
            name or phrase) which may be pronounced as a word
         </p>
         
               <p class="example">NOAA is an acronym made from the initial letters of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric
            Administration in the United States.
         </p>
         
            </li>
      
         </ol>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Some companies have adopted what used to be an initialism as their company name. In
      these cases, the new name of the company is the letters (for example, Ecma) and the
      word is no longer considered an abbreviation.
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-accessibility-supported</id>
      <name>accessibility supported</name>
      <name>accessibility-supported</name>
      <name>accessibility support</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">supported by users' <a>assistive technologies</a> as well as the accessibility features in browsers and other <a>user agents</a>
         </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To qualify as an accessibility-supported use of a Web content technology (or feature
      of a technology), both 1 and 2 must be satisfied for a Web content technology (or
      feature):
   </p>
   
         <ol xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      
            <li>
         
               <p>
                  <strong>The way that the <a>Web content technology</a> is used must be supported by users' assistive technology (AT). </strong> This means that the way that the technology is used has been tested for interoperability
            with users' assistive technology in the <a>human language(s)</a> of the content,
         </p>
         
               <p>
                  <strong>AND</strong>
               </p>
         
            </li>
      
            <li>
         
               <p>
                  <strong>The Web content technology must have accessibility-supported user agents that are
               available to users. </strong> This means that at least one of the following four statements is true:
         </p>
         
               <ol>
            
                  <li>
               
                     <p>The technology is supported natively in widely-distributed user agents that are also
                  accessibility supported (such as HTML and CSS);
               </p>
               
                     <p>
                        <strong>OR</strong>
                     </p>
                  </li>
            
                  <li>
                     <p>The technology is supported in a widely-distributed plug-in that is also accessibility
                  supported;
               </p>
               
                     <p>
                        <strong>OR</strong>
                     </p>
                  </li>
            
                  <li>
                     <p>The content is available in a closed environment, such as a university or corporate
                  network, where the user agent required by the technology and used by the organization
                  is also accessibility supported;
               </p>
               
                     <p>
                        <strong>OR</strong>
                     </p>
                  </li>
            
                  <li>
                     <p>The user agent(s) that support the technology are accessibility supported and are
                  available for download or purchase in a way that:
               </p>
               
                     <ul>
                  
                        <li>does not cost a person with a disability any more than a person without a disability
                     <strong>and</strong>
                        </li>
                  
                        <li>is as easy to find and obtain for a person with a disability as it is for a person
                     without disabilities.
                  </li>
                  
                     </ul>
               
                  </li>
            
               </ol>
         
            </li>
      
         </ol>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">The Accessibility Guidelines Working Group and the W3C do not specify which or how much support by assistive
      technologies there must be for a particular use of a Web technology in order for it
      to be classified as accessibility supported. (See <a href="https://www.w3.org/WAI/WCAG21/Understanding/conformance#support-level">Level of Assistive Technology Support Needed for "Accessibility Support"</a>.)
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Web technologies can be used in ways that are not accessibility supported as long
      as they are not <a>relied upon</a> and the page as a whole meets the conformance requirements, including <a href="#cc4">Conformance Criterion 4</a> and <a href="#cc5">Conformance Criterion 5</a>, are met.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">When a <a>Web Technology</a> is used in a way that is "accessibility supported," it does not imply that the entire
      technology or all uses of the technology are supported. Most technologies, including
      HTML, lack support for at least one feature or use. Pages conform to WCAG only if
      the uses of the technology that are accessibility supported can be relied upon to
      meet WCAG requirements.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">When citing Web content technologies that have multiple versions, the version(s) supported
      should be specified.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">One way for authors to locate uses of a technology that are accessibility supported
      would be to consult compilations of uses that are documented to be accessibility supported.
      (See <a href="https://www.w3.org/WAI/WCAG21/Understanding/conformance#documented-lists">Understanding Accessibility-Supported Web Technology Uses</a>.) Authors, companies, technology vendors, or others may document accessibility-supported
      ways of using Web content technologies. However, all ways of using technologies in
      the documentation would need to meet the definition of accessibility-supported Web
      content technologies above.
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-alternative-for-time-based-media</id>
      <name>alternative for time-based media</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">document including correctly sequenced text descriptions of time-based visual and
      auditory information and providing a means for achieving the outcomes of any time-based
      interaction
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">A screenplay used to create the synchronized media content would meet this definition
      only if it was corrected to accurately represent the final synchronized media after
      editing.
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-ambiguous-to-users-in-general</id>
      <name>ambiguous to users in general</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">the purpose cannot be determined from the link and all information of the Web page
      presented to the user simultaneously with the link (i.e., readers without disabilities
      would not know what a link would do until they activated it)
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="example">The word guava in the following sentence "One of the notable exports is guava" is
      a link. The link could lead to a definition of guava, a chart listing the quantity
      of guava exported or a photograph of people harvesting guava. Until the link is activated,
      all readers are unsure and the person with a disability is not at any disadvantage.
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-ascii-art</id>
      <name>ascii art</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">picture created by a spatial arrangement of characters or glyphs (typically from the
      95 printable characters defined by ASCII)
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-assistive-technology</id>
      <name>assistive technology</name>
      <name>assistive technologies</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">hardware and/or software that acts as a <a>user agent</a>, or along with a mainstream user agent, to provide functionality to meet the requirements
      of users with disabilities that go beyond those offered by mainstream user agents
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">functionality provided by assistive technology includes alternative presentations
      (e.g., as synthesized speech or magnified content), alternative input methods (e.g.,
      voice), additional navigation or orientation mechanisms, and content transformations
      (e.g., to make tables more accessible).
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Assistive technologies often communicate data and messages with mainstream user agents
      by using and monitoring APIs.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">The distinction between mainstream user agents and assistive technologies is not absolute.
      Many mainstream user agents provide some features to assist individuals with disabilities.
      The basic difference is that mainstream user agents target broad and diverse audiences
      that usually include people with and without disabilities. Assistive technologies
      target narrowly defined populations of users with specific disabilities. The assistance
      provided by an assistive technology is more specific and appropriate to the needs
      of its target users. The mainstream user agent may provide important functionality
      to assistive technologies like retrieving Web content from program objects or parsing
      markup into identifiable bundles.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="example">Assistive technologies that are important in the context of this document include
      the following:
   </p>
   
         <ul xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      
            <li>screen magnifiers, and other visual reading assistants, which are used by people with
         visual, perceptual and physical print disabilities to change text font, size, spacing,
         color, synchronization with speech, etc. in order to improve the visual readability
         of rendered text and images;
      </li>
      
            <li>screen readers, which are used by people who are blind to read textual information
         through synthesized speech or braille;
      </li>
      
            <li>text-to-speech software, which is used by some people with cognitive, language, and
         learning disabilities to convert text into synthetic speech;
      </li>
      
            <li>speech recognition software, which may be used by people who have some physical disabilities;</li>
      
            <li>alternative keyboards, which are used by people with certain physical disabilities
         to simulate the keyboard (including alternate keyboards that use head pointers, single
         switches, sip/puff and other special input devices.);
      </li>
      
            <li>alternative pointing devices, which are used by people with certain physical disabilities
         to simulate mouse pointing and button activations.
      </li>
      
         </ul>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-audio</id>
      <name>audio</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">the technology of sound reproduction</p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Audio can be created synthetically (including speech synthesis), recorded from real
      world sounds, or both.
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-audio-description</id>
      <name>audio description</name>
      <name>audio descriptions</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">narration added to the soundtrack to describe important visual details that cannot
      be understood from the main soundtrack alone
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Audio description of <a>video</a> provides information about actions, characters, scene changes, on-screen text, and
      other visual content.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">In standard audio description, narration is added during existing pauses in dialogue.
      (See also <a>extended audio description</a>.)
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Where all of the <a>video</a> information is already provided in existing <a>audio</a>, no additional audio description is necessary.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Also called "video description" and "descriptive narration."</p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-audio-only</id>
      <name>audio-only</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">a time-based presentation that contains only <a>audio</a> (no <a>video</a> and no interaction)
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-blinking</id>
      <name>blinking</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">switch back and forth between two visual states in a way that is meant to draw attention</p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">See also <a>flash</a>. It is possible for something to be large enough and blink brightly enough at the
      right frequency to be also classified as a flash.
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-blocks-of-text</id>
      <name>blocks of text</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">more than one sentence of text</p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-captcha</id>
      <name>captcha</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">initialism for "Completely Automated Public Turing test to tell Computers and Humans
      Apart"
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">CAPTCHA tests often involve asking the user to type in text that is displayed in an
      obscured image or audio file.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">A Turing test is any system of tests designed to differentiate a human from a computer.
      It is named after famed computer scientist Alan Turing. The term was coined by researchers
      at Carnegie Mellon University.
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-captions</id>
      <name>captions</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">synchronized visual and/or <a>text alternative</a> for both speech and non-speech audio information needed to understand the media content
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Captions are similar to dialogue-only subtitles except captions convey not only the
      content of spoken dialogue, but also equivalents for non-dialogue audio information
      needed to understand the program content, including sound effects, music, laughter,
      speaker identification and location.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Closed Captions are equivalents that can be turned on and off with some players.</p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Open Captions are any captions that cannot be turned off. For example, if the captions
      are visual equivalent <a>images of text</a> embedded in <a>video</a>.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Captions should not obscure or obstruct relevant information in the video.</p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">In some countries, captions are called subtitles.</p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">
            <a>Audio descriptions</a> can be, but do not need to be, captioned since they are descriptions of information
      that is already presented visually.
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-changes-of-context</id>
      <name>changes of context</name>
      <name>change of context</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">major changes in the content of the <a>Web page</a> that, if made without user awareness, can disorient users who are not able to view
      the entire page simultaneously
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Changes in context include changes of:</p>
   
         <ol xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      
            <li>
               <a>user agent</a>;
      </li>
      
            <li>
               <a>viewport</a>;
      </li>
      
            <li>focus;</li>
      
            <li>
               <a>content</a> that changes the meaning of the <a>Web page</a>
            </li>
      
         </ol>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">A change of content is not always a change of context. Changes in content, such as
      an expanding outline, dynamic menu, or a tab control do not necessarily change the
      context, unless they also change one of the above (e.g., focus).
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="example">Opening a new window, moving focus to a different component, going to a new page (including
      anything that would look to a user as if they had moved to a new page) or significantly
      re-arranging the content of a page are examples of changes of context.
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-conformance</id>
      <name>conformance</name>
      <name>conform</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">satisfying all the requirements of a given standard, guideline or specification</p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-conforming-alternate-version</id>
      <name>conforming alternate version</name>
      <name>conforming alternate versions</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">version that</p>
   
         <ol xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      
            <li>conforms at the designated level, and</li>
      
            <li>provides all of the same information and <a>functionality</a> in the same <a>human language</a>, and
      </li>
      
            <li>is as up to date as the non-conforming content, and</li>
      
            <li>
               <p>for which at least one of the following is true:</p>
         
               <ol>
            
                  <li>the conforming version can be reached from the non-conforming page via an <a>accessibility-supported</a>
                     <a>mechanism</a>, or
            </li>
            
                  <li>the non-conforming version can only be reached from the conforming version, or</li>
            
                  <li>the non-conforming version can only be reached from a conforming page that also provides
               a mechanism to reach the conforming version
            </li>
            
               </ol>
         
            </li>
      
         </ol>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">In this definition, "can only be reached" means that there is some mechanism, such
      as a conditional redirect, that prevents a user from "reaching" (loading) the non-conforming
      page unless the user had just come from the conforming version.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">The alternate version does not need to be matched page for page with the original
      (e.g., the conforming alternate version may consist of multiple pages).
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">If multiple language versions are available, then conforming alternate versions are
      required for each language offered.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Alternate versions may be provided to accommodate different technology environments
      or user groups. Each version should be as conformant as possible. One version would
      need to be fully conformant in order to meet <a href="#cc1">conformance requirement 1</a>.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">The conforming alternative version does not need to reside within the scope of conformance,
      or even on the same Web site, as long as it is as freely available as the non-conforming
      version.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Alternate versions should not be confused with <a>supplementary content</a>, which support the original page and enhance comprehension.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Setting user preferences within the content to produce a conforming version is an
      acceptable mechanism for reaching another version as long as the method used to set
      the preferences is accessibility supported.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">See <a href="https://www.w3.org/WAI/WCAG21/Understanding/conformance#conforming-alt-versions">Understanding Conforming Alternate Versions</a>
         </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-content</id>
      <name>content</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">information and sensory experience to be communicated to the user by means of a <a>user agent</a>, including code or markup that defines the content's <a>structure</a>, <a>presentation</a>, and interactions
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-context-sensitive-help</id>
      <name>context-sensitive help</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">help text that provides information related to the function currently being performed</p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Clear labels can act as context-sensitive help.</p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-contrast-ratio</id>
      <name>contrast ratio</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(L1 + 0.05) / (L2 + 0.05), where</p>
   
         <ul xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      
            <li>L1 is the <a>relative luminance</a> of the lighter of the colors, and
      </li>
      
            <li>L2 is the <a>relative luminance</a> of the darker of the colors.
      </li>
      
         </ul>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Contrast ratios can range from 1 to 21 (commonly written 1:1 to 21:1).</p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Because authors do not have control over user settings as to how text is rendered
      (for example font smoothing or anti-aliasing), the contrast ratio for text can be
      evaluated with anti-aliasing turned off.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">For the purpose of Success Criteria 1.4.3 and 1.4.6, contrast is measured with respect
      to the specified background over which the text is rendered in normal usage. If no
      background color is specified, then white is assumed.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Background color is the specified color of content over which the text is to be rendered
      in normal usage. It is a failure if no background color is specified when the text
      color is specified, because the user's default background color is unknown and cannot
      be evaluated for sufficient contrast. For the same reason, it is a failure if no text
      color is specified when a background color is specified.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">When there is a border around the letter, the border can add contrast and would be
      used in calculating the contrast between the letter and its background. A narrow border
      around the letter would be used as the letter. A wide border around the letter that
      fills in the inner details of the letters acts as a halo and would be considered background.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">WCAG conformance should be evaluated for color pairs specified in the content that
      an author would expect to appear adjacent in typical presentation. Authors need not
      consider unusual presentations, such as color changes made by the user agent, except
      where caused by authors' code.
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-correct-reading-sequence</id>
      <name>correct reading sequence</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">any sequence where words and paragraphs are presented in an order that does not change
      the meaning of the content
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-css-pixel</id>
      <name>css pixel</name>
      <name>css pixels</name>
      <definition>
   					
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">visual angle of about 0.0213 degrees</p>
   					
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A CSS pixel is the canonical unit of measure for all lengths and measurements in CSS.
      This unit is density-independent, and distinct from actual hardware pixels present
      in a display. User agents and operating systems should ensure that a CSS pixel is
      set as closely as possible to the <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/css3-values/#reference-pixel">CSS Values and Units Module Level 3 reference pixel</a> [[!css3-values]], which takes into account the physical dimensions of the display
      and the assumed viewing distance (factors that cannot be determined by content authors).
   </p>
   				
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-down-event</id>
      <name>down-event</name>
      <definition>
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">platform event that occurs  when the trigger stimulus of a pointer is depressed</p>
	        <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The down-event may have different names on different platforms, such as "touchstart" or "mousedown".</p>
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-emergency</id>
      <name>emergency</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">a sudden, unexpected situation or occurrence that requires immediate action to preserve
      health, safety, or property
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-essential</id>
      <name>essential</name>
      <definition>
   					
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">if removed, would fundamentally change the information or functionality of the content,
      <strong>and</strong> information and functionality cannot be achieved in another way that would conform
   </p>
   				
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-extended-audio-description</id>
      <name>extended audio description</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">audio description that is added to an audiovisual presentation by pausing the <a>video</a> so that there is time to add additional description
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">This technique is only used when the sense of the <a>video</a> would be lost without the additional <a>audio description</a> and the pauses between dialogue/narration are too short.
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-flash</id>
      <name>flash</name>
      <name>flashes</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">a pair of opposing changes in <a>relative luminance</a> that can cause seizures in some people if it is large enough and in the right frequency
      range
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">See <a>general flash and red flash thresholds</a> for information about types of flash that are not allowed.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">See also <a>blinking</a>.
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-functionality</id>
      <name>functionality</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
            <a>processes</a> and outcomes achievable through user action
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-general-flash-and-red-flash-thresholds</id>
      <name>general flash and red flash thresholds</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">a <a>flash</a> or rapidly changing image sequence is below the threshold (i.e., content <strong>passes</strong>) if any of the following are true:
   </p>
   
         <ol xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      
            <li>there are no more than three <strong>general flashes</strong> and / or no more than three <strong>red flashes</strong> within any one-second period; or
      </li>
      
            <li>the combined area of flashes occurring concurrently occupies no more than a total
         of .006 steradians within any 10 degree visual field on the screen (25% of any 10
         degree visual field on the screen) at typical viewing distance
      </li>
      
         </ol>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">where:</p>
   
         <ul xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      
            <li>A <strong>general flash</strong> is defined as a pair of opposing changes in <a>relative luminance</a> of 10% or more of the maximum relative luminance where the relative luminance of
         the darker image is below 0.80; and where "a pair of opposing changes" is an increase
         followed by a decrease, or a decrease followed by an increase, and
      </li>
      
            <li>A <strong>red flash</strong> is defined as any pair of opposing transitions involving a saturated red
      </li>
      
         </ul>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
            <em>Exception:</em> Flashing that is a fine, balanced, pattern such as white noise or an alternating
      checkerboard pattern with "squares" smaller than 0.1 degree (of visual field at typical
      viewing distance) on a side does not violate the thresholds.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">For general software or Web content, using a 341 x 256 pixel rectangle anywhere on
      the displayed screen area when the content is viewed at 1024 x 768 pixels will provide
      a good estimate of a 10 degree visual field for standard screen sizes and viewing
      distances (e.g., 15-17 inch screen at 22-26 inches). (Higher resolutions displays
      showing the same rendering of the content yield smaller and safer images so it is
      lower resolutions that are used to define the thresholds.)
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">A transition is the change in relative luminance (or relative luminance/color for
      red flashing) between adjacent peaks and valleys in a plot of relative luminance (or
      relative luminance/color for red flashing) measurement against time. A flash consists
      of two opposing transitions.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">The current working definition in the field for <strong>"pair of opposing transitions involving a saturated red"</strong> is where, for either or both states involved in each transition, R/(R+ G + B) &gt;=
      0.8, and the change in the value of (R-G-B)x320 is &gt; 20 (negative values of (R-G-B)x320
      are set to zero) for both transitions. R, G, B values range from 0-1 as specified
      in relative luminance definition. [[HARDING-BINNIE]]
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Tools are available that will carry out analysis from video screen capture. However,
      no tool is necessary to evaluate for this condition if flashing is less than or equal
      to 3 flashes in any one second. Content automatically passes (see #1 and #2 above).
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-human-language</id>
      <name>human language</name>
      <name>human language(s)</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">language that is spoken, written or signed (through visual or tactile means) to communicate
      with humans
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">See also <a>sign language</a>.
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-idiom</id>
      <name>idiom</name>
      <name>idioms</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">phrase whose meaning cannot be deduced from the meaning of the individual words and
      the specific words cannot be changed without losing the meaning
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">idioms cannot be translated directly, word for word, without losing their (cultural
      or language-dependent) meaning.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="example">In English, "spilling the beans" means "revealing a secret." However, "knocking over
      the beans" or "spilling the vegetables" does not mean the same thing.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="example">In Japanese, the phrase "<span lang="ja"></span>" literally translates into "he throws a spoon," but it means that there is nothing
      he can do and finally he gives up.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="example">In Dutch, "<span lang="nl">Hij ging met de kippen op stok</span>" literally translates into "He went to roost with the chickens," but it means that
      he went to bed early.
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-image-of-text</id>
      <name>image of text</name>
      <name>images of text</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">text that has been rendered in a non-text form (e.g., an image) in order to achieve
      a particular visual effect
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">This does not include <a>text</a> that is part of a picture that contains significant other visual content.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="example">A person's name on a nametag in a photograph.</p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-informative</id>
      <name>informative</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">for information purposes and not required for conformance</p>
  
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Content required for <a>conformance</a> is referred to as "<a>normative</a>."</p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-input-error</id>
      <name>input error</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">information provided by the user that is not accepted</p>
   
         <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">
            <p>This includes:</p>
   
            <ol>
      
               <li>Information that is required by the <a>Web page</a> but omitted by the user
      </li>
      
               <li>Information that is provided by the user but that falls outside the required data
         format or values
      </li>
      
            </ol>
         </div>
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-jargon</id>
      <name>jargon</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">words used in a particular way by people in a particular field</p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="example">The word StickyKeys is jargon from the field of assistive technology/accessibility.</p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-keyboard-interface</id>
      <name>keyboard interface</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">interface used by software to obtain keystroke input</p>
   
         <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">
            <p>A keyboard interface allows users to provide keystroke input to programs even if the
        native technology does not contain a keyboard.</p>

            <p class="example">A touchscreen PDA has a keyboard interface built into its operating system as well
        as a connector for external keyboards. Applications on the PDA can use the interface
        to obtain keyboard input either from an external keyboard or from other applications
        that provide simulated keyboard output, such as handwriting interpreters or speech-to-text
        applications with "keyboard emulation" functionality.</p>
         </div>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Operation of the application (or parts of the application) through a keyboard-operated
      mouse emulator, such as MouseKeys, does not qualify as operation through a keyboard
      interface because operation of the program is through its pointing device interface,
      not through its keyboard interface.
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-keyboard-shortcut</id>
      <name>keyboard shortcut</name>
      <name>keyboard shortcuts</name>
      <definition>
   					
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">alternative means of triggering an action by the pressing of one or more keys</p>
   				
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-label</id>
      <name>label</name>
      <name>labels</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
            <a>text</a> or other component with a <a>text alternative</a> that is presented to a user to identify a component within Web <a>content</a>
         </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">A label is presented to all users whereas the <a>name</a> may be hidden and only exposed by assistive technology. In many (but not all) cases
      the name and the label are the same.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">The term label is not limited to the label element in HTML.</p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-large-scale</id>
      <name>large scale</name>
      <name>large-scale</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">with at least 18 point or 14 point bold or font size that would yield equivalent size
      for Chinese, Japanese and Korean (CJK) fonts
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Fonts with extraordinarily thin strokes or unusual features and characteristics that
      reduce the familiarity of their letter forms are harder to read, especially at lower
      contrast levels.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Font size is the size when the content is delivered. It does not include resizing
      that may be done by a user.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">The actual size of the character that a user sees is dependent both on the author-defined
      size and the user's display or user-agent settings. For many mainstream body text
      fonts, 14 and 18 point is roughly equivalent to 1.2 and 1.5 em or to 120% or 150%
      of the default size for body text (assuming that the body font is 100%), but authors
      would need to check this for the particular fonts in use. When fonts are defined in
      relative units, the actual point size is calculated by the user agent for display.
      The point size should be obtained from the user agent, or calculated based on font
      metrics as the user agent does, when evaluating this success criterion. Users who
      have low vision would be responsible for choosing appropriate settings.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">When using text without specifying the font size, the smallest font size used on major
      browsers for unspecified text would be a reasonable size to assume for the font. If
      a level 1 heading is rendered in 14pt bold or higher on major browsers, then it would
      be reasonable to assume it is large text. Relative scaling can be calculated from
      the default sizes in a similar fashion.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">The 18 and 14 point sizes for roman texts are taken from the minimum size for large
      print (14pt) and the larger standard font size (18pt). For other fonts such as CJK
      languages, the "equivalent" sizes would be the minimum large print size used for those
      languages and the next larger standard large print size.
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-legal-commitments</id>
      <name>legal commitments</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">transactions where the person incurs a legally binding obligation or benefit</p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="example">A marriage license, a stock trade (financial and legal), a will, a loan, adoption,
      signing up for the army, a contract of any type, etc.
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-link-purpose</id>
      <name>link purpose</name>
      <name>purpose of each link</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">nature of the result obtained by activating a hyperlink</p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-live</id>
      <name>live</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">information captured from a real-world event and transmitted to the receiver with
      no more than a broadcast delay
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">A broadcast delay is a short (usually automated) delay, for example used in order
      to give the broadcaster time to cue or censor the audio (or video) feed, but not sufficient
      to allow significant editing.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">If information is completely computer generated, it is not live.</p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-lower-secondary-education-level</id>
      <name>lower secondary education level</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">the two or three year period of education that begins after completion of six years
      of school and ends nine years after the beginning of <a>primary education</a>
         </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">This definition is based on the International Standard Classification of Education
      [[UNESCO]].
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-mechanism</id>
      <name>mechanism</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
            <a>process</a> or technique for achieving a result
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">The mechanism may be explicitly provided in the content, or may be <a>relied upon</a> to be provided by either the platform or by <a>user agents</a>, including <a>assistive technologies</a>.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">The mechanism needs to meet all success criteria for the conformance level claimed.</p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-media-alternative-for-text</id>
      <name>media alternative for text</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">media that presents no more information than is already presented in text (directly
      or via text alternatives)
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">A media alternative for text is provided for those who benefit from alternate representations
      of text. Media alternatives for text may be audio-only, video-only (including sign-language
      video), or audio-video.
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-motion-animation</id>
      <name>motion animation</name>
      <definition>
   					
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">addition of steps between conditions to create the illusion of movement or to give a sense of a smooth transition</p>
	        <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="example">For example, an element which moves into place or changes size while appearing is considered to be animated. An element which appears instantly without transitioning is not using animation. Motion animation does not include changes of color, blurring or opacity.</p>
   				
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-name</id>
      <name>name</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">text by which software can identify a component within Web content to the user</p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">The name may be hidden and only exposed by assistive technology, whereas a <a>label</a> is presented to all users. In many (but not all) cases, the label and the name are
      the same.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">This is unrelated to the name attribute in HTML.</p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-navigated-sequentially</id>
      <name>navigated sequentially</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">navigated in the order defined for advancing focus (from one element to the next)
      using a <a>keyboard interface</a>
         </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-non-text-content</id>
      <name>non-text content</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">any content that is not a sequence of characters that can be <a>programmatically determined</a> or where the sequence is not expressing something in <a>human language</a>
         </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">This includes <a>ASCII Art</a> (which is a pattern of characters), emoticons, leetspeak (which uses character substitution),
      and images representing text
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-normative</id>
      <name>normative</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">required for conformance</p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">One may conform in a variety of well-defined ways to this document.</p>
  
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Content identified as "<a>informative</a>" or "non-normative" is never required for <a>conformance</a>.</p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-on-a-full-screen-window</id>
      <name>on a full-screen window</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">on the most common sized desktop/laptop display with the viewport maximized</p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Since people generally keep their computers for several years, it is best not to rely
      on the latest desktop/laptop display resolutions but to consider the common desktop/laptop
      display resolutions over the course of several years when making this evaluation.
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-paused</id>
      <name>paused</name>
      <name>pause</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">stopped by user request and not resumed until requested by user</p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-pointer-input</id>
      <name>pointer input</name>
      <name>pointer inputs</name>
      <definition>
   					
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">input device that can target a specific coordinate (or set of coordinates) on a screen,
      such as a mouse, pen, or touch contact
   </p>
   					
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">See also <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/pointerevents/#dfn-pointer">Pointer Events pointer definition</a> [[!pointerevents]].
   </p>
   				
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-prerecorded</id>
      <name>prerecorded</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">information that is not <a>live</a>
         </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-presentation</id>
      <name>presentation</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">rendering of the <a>content</a> in a form to be perceived by users
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-primary-education-level</id>
      <name>primary education level</name>
      <name>primary education</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">six year time period that begins between the ages of five and seven, possibly without
      any previous education
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">This definition is based on the International Standard Classification of Education
      [[UNESCO]].
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-process</id>
      <name>process</name>
      <name>processes</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">series of user actions where each action is required in order to complete an activity</p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="example">Successful use of a series of Web pages on a shopping site requires users to view
      alternative products, prices and offers, select products, submit an order, provide
      shipping information and provide payment information.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="example">An account registration page requires successful completion of a Turing test before
      the registration form can be accessed.
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-programmatically-determined</id>
      <name>programmatically determined</name>
      <name>programmatically determinable</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">determined by software from author-supplied data provided in a way that different
      <a>user agents</a>, including <a>assistive technologies</a>, can extract and present this information to users in different modalities
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Determined in a markup language from elements and attributes that are accessed directly
      by commonly available assistive technology.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Determined from technology-specific data structures in a non-markup language and exposed
      to assistive technology via an accessibility API that is supported by commonly available
      assistive technology.
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-programmatically-determined-link-context</id>
      <name>programmatically determined link context</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">additional information that can be <a>programmatically determined</a> from <a>relationships</a> with a link, combined with the link text, and presented to users in different modalities
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="example">In HTML, information that is programmatically determinable from a link in English
      includes text that is in the same paragraph, list, or table cell as the link or in
      a table header cell that is associated with the table cell that contains the link.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Since screen readers interpret punctuation, they can also provide the context from
      the current sentence, when the focus is on a link in that sentence.
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-programmatically-set</id>
      <name>programmatically set</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">set by software using methods that are supported by user agents, including assistive
      technologies
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-pure-decoration</id>
      <name>pure decoration</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">serving only an aesthetic purpose, providing no information, and having no functionality</p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Text is only purely decorative if the words can be rearranged or substituted without
      changing their purpose.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="example">The cover page of a dictionary has random words in very light text in the background.</p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-real-time-event</id>
      <name>real-time event</name>
      <name>real-time events</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">event that a) occurs at the same time as the viewing and b) is not completely generated
      by the content
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="example">A Webcast of a live performance (occurs at the same time as the viewing and is not
      prerecorded).
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="example">An on-line auction with people bidding (occurs at the same time as the viewing).</p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="example">Live humans interacting in a virtual world using avatars (is not completely generated
      by the content and occurs at the same time as the viewing).
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-region</id>
      <name>region</name>
      <name>regions</name>
      <definition>
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">perceivable, programmatically determined section of content</p>
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">In HTML, any area designated with a landmark role would be a region.</p>
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-relationships</id>
      <name>relationships</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">meaningful associations between distinct pieces of content</p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-relative-luminance</id>
      <name>relative luminance</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">the relative brightness of any point in a colorspace, normalized to 0 for darkest
      black and 1 for lightest white
   </p>
   
         <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">
            <p>For the sRGB colorspace, the relative luminance of a color is defined as L = 0.2126
      * <strong>R</strong> + 0.7152 * <strong>G</strong> + 0.0722 * <strong>B</strong> where <strong>R</strong>, <strong>G</strong> and <strong>B</strong> are defined as:
   </p>
   
            <ul>
      
               <li>if RsRGB &lt;= 0.03928 then <strong>R</strong> = RsRGB/12.92 else <strong>R</strong> = ((RsRGB+0.055)/1.055) ^ 2.4
      </li>
      
               <li>if GsRGB &lt;= 0.03928 then <strong>G</strong> = GsRGB/12.92 else <strong>G</strong> = ((GsRGB+0.055)/1.055) ^ 2.4
      </li>
      
               <li>if BsRGB &lt;= 0.03928 then <strong>B</strong> = BsRGB/12.92 else <strong>B</strong> = ((BsRGB+0.055)/1.055) ^ 2.4
      </li>
      
            </ul>
   
            <p>and RsRGB, GsRGB, and BsRGB are defined as:</p>
   
            <ul>
      
               <li>RsRGB = R8bit/255</li>
      
               <li>GsRGB = G8bit/255</li>
      
               <li>BsRGB = B8bit/255</li>
      
            </ul>
   
            <p>The "^" character is the exponentiation operator. (Formula taken from [[sRGB]] and
      [[IEC-4WD]]).
   </p>

         </div>
  
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Almost all systems used today to view Web content assume sRGB encoding. Unless it
      is known that another color space will be used to process and display the content,
      authors should evaluate using sRGB colorspace. If using other color spaces, see <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/UNDERSTANDING-WCAG20/visual-audio-contrast-contrast">Understanding Success Criterion 1.4.3</a>.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">If dithering occurs after delivery, then the source color value is used. For colors
      that are dithered at the source, the average values of the colors that are dithered
      should be used (average R, average G, and average B).
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Tools are available that automatically do the calculations when testing contrast and
      flash.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">A <a href="relative-luminance.xml">MathML version of the relative luminance definition</a> is available.
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-relied-upon</id>
      <name>relied upon</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">the content would not <a>conform</a> if that <a>technology</a> is turned off or is not supported
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-role</id>
      <name>role</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">text or number by which software can identify the function of a component within Web
      content
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="example">A number that indicates whether an image functions as a hyperlink, command button,
      or check box.
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-same-functionality</id>
      <name>same functionality</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">same result when used</p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="example">A submit "search" button on one Web page and a "find" button on another Web page may
      both have a field to enter a term and list topics in the Web site related to the term
      submitted. In this case, they would have the same functionality but would not be labeled
      consistently.
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-same-relative-order</id>
      <name>same relative order</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">same position relative to other items</p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Items are considered to be in the same relative order even if other items are inserted
      or removed from the original order. For example, expanding navigation menus may insert
      an additional level of detail or a secondary navigation section may be inserted into
      the reading order.
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-satisfies-a-success-criterion</id>
      <name>satisfies a success criterion</name>
      <name>satisfies</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">the success criterion does not evaluate to 'false' when applied to the page</p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-section</id>
      <name>section</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">a self-contained portion of written content that deals with one or more related topics
      or thoughts
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">A section may consist of one or more paragraphs and include graphics, tables, lists
      and sub-sections.
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-set-of-web-pages</id>
      <name>set of web pages</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">collection of <a>web pages</a> that share a common purpose and that are created by the same author, group or organization
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="example">Examples include a publication which is split across multiple Web pages, where each page contains
      one chapter or other significant section of the work. The publication is logically
      a single contiguous unit, and contains navigation features that enable access to the
      full set of pages.
   </p>

         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Different language versions would be considered different sets of Web pages.</p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-sign-language</id>
      <name>sign language</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">a language using combinations of movements of the hands and arms, facial expressions,
      or body positions to convey meaning
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-sign-language-interpretation</id>
      <name>sign language interpretation</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">translation of one language, generally a spoken language, into a <a>sign language</a>
         </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">True sign languages are independent languages that are unrelated to the spoken language(s)
      of the same country or region.
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-single-pointer</id>
      <name>single pointer</name>
      <definition>
   	
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">pointer input that operates with one point of contact with the screen, including single taps and clicks, double-taps and clicks, long presses, and path-based gestures</p>
  				
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-specific-sensory-experience</id>
      <name>specific sensory experience</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">a sensory experience that is not purely decorative and does not primarily convey important
      information or perform a function
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="example">Examples include a performance of a flute solo, works of visual art etc.</p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-state</id>
      <name>state</name>
      <name>states</name>
      <definition>
   					
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">dynamic property expressing characteristics of a user interface component that may change in response to user action or automated processes</p>
	        <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">States do not affect the nature of the component, but represent data associated with the component or user interaction possibilities. Examples include focus, hover, select, press, check, visited/unvisited, and expand/collapse.</p>
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-status-message</id>
      <name>status message</name>
      <name>status messages</name>
      <definition>
   					
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">change in content that is not a <a>change of context</a>, and that provides information to the user on the success or results of an action, on the waiting state of an application, on the progress of a process, or on the existence of errors</p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-structure</id>
      <name>structure</name>
      <definition>
   
         <ol xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      
            <li>The way the parts of a <a>Web page</a> are organized in relation to each other; and
      </li>
      
            <li>The way a collection of <a>Web pages</a> is organized
      </li>
      
         </ol>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-style-property</id>
      <name>style property</name>
      <name>style properties</name>
      <definition>
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">property whose value determines the presentation (e.g. font, color, size, location, padding, volume, synthesized speech prosody) of
 content elements as they are rendered (e.g. onscreen, via loudspeaker, via braille display) by user agents</p>
 	       <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Style properties can have several origins:</p>
         <ul xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
            <li>User agent default styles: The default style property values applied in the absence of any author or user styles. Some web content technologies specify a default rendering, others do not;</li>
            <li>Author styles: Style property values that are set by the author as part of the content (e.g. in-line styles, author style
sheets);</li>
            <li>User styles: Style property values that are set by the user (e.g. via user agent interface settings, user style sheets)</li>
         </ul>
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-supplemental-content</id>
      <name>supplemental content</name>
      <name>supplementary content</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">additional <a>content</a> that illustrates or clarifies the primary content
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="example">An audio version of a <a>Web page</a>.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="example">An illustration of a complex <a>process</a>.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="example">A paragraph summarizing the major outcomes and recommendations made in a research
      study.
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-synchronized-media</id>
      <name>synchronized media</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
            <a>audio</a> or <a>video</a> synchronized with another format for presenting information and/or with time-based
      interactive components, unless the media is a <a>media alternative for text</a> that is clearly labeled as such
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-target</id>
      <name>target</name>
      <definition>
   					
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">region of the display that will accept a pointer action, such as the interactive area of a user interface component</p> 
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">If two or more touch targets are overlapping, the overlapping area should not be included in the measurement of the target size, except when the overlapping targets perform the same action or open the same page.</p>
  
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-technology</id>
      <name>technology</name>
      <name>technologies</name>
      <name>web technology</name>
      <name>web content technology</name>
      <name>web content technologies</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
            <a>mechanism</a> for encoding instructions to be rendered, played or executed by <a>user agents</a>
         </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">As used in these guidelines "Web Technology" and the word "technology" (when used
      alone) both refer to Web Content Technologies.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Web content technologies may include markup languages, data formats, or programming
      languages that authors may use alone or in combination to create end-user experiences
      that range from static Web pages to synchronized media presentations to dynamic Web
      applications.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="example">Some common examples of Web content technologies include HTML, CSS, SVG, PNG, PDF,
      Flash, and JavaScript.
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-text</id>
      <name>text</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">sequence of characters that can be <a>programmatically determined</a>, where the sequence is expressing something in <a>human language</a>
         </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-text-alternative</id>
      <name>text alternative</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
            <a>Text</a> that is programmatically associated with <a>non-text content</a> or referred to from text that is programmatically associated with non-text content.
      Programmatically associated text is text whose location can be programmatically determined
      from the non-text content.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="example">An image of a chart is described in text in the paragraph after the chart. The short
      text alternative for the chart indicates that a description follows.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Refer to <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/UNDERSTANDING-WCAG20/conformance">Understanding Text Alternatives</a> for more information.
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-up-event</id>
      <name>up-event</name>
      <definition>
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">platform event that occurs  when the trigger stimulus of a pointer is released</p>
	        <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The up-event may have different names on different platforms, such as "touchend" or "mouseup".</p>
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-used-in-an-unusual-or-restricted-way</id>
      <name>used in an unusual or restricted way</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">words used in such a way that requires users to know exactly which definition to apply
      in order to understand the content correctly
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="example">The term "gig" means something different if it occurs in a discussion of music concerts
      than it does in article about computer hard drive space, but the appropriate definition
      can be determined from context. By contrast, the word "text" is used in a very specific
      way in WCAG 2.1, so a definition is supplied in the glossary.
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-user-agent</id>
      <name>user agent</name>
      <name>user agents</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">any software that retrieves and presents Web content for users</p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="example">Web browsers, media players, plug-ins, and other programs  including <a>assistive technologies</a>  that help in retrieving, rendering, and interacting with Web content.
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-user-controllable</id>
      <name>user-controllable</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">data that is intended to be accessed by users</p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">This does not refer to such things as Internet logs and search engine monitoring data.</p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="example">Name and address fields for a user's account.</p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-user-interface-component</id>
      <name>user interface component</name>
      <name>user interface components</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">a part of the content that is perceived by users as a single control for a distinct
      function
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Multiple user interface components may be implemented as a single programmatic element.
      Components here is not tied to programming techniques, but rather to what the user
      perceives as separate controls.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">User interface components include form elements and links as well as components generated
      by scripts.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">What is meant by "component" or "user interface component" here is also sometimes
      called "user interface element".
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="example">An applet has a "control" that can be used to move through content by line or page
      or random access. Since each of these would need to have a name and be settable independently,
      they would each be a "user interface component."
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-user-inactivity</id>
      <name>user inactivity</name>
      <definition>
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">any continuous period of time where no user actions occur</p>
	        <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The method of tracking will be determined by the web site or application.</p>
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-video</id>
      <name>video</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">the technology of moving or sequenced pictures or images</p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Video can be made up of animated or photographic images, or both.</p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-video-only</id>
      <name>video-only</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">a time-based presentation that contains only <a>video</a> (no <a>audio</a> and no interaction)
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-viewport</id>
      <name>viewport</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">object in which the user agent presents content</p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">The <a>user agent</a> presents content through one or more viewports. Viewports include windows, frames,
      loudspeakers, and virtual magnifying glasses. A viewport may contain another viewport
      (e.g., nested frames). Interface components created by the user agent such as prompts,
      menus, and alerts are not viewports.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">This definition is based on <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/WAI-USERAGENT/glossary.html">User Agent Accessibility Guidelines 1.0 Glossary</a> [[UAAG10]].
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-visually-customized</id>
      <name>visually customized</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">the font, size, color, and background can be set</p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
   <term>
      <id>dfn-web-page</id>
      <name>web page</name>
      <name>web page(s)</name>
      <name>web pages</name>
      <definition>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">a non-embedded resource obtained from a single URI using HTTP plus any other resources
      that are used in the rendering or intended to be rendered together with it by a <a>user agent</a>
         </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">Although any "other resources" would be rendered together with the primary resource,
      they would not necessarily be rendered simultaneously with each other.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="note">For the purposes of conformance with these guidelines, a resource must be "non-embedded"
      within the scope of conformance to be considered a Web page.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="example">A Web resource including all embedded images and media.</p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="example">A Web mail program built using Asynchronous JavaScript and XML (AJAX). The program
      lives entirely at http://example.com/mail, but includes an inbox, a contacts area
      and a calendar. Links or buttons are provided that cause the inbox, contacts, or calendar
      to display, but do not change the URI of the page as a whole.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="example">A customizable portal site, where users can choose content to display from a set of
      different content modules.
   </p>
   
         <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" class="example">When you enter "http://shopping.example.com/" in your browser, you enter a movie-like
      interactive shopping environment where you visually move around in a store dragging
      products off of the shelves around you and into a visual shopping cart in front of
      you. Clicking on a product causes it to be demonstrated with a specification sheet
      floating alongside. This might be a single-page Web site or just one page within a
      Web site.
   </p>
   
      </definition>
   </term>
</guidelines>
