<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="G110">
   <short-name>Using an instant client-side redirect</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>Applies to all technologies.</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="consistent-behavior-no-extreme-changes-context"
                         relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to enable redirects on the client side
            without confusing the user. Redirects are preferably implemented on the
            server side (see <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" href="SVR1" linktype="server">Implementing automatic redirects on the server side instead of on the client side</loc>), because a server-side
            redirect does not cause new content to be displayed before the server sends
            the content located at the new URI. However, authors do not always have
            control over server-side technologies; in that case, they can use a
            client-side redirect. A client-side redirect is implemented by code inside
            the content that instructs the user agent to retrieve content from a
            different URI. It is important that the redirecting page or Web page
            only contains information related to the redirect.</p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <head>HTML:
              <code><![CDATA[
                meta
              ]]></code>
              Refresh With a URI and No Timeout</head>
         <description>
            <p>In HTML 4.x and XHTML 1.x, it is possible to implement a client-side
                redirect using the
                <code><![CDATA[
                  meta
                ]]></code>
                element: see
                <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" href="H76" linktype="html">Using
                  meta refresh to create an instant client-side redirect</loc>.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also/>
   </resources>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="H76"/>
      <relatedtech idref="SVR1"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Find each link or programmatic reference to another page or
                  Web page.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>For each link or programmatic reference, check if the referenced
                  Web page contains code (e.g., meta element or script) that
                  causes a client-side redirect.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>For each link or programmatic reference that causes a
                  client-side redirect, check if the redirect is implemented
                  without a time limit or delay and that the page only contains
                  information related to the redirect.</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <p>Step 2 is false or step 3 is true.</p>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
