<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="G111">
   <short-name>Using color and pattern</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>All technologies that support images.</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="visual-audio-contrast-without-color" relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to ensure that when color differences are used to convey information within non-text content, patterns are included to convey the same information in a manner that does not depend on color.</p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <description>
            <p>A real estate site provides a bar chart of average housing prices in several regions of the United States. The bar for each region is displayed with a different solid color and a different pattern. The legend uses the same colors and patterns to identify each bar.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <description>
            <p>An on-line map of a transportation system displays each route in a different color. The stops on each route are marked with a distinctive icon such as a diamond, square, or circle to help differentiate each route.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <description>
            <p>A flow chart describes a set of iterative steps to complete a process. It uses dashed, arrowed lines with a green background to point to the next step in the process when the specified condition passes. It uses dotted arrowed lines with a red background to point to the next step in the process when the specified condition fails.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <description>
            <p>The content includes an interactive game. The game pieces for the 4 players are distinguished from one another using both color and pattern.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources/>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="G14"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <p>For each image within the Web page that use color differences to convey information:</p>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Check that all information that is conveyed using color is also conveyed using patterns that do not rely on color.</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>Check #1 is true.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
