<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="G125">
   <short-name>Providing links to navigate to related Web pages</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>All technologies that contain links</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="navigation-mechanisms-mult-loc" relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to make it possible for users to locate additional information by providing links to related Web pages.
            It is one of a series of techniques for locating content that are sufficient for addressing Success Criterion 2.4.5. 
            Links are a basic component of the World Wide Web. They are the mechanism that makes the Web an interconnected Web of content. Most authors employ this technique automatically when creating Web pages.</p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <description>
            <p>The
                <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    href="http://www.w3.org/TR/WCAG20/">Web Content Accessibility Guidelines 2.0</loc>
                contains links to definitions of terms used in guidelines and Success Criteria, links to documents explaining how to meet different Success Criteria, a table of contents for each section containing links to different subsections of that section, and  a
                <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    href="http://www.w3.org/WAI/WCAG20/from10/comparison/">Comparison of WCAG 1.0 checkpoints to WCAG 2.0</loc>. As users browse the document, they can follow these links to find related information.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.w3.org/TR/webarch/">Architecture of the World Wide Web, Volume One</loc>
                </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </see-also>
   </resources>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="G63"/>
      <relatedtech idref="G64"/>
      <relatedtech idref="G126"/>
      <relatedtech idref="G185"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <p>For each link in the Web page:</p>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Check whether the link leads to related information.</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>Check #1 is true.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
