<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="G126">
   <short-name>Providing a list of links to all other Web pages</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>All technologies that contain links</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="navigation-mechanisms-mult-loc" relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to provide a list of links to all the Web pages in the set on each Web page. It is one of a series of techniques for locating content that are sufficient for addressing Success Criterion 2.4.5. 
            This technique is only effective for small sets of Web pages; if the list of links is longer than the rest of the content in the Web page, it may make the Web page more difficult for users to understand and use.</p>
      <note>
         <p>Success Criterion 2.4.1 requires a technique for skipping this list of links.</p>
      </note>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <description>
            <p>A family Web site contains home pages for all the members of the family. Each page contains a list of links to the home pages of the other family members.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <description>
            <p>An electonic book is broken into separate Web pages for each chapter. Each Web page starts with a small table of contents that contains links to all the chapters in the book.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources/>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="G1"/>
      <relatedtech idref="G63"/>
      <relatedtech idref="G64"/>
      <relatedtech idref="G123"/>
      <relatedtech idref="G125"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Check that each Web page contains a list of links to the other Web pages in the site</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Check that the links in the list lead to the corresponding Web pages.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Check that the list contains a link for every Web page in the site.</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>All of the checks above are true.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
