<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="G13">
   <short-name>Describing what will happen before a change to a form control that causes a change of context to occur is made</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>Applies to all technologies.</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="consistent-behavior-unpredictable-change"
                         relationship="sufficient"/>
      <success-criterion idref="minimize-error-cues" relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to provide information to users about
            what will happen when a change to a form control results in a change of
            context. Because changing the value of a form control does not typically
            result in a change of context, it is important that authors provide
            instructions that make the user aware of the behavior in advance. Where
            possible, it is a good idea to programmatically associate the instructions
            describing the change with the form control itself.</p>
      <p>The following are some examples of how to provide the instruction in different situations.</p>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>Provide instruction on the Web page with reading order that precedes the user interface element that causes change of context by change of setting.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>For a multi-step process where users must complete particular steps in order to reach the user interface element where changes of setting would cause a change of context, provide the instruction as part of the process prior to the step where they would encounter the change of context.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>In the case of an intranet where user training is required prior to the use of a Web application where user interface elements that cause changes of context when settings are changed, instruction is provided as part of the training.</p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>A series of radio buttons at the top of a page include
                options for German, French and Spanish. Instructions precede
                the buttons that instruct the user that the language will be
                changed upon selecting an option.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>A 50 question online survey displays one question at a time.
                Instructions appear at the beginning of the survey that
                explain that users will be taken to the next question of the
                survey upon selecting an answer to each question.</p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also/>
   </resources>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="G80"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>Locate content where changing the setting of a form control
                  results in a change of context</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Check to see that an explanation of what will happen when the
                  control is changed is available prior to the controls activation</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>Check #2 is true.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
