<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="G135">
   <short-name>Using the accessibility API features of a technology to expose names and
          roles, to allow user-settable properties to be directly set, and to provide
          notification of changes</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>programming technologies that have standard components that are programmed
            to interface with accessibility APIs</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="ensure-compat-rsv" relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to allow assistive technology to
            understand Web content so that it can convey equivalent information to the
            user through an alternate user interface.</p>
      <p>Sometimes content is not created using markup language but rather using a
            programming language or tools. In many cases, these technologies have
            interface components that are already programmed to interface with
            accessibility APIs. If an author uses these components and fills in the
            properties (e.g., name, etc) the resulting user interface components in the
            content will be accessible to assistive technology.</p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <description>
            <ulist>
               <item>
                  <p>A Web page uses java to create an applet. Java swing objects
                    (e.g., pushbutton) are used because they have accessibility
                    properties built in that can be accessed from assistive
                    technology written in Java and, with the Java Access Bridge,
                    those written in other languages that use the Accessibility
                    API of the operating system. The author fills in the values
                    for the components and the result is accessible to AT.</p>
               </item>
            </ulist>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also/>
   </resources>
   <related-techniques/>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Render content using an accessible User Agent</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Use an Accessibility Tool designed for the Accessibility API of
                  the User agent to evaluate each user interface component</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Check that name and role for each user interface component are
                  found by the tool.</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>Step #3 is true for each user interface component</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
