<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="G136">
   <short-name>Providing a link at the beginning of a nonconforming Web page that points to a conforming alternate version</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>Primary content does not conform to WCAG but alternate versions exist that do conform to WCAG. This technique can only be used if a technology makes it possible to create an accessible link to an alternate version.</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <conformance-criterion idref="cc1" relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to enable users to access alternate content that conforms to WCAG if the primary content, or the default content that users encounter when visiting a particular URI, does not conform. The alternate page, or conforming alternate version, may make some design or functionality compromises in order to conform, but must meet the requirements described in the definition in order to be a conforming alternate version. The definition of "conforming alternate version" is:</p>
      <p id="copyconforming-alternate-versiondef"/>
      <p>When using this techique, placing a WCAG-conforming link to alternate content at the top of the page allows users to find the link quickly and to move to the conforming alternate version. To ensure users can always find the alternate version, regardless of where they enter the site, each page that does not conform at the specified level would include a link to the conforming alternate version.</p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>On a Web site, for each page that does not conform to WCAG at the declared level, the first link on the page is called "Accessible version" (or using other link text that properly conveys the purpose of the link). The target of this link is the alternate version of the page that conforms to WCAG at the declared level.</p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
   </examples>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="SVR2"/>
      <relatedtech idref="SCR38"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Identify a page that does not conform to WCAG at the claimed conformance level.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Determine if the page contains a link to a conforming alternate version of the page.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Determine if the alternate version is a
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="conforming-alternate-versiondef"
                       linktype="glossary">conforming alternate version</loc>
                  of the original page and that it conforms to WCAG 2.0 at the claimed conformance level.</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>Both #2 and #3 are true.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
