<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="G144">
   <short-name>Ensuring that the Web Page contains another CAPTCHA serving the same purpose using a different modality</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>Applies to all technologies.</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="text-equiv-all" relationship="cosufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>The purpose of this technique is to reduce occasions in which a user with a disability cannot complete a CAPTCHA task. Because there are alternate CAPTCHA tasks that use different modalities, a user is more likely to be able to complete one of the tasks successfully.</p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>A Web page that includes a CAPTCHA test that must be completed successfully before the user can advance to the next step in a process. The page includes both a visual task, such as typing words displayed in a image, and an audio task, such as typing letters spoken in an audio file. A user with hearing disabilities who cannot pass the audio CAPTCHA may be able to pass the visual CAPTCHA.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>A blog comment form includes a visual CAPTCHA that must be completed before a user can submit comments. In addition to the visual CAPTCHA, it includes a CAPTCHA with a form field that asks, "What is two plus seven?" with a text entry field that allows users to enter the correct answer.</p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
   </examples>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="G143"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <p>For each CAPTCHA in a Web page</p>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Check that the Web page contains another CAPTCHA for the same purpose but using a different modality.</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>Check #1 is true.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
