<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="G150">
   <short-name>Providing text based alternatives for live audio-only content</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>All technologies that present live audio-only information</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="media-equiv-live-audio-only" relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to allow users who cannot hear to be able to access real-time audio broadcasts. It is more difficult to create accurate real-time alternatives because there is little time to correct mistakes, to listen a second time or to consult someone to be sure the words are accurately reproduced. It is also harder to simplify or paraphrase information if it is flowing too quickly.</p>
      <p>Real-time typing text entry techniques exist using stenographic and rapid typing technologies. Re-voicing speech-to-text (where a person listens to speech and then carefully re-voices it into a computer trained to their speech) is used today for telephone relay services and may be used in the future for captioning. Eventually speech-to-text with correction will be possible.</p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>A radio station uses Web based captioning services to provide alternatives for live sporting events; the output from the service is incorporated in a viewport of the Web page which also includes a streaming audio control.</p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
   </examples>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="G9"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Check that a procedure and policy is in place to ensure that text alternatives are delivered in real-time.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Check that procedure and policy are working by conducting a random sample to see if text alternatives appear.</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>Both #1 and #2 are true.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
