<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="G172">
   <short-name>Providing a mechanism to remove full justification of text</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>All technologies.</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="visual-audio-contrast-visual-presentation"
                         relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to provide a version of the page that does not have full justification (justified both left and right).</p>
      <p>There may be circumstances when for layout purposes an author may want to have the text fully justified. In these cases, it is sufficient to provide a feature that removes the justification of text. The control should be easy to find and access and near the beginning of the page.</p>
      <note>
         <p>This technique can be used in combination with a style switching technique to present a page that is a
              <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                 href="conforming-alternate-versiondef"
                 linktype="glossary">conforming alternate version</loc>
              for non-conforming content. Refer to
              <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" href="C29" linktype="css">C29: Using a style switcher to provide a conforming alternate version</loc>
              and
              <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                 href="conformance"
                 locn-note="uc-conforming-alt-versions-head"
                 linktype="understanding">Understanding Conforming Alternate Versions</loc>
              for more information.</p>
      </note>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <description>
            <p>A classic novel online is on a site that attempts to duplicate the look of the originally published work, which includes full justification. A button is provided near the top of the page saying "remove full justification" and a style switching technique is used to swap out the style sheet. The new style sheet aligns the text only on the left.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="C19"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Open a page with full justification.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Check that there is a feature to remove the full justification.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Check that the feature removes the full justification.</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>Checks #2 and #3 are true.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
