<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="G186">
   <short-name>Using a control in the Web page that stops moving, blinking, or auto-updating content</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>All technologies.</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="time-limits-pause" relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to provide the user a control that allows him to stop moving or blinking content. Since the control is in the web page, the control itself meets the appropriate level of WCAG conformance e.g., it has appropriate contrast, it has a name that identifies it, it is keyboard accessible. The control is either at the top of the page or adjacent to the moving content. A single control may stop all moving or blinking content on the page, or there may be separate controls for separate parts of the content.</p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Stock Market Ticker Tape</head>
         <description>
            <p>A Web page displays the latest stock market results in a "ticker tape" that automatically scrolls across the bottom of the screen. A "Pause" button lets the user stop the ticker tape. When the ticker tape is unpaused, it resumes displaying the current stock market information.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Teleconferencing Tool</head>
         <description>
            <p>A teleconferencing Web page displays a speaker queue of people who wish to speak. A checkbox on the page lets the user choose whether the display of the queue should be updated automatically when a new person is added or removed, or whether it should only be updated when the user presses the "Refresh" button. When the queue is being updated automatically, the Refresh button is deactivated.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="G4"/>
      <relatedtech idref="G191"/>
      <relatedtech idref="SCR22"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Check that there is a control on the Web page to stop the motion.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Activate the control.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Check that the motion, blinking  or auto-updating has stopped.</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>Checks #1 and #3 are true.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
