<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="G189">
   <short-name>Providing a control near the beginning of the Web page that changes the link text</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>All technologies that contain links.</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="navigation-mechanisms-refs" relationship="sufficient"/>
      <success-criterion idref="navigation-mechanisms-link" relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to provide the user with a control near the beginning of the page that takes the user to a conforming alternate version of the Web page where the link text alone of each link is sufficient to determine its purpose out of context.</p>
      <p>Some users prefer to have links that are self-contained, where there is no need to explore the context of the link. Other users find including the context information in each link to be repetitive and to reduce their ability to use a site. Among users of assistive technology, the feedback to the working group on which is preferable has been divided. This technique allows users to pick the approach that works best for them. Users who need or prefer potentially longer but complete link text use this version.</p>
      <p>If the control for switching to the alternate version is a link, it must always be possible to understand the purpose of the control directly from its link text.</p>
      <p>This technique provides the alternate version for the current page view. It is also possible, and in some cases would be advisable, to save this preference in a cookie or server-side user profile, so that users would only have to make the selection once per site and would automatically be taken to their preferred version.</p>
      <note>
         <p>This technique can be used in combination with a style switching technique to present a page that is a
              <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                 href="conforming-alternate-versiondef"
                 linktype="glossary">conforming alternate version</loc>
              for non-conforming content. Refer to
              <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" href="C29" linktype="css">C29: Using a style switcher to provide a conforming alternate version</loc>
              and
              <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                 href="conformance"
                 locn-note="uc-conforming-alt-versions-head"
                 linktype="understanding">Understanding Conforming Alternate Versions</loc>
              for more information.</p>
      </note>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Providing a Link to another Version</head>
         <description>
            <p>A Web page lists books for download in different formats. Alternate versions of the Web page use just the book format as the link text or the book title and format type.</p>
            <p>Version with short link text:</p>
         </description>
         <code><![CDATA[
              ...
                <h1>Books for download</h1>
                <p><a href="books-full-links.html" >Full link Version</a></p>
                <ul>
                <li>The History of the Web: 
                <a href="history.docx" class="hist">Word</a>, 
                <a href="history.pdf" class="hist">PDF</a>, 
                <a href="history.html" class="hist">HTML</a>
                </li>
                ...
                </ul>
            ]]></code>
         <description>
            <p>Version with full link text:</p>
         </description>
         <code><![CDATA[
              ...
                <h1>Books for download</h1>
                <p><a href="books-short-links.html" >Short link Version</a></p>
                <ul>
                <li>The History of the Web: 
                <a href="history.docx" class="hist">The History of the Web(Word)</a>, 
                <a href="history.pdf" class="hist">The History of the Web(PDF)>/a>, 
                <a href="history.html" class="hist">The History of the Web(HTML)</a>
                </li>
                ...
                </ul>
            ]]></code>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="G91"/>
      <relatedtech idref="H30"/>
      <relatedtech idref="H24"/>
      <relatedtech idref="C7"/>
      <relatedtech idref="SCR30"/>
      <relatedtech idref="G136"/>
      <relatedtech idref="C29"/>
      <!--Providing user settings as a way to store preferences (future link)   -->
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Check that there is a control near the beginning of the Web page to change link text.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Activate the control.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Check that all links in the resulting Web page have link text that describes their purpose.</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>Checks #1 and #3 are true.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
