<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="G191">
   <short-name>Providing a link, button, or other mechanism that reloads the page without any blinking content</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>This technique relates to all technologies.</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="time-limits-pause" relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>This is a general technique for allowing people who cannot use a page with blinking content to turn the blinking content off.
            <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
              href="cc1"
              linktype="guideline">Conformance Requirement 1</loc>
            allows for conforming alternate pages to be used to meet conformance. This technique is an example of that approach applied to success criteria 2.2.2.</p>
      <p>It is important that the page without blinking content contain all of the information that was on the page with blinking content.</p>
      <note>
         <p>Removing the content that was blinking from the page would only be satisfactory if the blinking content was redundant with non blinking content in the original page.</p>
         <p>This technique can be used in combination with a style switching technique to present a page that is a
              <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                 href="conforming-alternate-versiondef"
                 linktype="glossary">conforming alternate version</loc>
              for non-conforming content. Refer to
              <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" href="C29" linktype="css"/>
              and
              <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                 href="conformance"
                 locn-note="uc-conforming-alt-versions-head"
                 linktype="understanding">Understanding Conforming Alternate Versions</loc>
              for more information.</p>
      </note>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>A page has blinking text at the top warning users that they should not submit the page without first registering. A link at the very top of the page reloads the page with the blinking text replaced with text that is styled to be highly visible but does not blink.</p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
   </examples>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="G4"/>
      <relatedtech idref="G11"/>
      <relatedtech idref="G152"/>
      <relatedtech idref="G186"/>
      <relatedtech idref="G187"/>
      <relatedtech idref="SCR22"/>
      <relatedtech idref="SCR33"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Check that there is a mechanism to reload page to turn off blinking.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Check that reloaded page has no blinking.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Check that the reloaded page has all the information and functionality of the original page.</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>All of the above checks are true.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
