<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="G194">
   <short-name>Providing spell checking and suggestions for text input</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>This technique relates to all technologies.</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="minimize-error-context-help" relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>In this technique spell checking and suggestions for text are provided. Often people with cognitive disabilities have trouble spelling a word, but may be able to get the spelling approximately correct. A spell checking program will save them time-consuming research on how to spell the word. This may also be true for blind and low vision users who might make a mistake when typing. It will also help people with dexterity disabilities who may be using a head pointer, or who may have scanning software which makes it very slow and difficult to type. A spell-checking solution that provides word suggestion(s) and a simple mechanism to select one and input it into the text input field provides important help for these users and others.</p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>A search engine has a form field for search terms. When the form is submitted, a server-side application checks the spelling. If the spelling doesn't match any words for that language, it sends back a page with a text message at the top saying "Did you mean ..." with a link to the suggested word. If the user clicks on the link the suggested term is entered into the form field and is resubmitted.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>An airline has a on online ticket purchasing application. When a user types the name of a city into the form field a dropdown menu shows the closest match to the city in the top of the menu and other suggestions below.</p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
   </examples>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="G71"/>
      <relatedtech idref="G103"/>
      <relatedtech idref="G120"/>
      <relatedtech idref="G121"/>
      <relatedtech idref="H89"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Check that there is a form field on the page.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Enter a misspelled word.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Check that a suggested spelling is presented.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Check that a mechanism is available to enter the suggested word into the form.</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>Checks #3 and #4 are true.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
