<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="G200">
   <short-name>Opening new windows and tabs from a link only when necessary</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>Pages that open new windows</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
	   <guideline idref="consistent-behavior" relationship="advisory"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to limit the use of links or  buttons that open new windows or tabs within Web content. In general, it is better not to open new windows and tabs since they can be disorienting for people, especially people who have difficulty  perceiving visual content. However there are some situations where it is preferable from an accessibility perspective to open a new window or tab. Here are two such situations:</p>
      <olist>
         <item>
            <p>Opening a page containing context-sensitive information, such  as help instructions, or an alternate means of completing a form, such  as a calendar-based date picker, will significantly disrupt a  multi-step workflow, such as filling in and submitting a form, if the  page is opened in the same window or tab.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>The user is logged into a secured <phrase>area</phrase> of a site, and following a  link to a page outside of the secured <phrase>area</phrase> would terminate the user's logon. In this case opening external links in an external window allows  the user to access such references while keeping their login active in  the original window.</p>
         </item>
      </olist>
      <p>It is recommended that when links are opened to a new window, there is advance warning.</p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Online Form</head>
         <description>
            <p>An online form provides extensive context-sensitive help for each  form field on a separate page because there is too much text to include  within the form. The links to the context-sensitive help open in new  windows or tabs to prevent the loss of any form data that has already  been entered.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Secure Web site</head>
         <description>
            <p>A page on a secure Web site includes a link to an external page that  is outside of the secure session. The link opens in a new window or tab  since opening the link in the same window will break or destroy the  secure session.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Date Picker</head>
         <description>
            <p>An online form includes a date field that allows the user to  manually type in the date or select a date from a calendar-based date  picker on a separate page. The link to the calendar-based date picker  opens in a new window or tab to prevent the loss of any form data that  has already been entered.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also>
         <p>
              <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
              	href="http://www.webcredible.com/blog/beware-opening-links-new-window/">Beware of opening links in a new window</loc>
            </p>
      </see-also>
      <see-also>
         <p>
              <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                 href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/the-top-ten-web-design-mistakes-of-1999/">Top-10 New Mistakes of Web Design</loc>
            </p>
      </see-also>
   </resources>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="G201"/>
      <relatedtech idref="H83"/>
      <relatedtech idref="SCR24"/>
   </related-techniques>
</technique>
