<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="G5">
   <short-name>Allowing users to complete an activity without any time limit</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>This technique applies to any technologies or methods supporting the implementation of an activity which does not require timed interaction for its functionality.</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="time-limits-no-exceptions" relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to provide users with all the time they need to complete an activity. This technique involves providing a specified activity which does not require timed interaction. Users are allowed as much time as they need to interact with the activity.</p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>An interactive exam for a course provides all questions on one Web page. Users can take as much time as they need to complete it.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>In an interactive game, users can take as much time as they like on their turn instead of having to complete their move within a limited amount of time.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>In an online auction, each bidder can submit only one bid rather than submitting multiple competitive bids based on timing. The bidding is open for a full day, providing enough time for anyone to complete the simple bid form. Once bidding is closed, the best bid wins.</p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/top-ten-web-design-mistakes-of-2005/">Top Ten Web Design Mistakes of 2005</loc>
                </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </see-also>
   </resources>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="G75"/>
      <relatedtech idref="G76"/>
      <relatedtech idref="G80"/>
      <relatedtech idref="G198"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Determine if any timed interactions are present (client and/or server side).</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>#1 is false.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
