<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="G53">
   <short-name>Identifying the purpose of a link using link text combined with the text of the enclosing sentence</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>All technologies that contain links.</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="navigation-mechanisms-refs" relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <ua-issues>
      <ua-issue name="JAWS" version="5.0+">
         <p>JAWS 5.0 and later includes the following keystrokes:</p>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>alt+leftArrow: read previous sentence</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>alt+rightArrow: read next sentence</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>alt+NumPad 5: read current sentence</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Ctrl+NumPad5: read current paragraph</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </ua-issue>
      <ua-issue name="WinEyes" version="5.5">
         <p>Window-Eyes 5.5 has hotkeys to read the current sentence and current paragraph.</p>
         <p>To surf the internet with WindowEyes  you must be in browse mode. Current sentence and current paragraph hot keys do not work in browse mode in version 6.1.</p>
         <p>The Window-Eyes default settings for reading surrounding link context are as follows:</p>
         <p>Desktop settings:</p>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>Character = CTRL-NUMPAD-LEFT ARROW</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Word = CTRL-NUMPAD-RIGHT ARROW</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Line = CTRL-NUMPAD-CENTER</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Sentence = Not available in Browse mode</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>(Next Sentence command is undefined by default on Desktop mode but the next line is the DOWN Arrow.)</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Next Paragraph = P</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Prior Paragraph = Shift P</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Current Paragraph = Not Available in Browse mode</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
         <p>Laptop</p>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>Character = ALT-SHIFT-LESS THAN</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Word Prior = ALT-SHIFT-J</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Word = ALT-SHIFT-K</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Word Next = ALT-SHIFT-L</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Sentence Prior = ALT-SHIFT-7</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Sentence = unavailable in browse mode</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Sentence Next = unavailable in browse mode</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Paragraph = Undefined on Laptop by default</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Line Prior = ALT-SHIFT-U</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Line = ALT-SHIFT-I</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Line Next =  ALT-SHIFT-O</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </ua-issue>
   </ua-issues>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to identify the purpose of a link from the link and its sentence context. The sentence enclosing the link provides context for an otherwise unclear link. The description lets a user distinguish this link from links in the Web page that lead to other destinations and helps the user determine whether to follow the link. Note that simply providing the URI of the destination is generally not sufficiently descriptive.</p>
      <note>
         <p>These descriptions will be most useful to the user if the additional information needed to understand the link precedes the link. If the additional information follows the link, there can be confusion and difficulty for screen reader users who are reading through the page in order (top to bottom).</p>
      </note>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <head/>
         <description>
            <p>A Web page contains the sentence "To advertise on this page,
                <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" href="http://example.com">click here</loc>."</p>
            <p>Although the link phrase 'click here' is not sufficient to understand the link, the information needed precedes the link in the same sentence.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <head/>
         <description>
            <p>In the news summary containing the sentence "The Smallville Times
                <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" href="http://example.com">reports that</loc>
                the School Board chose a 2007 school calendar that starts on August 27.", the words "reports that" are a link to an article in the Smallville Times about the School Board meeting.</p>
            <note>
               <p>Although this example satisfies the Success Criterion, putting information needed to understand the link after the link in this way is awkward for those who are reading through the document with a screen reader.</p>
            </note>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources/>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="G91"/>
      <relatedtech idref="H2"/>
      <relatedtech idref="H30"/>
      <relatedtech idref="H33"/>
      <relatedtech idref="H77"/>
      <relatedtech idref="H78"/>
      <relatedtech idref="H79"/>
      <relatedtech idref="H80"/>
      <relatedtech idref="H81"/>
      <relatedtech idref="C7"/>
      <relatedtech idref="ARIA1"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <p>For each link in the content that uses this technique:</p>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Check that the link is part of a sentence</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Check that text of the link combined with the text of its enclosing sentence describes the purpose of the link</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>The above checks are true.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
