<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="G55">
   <short-name>Linking to definitions</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>All technologies that include links.</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="meaning-idioms" relationship="sufficient"/>
      <success-criterion idref="meaning-located" relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to make the definition of a word, phrase, or abbreviation available by providing the definition, either within the same Web page or in a different Web page, and establishing a link between the item and its definition.</p>
      <p>Links are a powerful option for providing access to the definition of a word, phrase, or abbreviation. A user can use the link to find the definition quickly and easily, and then return to his place in the content via the user agent's Back button.</p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <description>
            <p>Technical terms and abbreviations in an article about sports injuries are linked to definitions in a medical dictionary.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <description>
            <p>A textbook contains a glossary of new vocabulary words introduced in each chapter. The first occurrence of each of these words is linked to its definition in the glossary.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <description>
            <p>A general glossary of abbreviations is provided. All occurrences of abbreviations are linked directly to the appropriate definition within that glossary.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <description>
            <p>The word
                <emph>
                  <loc href="jargondef" linktype="glossary">jargon</loc>
                </emph>
                is linked to its definition in the WCAG2 Glossary.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <description>
            <p>The word "modulo" is jargon used in Web content about mathematics. A definition for modulo is included within the Web page. Each occurrence of the word modulo is linked to its definition.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <description>
            <p>A Japanese idiom is linked to its definition. This example uses a link within the page to navigate to the definition of an idiomatic expression.</p>
         </description>
         <code role="html401"><![CDATA[
              <p>...<a href="#definition">さじを投げる</a>...</p>
                <h3>脚注：</h3>
                <dl>
                <dt id="definition" name="definition">さじを投げる</dt>
                <dd>どうすることもできなくなり、あきらめること。</dd>
                </dl>
            ]]></code>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources/>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="G62"/>
      <relatedtech idref="G70"/>
      <relatedtech idref="G101"/>
      <relatedtech idref="G102"/>
      <relatedtech idref="G112"/>
      <relatedtech idref="H40"/>
      <relatedtech idref="H60"/>
      <relatedtech idref="H64"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <p>For each word, phrase, or abbreviation to be defined:</p>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Check that at least the first instance of the item is a link.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Check that each link navigates to the definition of the item.</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>Checks #1 and #2 are true.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
