<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="G58">
   <short-name>Placing a link to the alternative for time-based media immediately next to the non-text content</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>This technique is not technology specific and can be used in any technology that supports links.</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="media-equiv-audio-desc" relationship="sufficient"/>
      <success-criterion idref="media-equiv-text-doc" relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>With this technique, a link to the collated document of captions and audio description is provided. The collated document could be at another location on the same Web page or at another URI. A link to the collated document is immediately adjacent to the non-text content. The link can be immediately before or after the synchronized media content. If the collated document is on the same Web page as other content then put "End of document" at the end so that they know when to stop reading and return to their previous place. If a Back button will not take the person back to the point from which they jumped, then a link back to the non-text content location is provided.</p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <head>An .MOV Document in an HTML Document</head>
         <description>
            <p>Code on a page called "Olympic_Sports.htm"</p>
         </description>
         <code><![CDATA[
  <a name="Olympic_Wrestling"></a>
  <p><a href="http://www.example.com/movies/olympic_wrestling.mov">Olympic Wrestling movie</a>, 
  <a href="http://www.example.com/transcripts/olympic_wrestling_transcript.htm">Olympic 
  Wrestling collated Transcript</a></p>
            ]]></code>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <head>The link back to the .MOV Document in an HTML Document</head>
         <description>
            <p>Code on the page olympic_wrestling_transcript.htm</p>
         </description>
         <code><![CDATA[
  <p>Sports announcer 1: This is a great battle tonight between England's "Will Johnson" and 
  "Theodore Derringo" from Argentina</p>
  <p>Scenery: There is a mat set out in the middle of the stadium with 500 people in the 
  stands...</p>
  <p> ...more dialogue...<p>
  <p> ...more scenery...</p>
  <p> ...etc...</p>
  <p>Sports announcer 2: And that is all for tonight, thank you for joining us tonight where 
  Will Johnson is the new Gold Medalist. 
  <a href="../movies/Olympic_Sports.htm#Olympic_Wrestling>Return to Movie page</a> </p>
            ]]></code>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources/>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="G69"/>
      <relatedtech idref="G159"/>
      <relatedtech idref="H46"/>
      <relatedtech idref="H53"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Check for the presence of a link immediately before or after the non-text content.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Check that it is a valid link that points directly to the collated document of this particular synchronized media.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Check for the availability of a link or back function to get the user back to the original location of the synchronized media content.</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>Items #1 through 3 are all true.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
