<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="G68">
   <short-name>Providing a short text alternative that describes the purpose of live
          audio-only and live video-only content</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>Applies to all technologies</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="text-equiv-all" relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>This technique provides a short text alternative for Live audio-only and live video-only content. This text may be used in combination with a full text alternative for time-based media (for audio or video), or in combination with audio description (for video).
            Those alternatives, however, are not part of this technique. The purpose of
            this technique is to ensure that the user can determine what the non-text
            content is, even if they cannot access it. NOTE: Even if full alternatives
            are also available, it is important that users be able to identify the
            non-text content when they encounter it so that they are not confused, and
            so that they can associate it with the full alternative when they encounter
            it.</p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <description>
            <ulist>
               <item>
                  <p>A live video feed of the east coast highway has the
                    following descriptive label "Live video picture of East
                    Coast Highway just south of the I-81 interchange showing
                    current traffic conditions."</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>A live audio feed of the Mississippi House of
                    Representatives has the following descriptive label "Live
                    audio from the microphones in the Mississippi House of
                    Representatives."</p>
               </item>
            </ulist>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also/>
   </resources>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="G100"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Remove, hide, or mask the non-text content.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Display the short text alternative(s).</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Check that the purpose of the non-text content is clear, even if content is lost.</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>#3 is true.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
