<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="G70">
   <short-name>Providing a function to search an online dictionary</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>All technologies</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="meaning-idioms" relationship="sufficient"/>
      <success-criterion idref="meaning-located" relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to provide the definition of words, phrases, jargon, or abbreviation expansions by adding a mechanism to access an on-line dictionary to the Web page. This technique uses existing resources on the Web to provide the definition rather than requiring the author to create a glossary or other mechanism within the site. By providing access from within the Web page, a user can easily locate the desired definition. This technique can only be used if the online dictionary returns the correct definition.</p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <description>
            <p>A site that describes how a computer works would include a search feature on each Web page. The search would be performed against an on-line dictionary of computer terms, acronyms, and abbreviations. Since the dictionary is specialized for computer terms, the acronym expansion found should be more accurate than with a general dictionary.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <description>
            <p>An online course in English grammar provides a paragraph of text which introduces new vocabulary words. Each of the vocabulary words is a link to an on-line dictionary to find the definition of the word. Activating a link will open up a new window to an online dictionary site with the specific vocabulary word defined.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources/>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="G55"/>
      <relatedtech idref="G62"/>
      <relatedtech idref="G112"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <p>For each word, phrase, or abbreviation to be defined:</p>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Check that a mechanism exists within the Web page to search for the word, phrase, or abbreviation via an on-line dictionary.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Check that the result of the search of the dictionary for the word, phrase, or abbreviation is the correct definition.</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>Checks #1 and #2 are true.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
         <p>Note: The definition of abbreviation used in WCAG is: "shortened form of a word, phrase, or name where the original expansion has not been rejected by the organization that it refers to and where the abbreviation has not become part of the language."</p>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
