<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="G73">
   <short-name>Providing a long description in another location with a link to it that
          is immediately adjacent to the non-text content</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>Applies to all technologies</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="text-equiv-all" relationship="cosufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to provide a way to link to remote long
            descriptions in technologies that do not have a long description feature
            built directly into them (e.g., longdesc) or where the feature is known to
            not be supported.</p>
      <p>With this technique, the long description is provided in another location
            than the non-text content. This could be at another location within the same
            URI or at another URI. A link to that long description is provided that is
            immediately adjacent to the non-text content. The link can be immediately
            before or after the non-text content. If the description is located along
            with other text then put "End of description" at the end so that they know
            when to stop reading and return to the main content. If a "Back" button will
            not take the person back to the point from which they jumped, then a link
            back to the non-text content location is provided.</p>
      <p>This technique was commonly used in HTML before 'longdesc' was added to the
            specification. In HTML it was called a D-Link because it was usually
            implemented by putting a D next to images and using the D as a link to the
            long description. This technique is not technology specific and can be used
            in any technology that supports links.</p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Bar chart</head>
         <description>
            <p>There is a bar chart on a Web page showing the sales for the top
                three salespeople.</p>
            <p>The short text alternative says "October sales chart for top three
                salespeople."</p>
            <p>Immediately after the non-text content is a small image denoting a
                long description. The alternate text for the image is "Long
                description of chart". The image links to the bottom of the page
                where there is a section titled "Description of charts on this
                page". The link points to this specific description: "Sales for
                October show Mary leading with 400 units. Mike follows closely with
                389. Chris rounds out our top 3 with sales of 350. [end of
                description]"</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Bar chart - in non-HTML technology where user agent "back"
              is not supported for security reasons.</head>
         <description>
            <p>There is a bar chart on a Web page showing the sales for the top
                three salespeople.</p>
            <p>The short text alternative says "October sales chart for top three
                salespeople."</p>
            <p>Immediately after the non-text content is a small image denoting the
                long description. The alternate text for the image is "Long
                description of chart". The image links to another page titled
                "Description of charts in October Sales Report". The description
                link points to this specific description: "Sales for October show
                Mary leading with 400 units. Mike follows closely with 389. Chris
                rounds out our top 3 with sales of 350. End of description.
                <code><![CDATA[<link>]]></code>Back to Sales Chart<code><![CDATA[</link>]]></code>"</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Caption used as link</head>
         <description>
            <p>There is a chart. The figure caption immediately below the chart
                serves as a link to the long description. The Title attribute of the
                link makes it clear that this is a link to a long description.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Transcript of an audio-only file</head>
         <description>
            <p>There is a recording of a speech by Martin Luther King. Links to the
                audio file and the transcript appear side by side.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also/>
   </resources>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="G74"/>
      <relatedtech idref="H45"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>check for the presence of a link immediately before or after the
                  non-text content</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>check that the link is a valid link that points directly to the
                  long description of this particular non-text content.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>check that the long description conveys the same information as
                  the non-text content</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>check for the availability of a link or back function to get the
                  user back to the original location of the non-text content</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <p>All 4 of the above are true</p>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
