<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="G74">
   <short-name>Providing a long description in text near the non-text content, with a
          reference to the location of the long description in the short description</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>Applies to all technologies</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="text-equiv-all" relationship="cosufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to provide a long description without
            requiring the user to jump off to another location for the description. It
            also allows all users to see the description which may be useful to anyone
            who might miss some features in the non-text content.</p>
      <p>With this technique, the long description is provided as part of the
            standard presentation (i.e., everyone receives it). The description is
            located near the non-text content but does not have to be the very next
            item. For example, there may be a caption under a chart with the long
            description provided in the following paragraph.</p>
      <p>The location of this long description is then provided within the short text
            alternative so the user knows where to look for it if they cannot view the
            non-text content.</p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Bar chart</head>
         <description>
            <p>There is a bar chart on a Web page showing the sales for the top
                three salespeople.</p>
            <p>The short text alternative says: "October sales chart for top three
                salespeople. Details in text following the chart:"</p>
            <p>The following is in the paragraph immediately below the chart. "Sales for October show Mary leading with 400 units. Mike follows closely with 389. Chris rounds out our top 3 with sales of 350."</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also/>
   </resources>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="G73"/>
      <relatedtech idref="H45"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>check that the short text alternative includes the location of
                  the long description</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Check that the long description is near the non-text content
                  both visually and in the linear reading order</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>check that the long description conveys the same information as
                  the non-text content</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <p>All 3 of the above are true</p>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
