<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="G76">
   <short-name>Providing a mechanism to request an update of the content instead of
          updating automatically</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>Any technology or combination of technologies that support automatic updates.</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="time-limits-postponed" relationship="sufficient"/>
      <success-criterion idref="consistent-behavior-no-extreme-changes-context"
                         relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to let the user control if and when
            content is updated, in order to avoid confusion or disorientation caused by
            automatic refreshes that cause a change of context. Users of screen readers
            may find automatic updates confusing because it is not always clear what is
            happening. When a page is refreshed, the screen reader's “virtual cursor",
            which marks the user's current location on the page, is moved to the top of
            the page. People who use screen magnification software and people with
            reading disabilities may also be disoriented when pages are refreshed
            automatically.</p>
      <p>Some content is frequently updated with new data or information. Some
            developers force automatic updates by inserting code in the content that
            causes the content to request a new copy of itself from the server. These
            updates and the frequency of these updates are not always under the user's
            control. Instead of triggering updates automatically, authors can provide a
            mechanism that allows the user to request an update of the content as
            needed.</p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <description>
            <p>In HTML, a developer can provide a button or link that
                allows the user to update the content. For example, on a
                page with news items located at http://www.example.com/news.jsp</p>
         </description>
         <code><![CDATA[
              <a href="news.jsp">Update this page</a>
            ]]></code>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <description>
            <p>In a Web interface for e-mail (Webmail), a developer can
                provide a button or link to fetch new incoming mails instead
                of updating automatically.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources/>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="G75"/>
      <relatedtech idref="SCR14"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Find mechanisms to update the content (if such a mechanism is
                  present).</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>For each such mechanism, check if it allows the user to request
                  an update.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>For each such mechanism, check if it can cause an automatic
                  update.</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>If #2 is true, then #3 is false.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
