<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="G81">
   <short-name>Providing a synchronized video of the sign language interpreter that can
          be displayed in a different viewport or overlaid on the image by the player</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>Applies to all synchronized media technologies that allow synchronization of
            multiple video streams</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="media-equiv-sign" relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to allow users who cannot hear or read
            text rapidly to be able to access synchronized media material without affecting the
            presentation of the material for all viewers.</p>
      <p>For those who communicate primarily in sign language it is sometimes less
            preferable and sometimes not possible for them to read and understand text
            at the rate it is presented in captions. For these latter individuals it is
            important to provide sign language presentation of the audio information.</p>
      <p>This technique accomplishes this by providing the sign language
            interpretation as a separate video stream that is synchronized with the
            original video stream. Depending on the player, this secondary video stream
            can be overlaid on top of the original video or displayed in a separate
            window. It may also be possible to enlarge the sign language interpreter
            separately from the original video to make it easier to read the hand, body
            and facial movements of the signer.</p>
      <p>NOTE: Since sign language is not usually a signed version of the printed
            language, the author has to decide which sign language to include. Usually
            the sign language of the primary audience would be used. If intended for
            multiple audiences, multiple languages may be used. See advisory technique
            for multiple sign languages.</p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <description>
            <p>Example 1: A university provides a synchronized sign language
                interpreter video stream that can be displayed, at the viewer's
                option, along with any of their education programs.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>Guidelines for the Production of Signing Books</p>
               <ulist>
                  <item>
                     <p>
                        <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                             href="http://www.sign-lang.uni-hamburg.de/signingbooks/deliver/d31/deliv_31_part3-2.html#3.2.2.6">"Sign Language presentation"</loc>
                      gives a
                      broad overview of issues to consider when filming
                      sign language interpreters. Includes discussion of
                      signing both written and spoken originals.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>Techniques for filming are discussed in
                      <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                             href="http://www.sign-lang.uni-hamburg.de/signingbooks/sbrc/grid/d71/guide12.htm">chapter 12, “Filming the Signer(s)"</loc>.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>Useful information about how to display the sign
                      language interpreter in relation to the original
                      synchronized media content is provided in
                      <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                             href="http://www.sign-lang.uni-hamburg.de/signingbooks/sbrc/grid/d71/guide13.htm">Chapter 13, "Editing"</loc>.</p>
                     <note>
                        <p>These techniques may need to be adapted for
                        Web-based presentation.</p>
                     </note>
                  </item>
               </ulist>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </see-also>
   </resources>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="G54"/>
      <relatedtech idref="SM13"/>
      <relatedtech idref="SM14"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Enable the display of the sign-language window in the player.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Have someone watch the program who can hear and is familiar with
                  the sign language being used.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Check to see if there is a sign language interpreter on screen
                  or in a separate window.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Check to see that dialogue and important sounds are being conveyed
                  by the interpreter and are synchronized with the audio.</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>#3 and #4 are true</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
