<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="G9">
   <short-name>Creating captions for live synchronized media</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>Applies to all technologies that present audio visual information.</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="media-equiv-real-time-captions" relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to allow users who cannot hear to be able
            to access real-time synchronized media broadcasts. It is more difficult to create
            accurate real-time captions because there is little time to correct mistakes
            or to listen a second time or consult someone to be sure the words are
            accurately reproduced. It is also harder to simplify or paraphrase
            information if it is flowing too quickly.</p>
      <p>Real-time typing text entry techniques exist using stenographic and rapid
            typing technologies. Re-voicing speech-to-text (where a person listens to
            speech and then carefully re-voices it into a computer trained to their
            speech) is used today for telephone relay services and may be used in the
            future for captioning. Eventually speech-to-text with correction will be
            possible.</p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>Example 1: A television studio uses a real-time captioning service
                to create captions for its evening news online.</p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
   </examples>
   <resources/>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="G87"/>
      <relatedtech idref="G93"/>
      <relatedtech idref="G157"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Check that a procedure and policy are in place to ensure that captions are delivered in real-time.</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>Check #1 is true.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
