<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="G90">
   <short-name>Providing keyboard-triggered event handlers</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>Applies to all technologies where content includes functionality.</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="keyboard-operation-keyboard-operable" relationship="sufficient"/>
      <success-criterion idref="keyboard-operation-all-funcs" relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to permit individuals who rely on a keyboard or keyboard interface to access the functionality of the content. To do this, make sure that all event handlers triggered by non-keyboard UI events are also associated with a keyboard-based event, or provide redundant keyboard-based mechanisms to accomplish the functionality provided by other device-specific functions.</p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>
                <emph role="bold">Example 1: A drag and drop feature</emph>
                A photo application includes a "drag" and "drop" feature to allow users to re-order photographs in an on-line album for presentation as a slide show. It also includes a feature that allows users to select a photo and 'cut' and 'paste' the items into the list at the appropriate point using only the keyboard.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
                <emph role="bold">Example 2: A reorder feature</emph>
                A Web application that allows users to create surveys by dragging questions into position includes a list of the questions followed by a text field that allows users to re-order questions as needed by entering the desired question number.</p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
   </examples>
   <resources/>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="SCR2"/>
      <relatedtech idref="SCR20"/>
      <relatedtech idref="SCR35"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>check that all functionality can be accessed using only the keyboard</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>#1 is true</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
