<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="G92">
   <short-name>Providing long description for non-text content that serves the same
          purpose and presents the same information</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>Applies to all technologies</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="text-equiv-all" relationship="cosufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to provide a long text alternative that
            serves the same purpose and presents the same information as the original
            non-text content when a short text alternative is not sufficient.</p>
      <p>Combined with the short text alternative, the long description should be
            able to substitute for the non-text content. The short alternative
            identifies the non-text content; the long alternative provides the
            information. If the non-text content were removed from the page and
            substituted with the short and long descriptions, the page would still
            provide the same function and information.</p>
      <p>In deciding what should be in the text alternatives, the following questions
            are helpful.</p>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>Why is this non-text content here?</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>What information is it presenting?</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>What purpose does it fulfill?</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>If I could not use the non-text content, what words would I use to
                convey the same function and/or information?</p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <description>
            <p>A chart showing sales for October has a short text
                alternative of "October sales chart". The long description would
                read "Bar Chart showing sales for October. There are 6 salespersons.
                Maria is highest with 349 units. Frances is next with 301. Then
                comes Juan with 256, Sue with 250, Li with 200 and Max with 195. The
                primary use of the chart is to show leaders, so the description is
                in sales order."</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <description>
            <p>A line graph that shows average winter temperatures from
                the past 10 years includes a short text alternative of "Average
                winter temperatures 1996-2006." The long description includes the
                data table that was used to generate the line graph.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also/>
   </resources>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="G94"/>
      <relatedtech idref="H45"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Remove, hide, or mask the non-text content</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Display the long description</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Check that the long description conveys the same information
                  conveyed by the non-text content.</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>#3 is true.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
