<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="G96">
   <short-name>Providing textual identification of items that otherwise rely only on sensory information to be understood</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>All technologies that present description of a content rendering to the user.</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="content-structure-separation-understanding"
                         relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to ensure that items within a Web page are referenced in the content not only by shape, size, sound or location, but also in ways that do not depend on that sensory perception. For example, a reference may also describe the function of the item or its label.</p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <description>
            <p>A round button is provided on a form to submit the form and move onto the next step in a progression.  The button is labeled with the text "go."  The instructions state, "to submit the form press the round button labeled
                <emph>go</emph>
                ".  This includes both shape and textual information to locate the button.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <description>
            <p>Instructions for a Web page providing on-line training state, "Use the list of links to the right with the heading, 'Class Listing' to navigate to the desired on-line course."  This description provides location as well as textual clues to help find the correct list of links.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <description>
            <p>The following layout places a button in the lower right corner and indicates it by position. An indication of the text label clarifies which button to use for users who access a linearized version in which the position is not meaningful.</p>
         </description>
         <code><![CDATA[
              <table>
                <tbody>
                <tr>
                <td colspan="2">Push the lower right [Preview] button.</td>
                <td>
                <span style="background: ButtonFace; color: ButtonText; border: 
                medium outset ButtonShadow; 
                width: 5em; display: block; font-weight: bold; text-align: center;">
                Print</span>
                </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                <td>
                <span style="background: ButtonFace; color: ButtonText; border: 
                medium outset ButtonShadow; 
                width: 5em; display: block; font-weight: bold; text-align: center;">
                Cancel</span>
                </td>
                <td>
                <span style="background: ButtonFace; color: ButtonText; border: 
                medium outset ButtonShadow; 
                width: 5em; display: block; font-weight: bold; text-align: center;">
                OK</span>
                </td>
                <td>
                <span style="background: ButtonFace; color: ButtonText; border: 
                medium outset ButtonShadow; 
                width: 5em; display: block; font-weight: bold; text-align: center;">
                Preview</span>
                </td>
                </tr>
                </tbody>
                </table>
              ]]><!--BBC: Add a working example here? --><![CDATA[
              
            ]]></code>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources/>
   <related-techniques/>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <p>Find all references in the Web page that mention the shape, size, or position of an object.  For each such item:</p>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Check that the reference contains additional information that allows the item to be located and identified without any knowledge of its shape, size, or relative position.</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>Check #1 is true.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
