<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="SL18">
   <short-name>Providing Text Equivalent for Nontext Silverlight Controls With AutomationProperties.Name</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p use-id="silverlight.applicability.general"/>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="text-equiv-all" relationship="sufficient"/>
      <success-criterion idref="navigation-mechanisms-refs" relationship="cosufficient"/>
      <success-criterion idref="navigation-mechanisms-link" relationship="sufficient"/>
      <success-criterion idref="ensure-compat-rsv" relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <ua-issues>
      <ua-issue use-id="silverlight.ua-issue.general"/>
   </ua-issues>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to use the Silverlight <prop>AutomationProperties.Name</prop> property
    				to provide a short text alternative for controls that do not otherwise
    				contain text. The text is intended to provide human-readable identifiers
    				and short-descriptions or user instructions for accessibility frameworks,
    				which can then be reported to assistive technologies. </p>
      <p>"Control" in this technique refers to any element that is
    				based on the Silverlight <obj>Control</obj> class, and is keyboard-focusable
    				either by user action or calling focus to the control programmatically.
    				The non-text control in question might be something like a button that
    				communicates information using only an icon or image. For example,
    				a triangle image rotated 90 degrees clockwise is commonly used in many
    				user interfaces to indicate a "Play"   button control. This "Play" icon
    				mimics interface metaphors from many non-software consumer products,
    				and is often presented in a user interface without any nearby visible
    				text information that explains the purpose of the control. Another
    				example is a "thumbnail" metaphor where a small image serves
    				as a control that can be activated, and where the action results in
    				the display of a larger version of the same image, or enters an editing
    				mode that loads the same image. </p>
      <p>For cases of controls such as buttons that invoke actions, the text
    				alternative also identifies link purpose. </p>
      <p>In Silverlight, a text-only identifier for any control can be set
    				specifically as <prop>AutomationProperties.Name</prop> on the parent
    				control. Silverlight control compositing techniques enable either per-control
    				images that are specified by the application author, or a general-purpose
    				image/icon for a control that is part of the control's template and
    				displays that way by default. The Silverlight API <prop>AutomationProperties.Name</prop> directly
    				sets <prop>Name</prop> in the UI Automation tree. The properties
    				in the UI Automation tree are reported to assistive technologies, when
    				the assistive technology implements behavior that acts as a UI Automation
    				client (or as an MSAA client, which relies on the UIA-MSAA bridge). </p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Applying a text alternative for an icon Button with
    					XAML</head>
         <description>
            <p>Application authors can specify the <prop>AutomationProperties.Name</prop> attribute
    						on the <obj>Button</obj> element, and leave accessibility information
    						for the composited <obj>Image</obj> content unspecified. It is
    						the button and its action that is relevant to users, not the non-interactive <obj>Image</obj> component.
    						The value provided for <prop>AutomationProperties.Name</prop> is
    						a meaningful text alternative for the action conveyed by the button's
    						icon/image, but where the functionality is conceptually embodied in
    						the button and not its images or other constituent parts in compositing
    						or visual design. </p>
            <codeblock xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[ <Button
   Height="20" Width="50"
   AutomationProperties.Name="Pause Media">
   <Image Height="12" Width="12" Source="/icon_pause.png"/>
 </Button>
]]></codeblock>
            <p>This example is shown in operation in the <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    href="ButtonNontextTextCompositionTestPage.html"
                    linktype="examples">working example of Button Text Alternative</loc>.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/ff400332%28VS.95%29.aspx">Automation
    					Properties for Accessibility Support in UI</loc> 
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/system.windows.automation.automationproperties.name%28VS.95%29.aspx">AutomationProperties.Name
    					Attached Property</loc> 
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Tools: <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://firstfloorsoftware.com/silverlightspy">SilverlightSpy</loc> or <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://uiautomationverify.codeplex.com/">UIAVerify</loc> 
               </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </see-also>
   </resources>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="SL30"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <head>Accessibility framework view </head>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p> Using a browser that supports Silverlight, open an HTML page that
    					references a Silverlight application through an object tag. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Use a verification tool that is capable of showing the full accessibility
    						framework tree, and an object’s "Name" text alternative
    						as part of the tree. Verify that all interactive elements such as
    						buttons without visible text provide a human-readable text identifier "Name" in
    						the automation tree. </p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <p>#2 is true. </p>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
   <tests>
      <head>Screen Reader</head>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p> Using a browser that supports Silverlight, open an HTML page that
    					references a Silverlight application through an object tag. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Engage the screen reader. Press TAB to traverse the tab sequence
    						inside the Silverlight content area to focus to a composite control
    						that has no visible text, but has an <prop>AutomationProperties.Name</prop> applied. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Check that the "Name" as applied to the control instance,
    							along with the class name of the named control, is read by the screen
    							reader. </p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <p>#3 is true. </p>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
   <admin>
      <source>
         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
              href="http://trace.wisc.edu/wcag_wiki/index.php?title=Providing_Text_Equivalent_for_Nontext_Silverlight_Controls_With_AutomationProperties.Name"/>
      </source>
   </admin>
</technique>
