<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="SL21">
   <short-name>Replacing A Silverlight Timed Animation With a Nonanimated Element</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p use-id="silverlight.applicability.general"/>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="time-limits-required-behaviors" relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <ua-issues>
      <ua-issue use-id="silverlight.ua-issue.general"/>
   </ua-issues>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to replace a timed Silverlight
    				animation with a non-timed user interface element that presents equivalent
    				information. This is useful in cases where the Silverlight animation
    				is a timed animation that may contain information that the user wants
    				to see without a time limit, such as crawling text in a text area.
    				The animated version of information in the user interface element can
    				instead be swapped out for an equivalent static element. </p>
      <p>The Silverlight animation system is generalized such that nearly any
    				Silverlight property of type <obj>Double</obj>, <obj>Point</obj> or <obj>Color</obj> can
    				be animated, or a property can cycle through discrete object values.
    				Thus the possibilities for which properties in the user interface can
    				be animated are quite broad. The general technique shown can be used
    				to stop any animation. </p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Stopping an animation that is scrolling text, replacing the animation with a full text alternative </head>
         <description>
            <p>This example has a UI definition in XAML and interaction logic in C#. The following is the basic UI in XAML. </p>
            <codeblock xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[<UserControl x:Class="StopAnimation.MainPage"
   xmlns="http://schemas.microsoft.com/winfx/2006/xaml/presentation"
   xmlns:x="http://schemas.microsoft.com/winfx/2006/xaml"
xmlns:sys="clr-namespace:System;assembly=mscorlib">
   <UserControl.Resources>
       <ImageBrush x:Key="Stars" ImageSource="/stars.jpg" Stretch="Fill"/>
       <Storyboard x:Key="crawl">
           <DoubleAnimation From="700" To="-100" Duration="0:0:20"
             Storyboard.TargetName="crawltext" Storyboard.TargetProperty="(Canvas.Top)"/> 
       </Storyboard>
       <sys:String x:Key="crawlText">
           Episode IV, A NEW HOPE It is a period of civil war. Rebel spaceships, striking from a hidden base, 
           have won their first victory against the evil Galactic Empire. During the battle, Rebel spies managed 
           to steal secret plans to the Empire’s ultimate weapon, the DEATH STAR, an armored space station with 
           enough power to destroy an entire planet. Pursued by the Empire’s sinister agents, Princess Leia 
           races home aboard her starship, custodian of the stolen plans that can save her people and restore 
           freedom to the galaxy….
       </sys:String>
   </UserControl.Resources>
   <StackPanel x:Name="LayoutRoot"
   Background="{StaticResource Stars}"
   Height="600" Width="800">
       <Button Width="200"
   Click="Button_Click">Stop crawling text, display fixed text</Button>
       <Canvas Name="CrawlPanel" Width="605" Height="595" >
           <Canvas.Projection>
               <PlaneProjection RotationX="-75"/>
           </Canvas.Projection>
           <Canvas.Clip>
               <RectangleGeometry Rect="0 0 600 600"/>
           </Canvas.Clip>
           <TextBlock Text="{StaticResource crawlText}"
   TextWrapping="Wrap" FontSize="20"
   Width="300" Canvas.Left="150" Name="crawltext"
   Foreground="Goldenrod"/>
       </Canvas>
   </StackPanel>
</UserControl>
]]></codeblock>
            <p>The following is the C# logic. In this example, the animation starts
    						automatically. When the user activates the control (the <obj>Button</obj>),
    						the event handler stops the animation, removes the animated element
    						from the visual tree, and replaces it with a fixed text element that
    						presents all text at once. Because it is a <obj>TextBox</obj>,
    						assistive technologies could identify the newly introduced text element
    						and present it, for example read the text in a screen reader. </p>
            <codeblock xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[       public MainPage()
       {
           InitializeComponent();
           (this.Resources["crawl"] as Storyboard).Begin();
       }
       private void Button_Click(object sender, RoutedEventArgs e)
       {
           (this.Resources["crawl"] as Storyboard).Stop();
           LayoutRoot.Children.Remove(CrawlPanel);
           TextBox tb = new TextBox();
           tb.IsReadOnly = true;
           tb.FontSize = 30;
           tb.TextWrapping = TextWrapping.Wrap;
           tb.Text = (string)this.Resources["crawlText"];
           LayoutRoot.Children.Add(tb);
       }
]]></codeblock>
            <p>This example is shown in operation in the <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    href="StopAnimationTestPage.html"
                    linktype="examples">working example of Stop Text Animation</loc>.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc189019(VS.95).aspx">Animation
    					Overview</loc> 
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc189069(VS.95).aspx">Working
    						with Animations Programmatically</loc> 
               </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </see-also>
   </resources>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p> Using a browser that supports Silverlight, open an HTML page that
    					references a Silverlight application through an object tag. For a
    					Silverlight application that has a time limit on interaction due
    					to an animated user interface element: </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Check for a mechanism to stop the time limit on interaction. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> When the mechanism is activated, check that the element that is
    						animated and resulting in a time limit is removed, and the time-limited
    						element is replaced with static content that is equivalent and does
    						not have a time limit. </p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <p>#3 is true. </p>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
   <admin>
      <source>
         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
              href="http://trace.wisc.edu/wcag_wiki/index.php?title=Replacing_A_Silverlight_Timed_Animation_With_a_Nonanimated_Element"/>
      </source>
   </admin>
</technique>
