<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="SL22">
   <short-name>Supporting Browser Zoom in Silverlight</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p use-id="silverlight.applicability.general"/>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p> Silverlight content in a user agent host that supports browser
    					zoom </p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="visual-audio-contrast-scale" relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <ua-issues>
      <ua-issue use-id="silverlight.ua-issue.general"/>
      <ua-issue>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p> Not all user agents implement a browser zoom feature. Of those
    				that do as of 30 March 2011, best results are obtained when the
    				user agent is Internet Explorer or Firefox. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Note that on Firefox, the Ctrl+(+) accelerator for browser zoom
    					may not work due to an issue where if the plugin (Silverlight) has
    					focus, it traps all keyboard events, even those that would ordinarily
    					be the user agent's set of accelerators. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Some versions of Firefox have a browser zoom mode that zooms text
    						only. This functionality is based on text by an HTML definition,
    						so selecting this option does not zoom any Silverlight content (whether
    						it is text by any Silverlight definition, or not.) </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Internet Explorer version 8 has an "AutoZoom" feature
    							that is based on operating system DPI. Silverlight accounts for this
    							through a native sizing behavior, but that behavior is not relevant
    							for this technique because the DPI settings are not typically used
    							as a primary technique by Web technology users for accessibility
    							purposes. DPI is more relevant to device choices, or specific operating
    							system features. </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </ua-issue>
   </ua-issues>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to support or anticipate existing
    				browser zoom features effectively when users interact with the Silverlight
    				application. This technique explains how the Silverlight content area
    				reacts to the browser zoom feature implemented by some user agent hosts.
    				Silverlight content and layout properties are based on physical screen
    				pixel measurements. When the browser zoom is engaged, Silverlight content
    				scales correctly for the zoom factor, and uses the same zoom factor
    				as any surrounding HTML content. </p>
      <p>Browser zoom is relevant for accessibility and Silverlight because
    				it is likely to be the zoom /scaling feature enabled by the browser
    				host that Web technology users are the most familiar with as a technique
    				for increasing the text size in Web content. </p>
      <section id="SL22_legacy">
         <head> Legacy behavior in Silverlight version 2 </head>
         <p>Built-in support for browser zoom was introduced as a feature in Silverlight
    					version 3. Older documents on the Web might describe techniques that
    					were relevant for Silverlight version 2, where dealing with browser
    					zoom required JavaScript handling of the <event>Resized</event> event,
    					and developers manually applied a <obj>ScaleTransform</obj> to Silverlight
    					content to scale it up. Silverlight has a "quirks mode"   that
    					detects existing handlers that might still use the older techniques.
    					Built-in zoom not active in these cases, so that applications can avoid
    					doubling or otherwise mishandling the user agent's zooming behavior. </p>
      </section>
      <section id="SL22_disable-zoom">
         <head> Deliberately disabling browser zoom in Silverlight applications </head>
         <p>Silverlight also provides the ability to disable the built-in browser
    					zoom handling and rendering behavior. This is sometimes done in order
    					to suppress some of the aliasing and distortion artifacts that host-level
    					scaling can introduce, particularly for video content or certain uses
    					of text. In these cases, application authors might consider other Silverlight
    					techniques for scaling the user interface, perhaps specifically only
    					for the text elements on a page. When an application disables the built-in
    					zoom behavior and rendering for Silverlight content, the browser still
    					retains its zoom settings, and that setting applies to other content
    					outside of Silverlight such as the hosting HTML. </p>
      </section>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Verifying browser zoom, and checking the zoom factor</head>
         <description>
            <p>This example has a UI defined in XAML and logic defined in C#. The
    						UI shows the zoom factor, and also demonstrates what happens when built-in
    						browser zoom handling is deliberately disabled. Note that the zooming
    						factor as reported by the API is still retained even when Silverlight
    						built-in zoom scaling is disabled deliberately. The following is the
    						XAML UI: </p>
            <codeblock xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[<UserControl x:Class="BrowserZoom.MainPage"
   xmlns="http://schemas.microsoft.com/winfx/2006/xaml/presentation"
   xmlns:x="http://schemas.microsoft.com/winfx/2006/xaml"
>
   <StackPanel x:Name="LayoutRoot" Background="White">
       <TextBlock>Some text you can zoom.</TextBlock>
       <Button Click="Button_Click">Toggle built-in zoom handling</Button>
       <StackPanel Orientation="Horizontal">
           <Button Click="Button_Click_1">Query current zoom factor</Button>
           <TextBox IsReadOnly="true" Name="zoomf"
   Text="{Binding Path=reportZoom}"/>
       </StackPanel>
   </StackPanel>
</UserControl>
]]></codeblock>
            <p>The following is the C# logic: </p>
            <codeblock xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[   public partial class MainPage : UserControl
   {
       public MainPage()
       {
           InitializeComponent();
       }
       private void Button_Click(object sender, RoutedEventArgs e)
       {
           if (!Application.Current.Host.Settings.EnableAutoZoom == false) {
           Application.Current.Host.Settings.EnableAutoZoom = false;
           }
           else
           {
               Application.Current.Host.Settings.EnableAutoZoom = true;
           }
       }
       private void Button_Click_1(object sender, RoutedEventArgs e)
       {
           zoomf.Text = Application.Current.Host.Content.ZoomFactor.ToString();
       }
   }
]]></codeblock>
            <p>This example is shown in operation in the <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    href="BrowserZoomTestPage.html"
                    linktype="examples">working example of Browser Zoom</loc>.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/system.windows.interop.settings.enableautozoom%28VS.95%29.aspx">EnableAutoZoom
    					Property</loc> 
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc707824(VS.95).aspx">Silverlight
    						Accessibility Overview</loc> 
               </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </see-also>
   </resources>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="G142"/>
      <relatedtech idref="G179"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p> Using a browser that supports Silverlight, open an HTML page that
    					references a Silverlight application through an object tag. The browser
    					being used for the test must support a browser zoom feature, and
    					the feature must be turned on as a user preference. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Verify that the Silverlight application enables auto zoom (no
    						Silverlight application-specific code or markup has set EnableAutoZoom
    						API to false). </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Test the zooming feature of the user agent. Verify that browser
    							zoom factors apply to the Silverlight content. </p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <p>#2 and #3 are true. </p>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
   <admin>
      <source>
         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
              href="http://trace.wisc.edu/wcag_wiki/index.php?title=Silverlight_and_Browser_Zoom"/>
      </source>
   </admin>
</technique>
