<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="SL23">
   <short-name>Using A Style Switcher to Increase Font Size of Silverlight Text
    			Elements</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p use-id="silverlight.applicability.general"/>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="visual-audio-contrast-scale" relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <ua-issues>
      <ua-issue use-id="silverlight.ua-issue.general"/>
   </ua-issues>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to define style switching logic
    				for Silverlight. In particular, the intent is to use the style switcher
    				to change the font size of text elements. This technique could be used
    				only for specific elements, or could also be applied to the entire
    				Silverlight content area and all text elements therein (including elements
    				such as <obj>TextBlock</obj> that are technically not controls).
    				Examples are provided for these two cases. </p>
      <p>The property to style or otherwise change is the <prop>FontSize</prop> property.
    				Primarily, this is done using the API <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
              href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/system.windows.controls.control.fontsize%28VS.95%29.aspx">Control.FontSize</loc>,
    				but developers can also use similar properties on other objects that do not
    				derive from <obj>Control</obj> (examples: <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
              href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/system.windows.controls.textblock.fontsize%28VS.95%29.aspx">TextBlock</loc>; <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
              href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/system.windows.controls.datagridtextcolumn.fontsize%28VS.95%29.aspx">DataGridTextColumn</loc>). </p>
      <p>Silverlight uses a style system whereby many properties that affect
    				UI appearance can be referred to and changed through a style resource.
    				The style resource overrides the default code implementation and the
    				default XAML template as provided by the Silverlight core implementation(or
    				a third party control author). A style enables an application author
    				to make a one-to-many change to property values in an efficient and
    				reversible way, and also to group multiple related property changes
    				as one unit of logic. Styles can be applied explicitly by referencing
    				them by name, or implicitly by associating a style with a class (which
    				then targets all instances of that class). This is analogous to how
    				CSS can either define styles globally for tags or uniquely for classids
    				and names. </p>
      <p>Silverlight styles are always written in XAML. Silverlight event handlers
    				are most often written in code (there are related techniques that can
    				react to states with event associations, defined in pure XAML, but
    				the specific style switching technique is most straightforward in code). </p>
      <section id="SL23_zoom-comparison">
         <head> Using this technique versus relying on browser zoom </head>
         <p>Silverlight supports browser zoom when viewed in browser hosts that
    					support a browser zoom feature. Specifically, Silverlight scales content
    					within its content area when the user engages browser zoom, based on
    					the browser zoom factor. However, not all browser hosts that Silverlight
    					supports have a browser zoom feature, and/or users might choose not
    					to use browser zoom. This technique presents an alternative technique
    					for font scaling in cases when relying on browser zoom is not viable
    					as a technique. Applications might use HTML DOM based logic to determine
    					the user agent string of the browser host, and use that as a determinant
    					of whether the user has browser zoom available as an option. If no
    					browser zoom feature exists for that user and their user agent, that
    					user could be served a version of the Silverlight application that
    					presents a UI and logic for sizing the fonts using the Silverlight
    					API, as described in this technique. </p>
         <p>For more information about Silverlight and browser zoom, see the technique <specref ref="SL22"/>. </p>
      </section>
      <section id="SL23_percent">
         <head> Sizing by percent </head>
         <p>Generally, sizing Silverlight <prop>FontSize</prop> values by
    					percentages is not recommended. Sizing by percentage produces non-integer
    					font size values, which in turn produce aliasing artifacts. The Silverlight
    					rendering routines for text work best when dealing with integer numbers.
    					The entire Silverlight rendering system is based on pixel measurements.
    					In particular, the behavior for text rendering produces optimized font
    					shaping and subpixel rendering for text areas, and this behavior is
    					based on the assumption that font unit measurements will be provided
    					by applications using whole pixel values. </p>
      </section>
      <section id="SL23_units">
         <head> Units for font sizing in Silverlight </head>
         <p>Font sizing in Silverlight is always specified by a unit measure of
    					pixels. Other unit measures such as ems or points that come from a
    					migrated UI definition in XAML would need to be unit-converted to all
    					use a purely numeric value, such that attribute values in XAML do not
    					not include unit identifier suffixes such as "px", "pt", "em",
    					or "cm". This note is most relevant if the application author
    					is porting or migrating a Windows Presentation Framework (WPF) application
    					to Silverlight, or is using a XAML-emitting design tool that is producing
    					general XAML UI definitions and not targeting a specific framework. </p>
      </section>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Style applied to all text elements within a RichTextBox
    					container</head>
         <description>
            <p>Variations of this example could be employed to offer more choices.
    						For example, multiple style switchers could be provided that gave three
    						or more fontsize choices. </p>
            <codeblock xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[<UserControl x:Class="StyleSwitcherFontSize.MainPage"
   xmlns="http://schemas.microsoft.com/winfx/2006/xaml/presentation"
   xmlns:x="http://schemas.microsoft.com/winfx/2006/xaml"
>
   <UserControl.Resources>
       <Style x:Key="BiggerRTBFonts" TargetType="RichTextBox">
           <Setter Property="FontSize" Value="24"/>
       </Style>
   </UserControl.Resources>

   <StackPanel x:Name="LayoutRoot" Background="White">
       <Button Click="Button_Click">Super size fonts!</Button>
       <Button Name="Undo" Click="Undo_Click">Make those big fonts stop!</Button>
       <RichTextBox IsReadOnly="True" Name="rtb1">
           <RichTextBox.Blocks>
               <Paragraph>Various test text</Paragraph>
               <Paragraph>
                   <Bold>Some bold test text</Bold></Paragraph>
               <Paragraph>
                   <Italic>Some italic</Italic>
               </Paragraph>
               <Paragraph FontFamily="Times New Roman">A different font, why not?</Paragraph>
           </RichTextBox.Blocks>
       </RichTextBox>
   </StackPanel>
</UserControl>
]]></codeblock>
            <p>The second listing is the C# code for the event handler . Note that
    						all it does is change a style property, using a value that keys into
    						the .Resources collection from XAML where the Style is defined. Another
    						event handler nulls out the style and returns values to defaults. </p>
            <codeblock xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[private void Button_Click(object sender, RoutedEventArgs e)
{
  rtb1.Style = this.Resources["BiggerRTBFonts"] as Style;
}
private void Undo_Click(object sender, RoutedEventArgs e)
{
   rtb1.Style = null;
}
]]></codeblock>
            <p>The following images show the original, and the applied style. </p>
            <p>
               <image>
                  <img xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       source="/WAI/WCAG20/Techniques/working-examples/SL23/originalfontsize.png"
                       height="119"
                       width="240"/>
                  <alt>Screen shot with standard fonts and a button to enlarge</alt>
               </image> 
            </p>
            <p>
               <image>
                  <img xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       source="/WAI/WCAG20/Techniques/working-examples/SL23/newfontsize.png"
                       height="257"
                       width="246"/>
                  <alt>Screen shot with enlarged fonts after activating button to enlarge</alt>
               </image> 
            </p>
            <p>This example is shown in operation in the <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    href="StyleSwitcherFontSizeTestPage.html"
                    linktype="examples">working example of Style Switcher Font Size</loc>.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Font size increase applied to all text content by applying
    				at UserControl level, and by percent increase logic</head>
         <description>
            <p>This example uses the inheritance characteristics of the <prop>FontSize</prop>
    						property that is available to all Silverlight controls. Rather than
    						using a style, this example uses a <prop>HoldEnd</prop> animation, to take advantage
    						of the "By" behavior of the animation system that can increment
    						an existing value by 2 (pixels) rather than replacing the value with
    						a fixed pixel value. </p>
            <p>The following is the XAML UI: </p>
            <codeblock xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[<UserControl x:Class="StyleSwitcherFontSize.MainPage"
   xmlns="http://schemas.microsoft.com/winfx/2006/xaml/presentation"
   xmlns:x="http://schemas.microsoft.com/winfx/2006/xaml"
   Name="rootcontrol">
   <UserControl.Resources>
       <Storyboard x:Key="BySize">
           <DoubleAnimation Storyboard.TargetName="rootcontrol" Storyboard.TargetProperty="FontSize" By="2" FillBehavior="HoldEnd" Duration="0"/>
       </Storyboard>
   </UserControl.Resources>
   <StackPanel x:Name="LayoutRoot" Background="White">
       <Button Click="Button_Click">Super size fonts!</Button>
       <Button Name="Undo" Click="Undo_Click">Make those big fonts stop!</Button>
       <TextBox Text="Various test text"/>
       <TextBox FontWeight="Bold" Text="Some bold test text"/>
       <TextBox FontStyle="Italic" Text="Some italic"/>
       <TextBox FontFamily="Times New Roman" Text="A different font, why not?"/>
   </StackPanel>
</UserControl>
]]></codeblock>
            <p>The following are the C# event handlers. </p>
            <codeblock xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[private void Button_Click(object sender, RoutedEventArgs e)
{
   (this.Resources["BySize"] as Storyboard).Begin();
}
private void Undo_Click(object sender, RoutedEventArgs e)
{
   (this.Resources["BySize"] as Storyboard).Stop();
}
]]></codeblock>
            <p>
                This example is shown in operation in the <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    href="ByAnimationFontSizeTestPage.html"
                    linktype="examples">working example of By Animation Font Size</loc>.
              </p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/system.windows.style%28VS.95%29.aspx">Style
    					Class</loc> 
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc189010(VS.95).aspx">Text
    					and Fonts</loc> 
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc189019(VS.95).aspx">Animation
    						Overview</loc> 
               </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </see-also>
   </resources>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="C29"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p> Using a browser that supports Silverlight, open an HTML page that
    					references a Silverlight application through an object tag. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Verify that the application provides a control that can increase
    						font size. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Activate the control, and check that the font sizes increase. </p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <p>#2 and #3 are true. </p>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
   <admin>
      <source>
         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
              href="http://trace.wisc.edu/wcag_wiki/index.php?title=Using_A_Style_Switcher_to_Increase_Font_Size_of_Silverlight_Text_Elements"/>
      </source>
   </admin>
</technique>
