<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="SL25">
   <short-name>Using Controls and Programmatic Focus to Bypass Blocks of Content
    			in Silverlight</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p use-id="silverlight.applicability.general"/>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="navigation-mechanisms-skip" relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <ua-issues>
      <ua-issue use-id="silverlight.ua-issue.general"/>
   </ua-issues>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to use the combination of Silverlight
    				control activation and programmatic focus to enable the user to skip
    				regions of content in a Silverlight application user interface. </p>
      <p>The control that the user activates should clearly indicate that its
    				purpose is to skip content, so that the resulting programmatic focus
    				shift is not interpreted as an undesired change of context. </p>
      <p>The object to call focus to (the receiver of focus after the user-initiated
    				action is triggered) has to be a <obj>Control</obj> in the Silverlight
    				programming model. This is because the <function>Focus</function> method
    				must be called on the target, and therefore the target must inherit
    				the <obj>Control</obj> class. So, an application author might
    				call focus to a read-only <obj>TextBox</obj>, or perhaps a <obj>RichTextBox</obj>,
    				depending on the purpose of the Silverlight application and its user
    				interface design. You can also focus a <obj>UserControl</obj>,
    				for cases where the area to call focus to represents a custom control
    				implementation. </p>
      <section>
         <head> Setting TabIndex (not recommended) </head>
         <p>Silverlight provides a <prop>TabIndex</prop> attribute that can
    					be used to override the default-generated tab sequence. Do not attempt
    					to adjust tab index as a technique for getting past content blocks.
    					Doing so will create a focus order that does not match the apparent
    					visual order, as described in <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                 href="navigation-mechanisms-focus-order"
                 linktype="understanding">SC
    					2.4.3</loc>. </p>
      </section>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <head>User-enabled control that programmatically sets focus</head>
         <description>
            <p>The following is the XAML for the user interface. </p>
            <codeblock xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[   <StackPanel Name="LayoutRoot">
       <Button Name="bypassbtn1" Click="bypassbtn1_Click">Skip menus, go to main page content</Button>
       <!intervening content-->
       <StackPanel>
           <RichTextBox Name="rtb_MainContent" IsReadOnly="True">
           <Paragraph>Here is the main content ....</Paragraph>
           </RichTextBox>
       </StackPanel>
   </StackPanel>
   ]]></codeblock>
            <p>The following is the event handler that forces focus. </p>
            <codeblock xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[       private void bypassbtn1_Click(object sender, RoutedEventArgs e)
       {
           rtb_MainContent.Focus();
       }
]]></codeblock>
            <p>This example is shown in operation in the <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    href="ProgrammaticFocusTestPage.html"
                    linktype="examples">working example of Programmatic Focus</loc>.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc903954(VS.95).aspx">Focus
    					Overview</loc> 
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc707824(VS.95).aspx">Silverlight
    						Accessibility Overview</loc> 
               </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </see-also>
   </resources>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="G123"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p> Open the test HTML page for a Silverlight application. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Check for a control that indicates that activating that control
    					can skip to some particular region of the content. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Activate that control. Verify that activating the control causes
    						focus to go to that region, and that a repeated block or blocks of
    						content are skipped. </p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <p>#2 and #3 are true. </p>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
   <admin>
      <source>
         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
              href="http://trace.wisc.edu/wcag_wiki/index.php?title=Using_Controls_and_Programmatic_Focus_to_Bypass_Blocks_of_Content_in_Silverlight"/>
      </source>
   </admin>
</technique>
