<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="SL28">
   <short-name>Using Separate Text-Format Text Captions for MediaElement Content</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p use-id="silverlight.applicability.general"/>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="media-equiv-captions" relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <ua-issues>
      <ua-issue use-id="silverlight.ua-issue.general"/>
   </ua-issues>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to use text captioning that comes
    				from a separate text file, synchronize the captions with the media
    				in a Silverlight <obj>MediaElement</obj>, and display the captions
    				in Silverlight. </p>
      <p>There are two variations of the general theme of implementing Silverlight
    				media player controls to work with external timed text: using built-in
    				capabilities of the Microsoft Expression Encoder tool, and using parsing
    				code that consumes caption as a raw file format and converts that format
    				into the Silverlight API's <obj>TimelineMarkers</obj> representation.
    				This technique primarily addresses how to use the Expression Encoder
    				technique, along with media player templates that are also provided
    				by Expression Encoder or related Silverlight SDKs such as the Smooth
    				Streaming SDK. </p>
      <p>At a pure architecture level, Silverlight uses the <obj>TimelineMarkers</obj> API
    				to display caption text at synchronized times. The Expression Encoder
    				and Expression Blend tools provide a front end to drive the <obj>TimelineMarkers</obj> API
    				for the supported formats. The intention of the architecture is so
    				that Silverlight as a run-time has a base architecture that could potentially
    				use any existing or future timed text format, but the tools for Silverlight
    				(rather than built-in features of the runtime) provide the optimized
    				workflow for producing captioned media projects. </p>
      <p>A procedure for using the Expression Encoder and Expression Blend
    				tools to produce a Silverlight media player application that can consume
    				timed text in TTML format is provided as Example 1 in this technique.
    				(Note: prior to the approval of TTML by W3C, DFXP was a format that
    				used much of the eventual TTML vocabulary. In tools that predate TTML,
    				this format is often identified as DFXP.) </p>
      <p>A purely code-based parsing technique, with the goal of avoiding Expression
    				Encoder dependencies, is necessarily more complex. This is because
    				there are multiple issues to solve: </p>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p> Obtaining and validating the timed text file </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Parsing the format into general information items like timings,
    				text, format etc. that are either consumable directly in a Silverlight
    				API, or useful as intermediates </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Using the timecode information to create <obj>TimelineMarker</obj> representations
    					for each timed text entity </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Associating the <obj>TimelineMarkers</obj> with media loaded
    						by the player </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Finding a place to store the additional formatting that is conveyed,
    							including the text and any formatting </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Handling events from <obj>TimelineMarkers</obj> in the media
    								player, in such a way that text and formatting behavior can be retrieved
    								and presented in the Text part of the player UI </p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
      <section id="SL28_formats">
         <head> Text Captioning Formats </head>
         <p>There are several existing text-based formats that are used for text
    					captioning of prerecorded media. The following are supported as formats
    					if using the Expression Encoder tool as shown in Example 1 (where the
    					Expression Encoder generated Silverlight application uses the existing
    					Silverlight MediaPlayerTemplate and the TimedTextLibrary component.)
    					For more information on which timed text formats can be referenced
    					in an Expression Encoder project, see <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                 href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/ff723862%28Expression.40%29.aspx">About
    						Captioning (Expression documentation on MSDN)</loc>. </p>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p> SAMI (Synchronized Accessible Media Interchange). For more information
    					on this format, see <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/ms971327.aspx">Understanding
    						SAMI 1.0</loc> on MSDN. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> SMIL (Synchronized Multimedia Integration Language). For more
    							information on this format, see <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2008/REC-SMIL3-20081201/">Synchronized
    								Multimedia Integration Language (SMIL 3.0)</loc> on W3C site. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> TT (Timed Text) in particular TTML (Timed Text Markup Language).
    									For more information, see <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.w3.org/TR/ttaf1-dfxp/">Timed
    										Text Markup Language (TTML) 1.0</loc> on W3C site. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> TTML (previously known as DFXP). This is the Timed Text format
    											used by Adobe Flash for its FLVPlaybackCaptioning component,
    											and is produced by a variety of tools and full-service captioning
    											vendors. For more information, see <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.adobe.com/accessibility.htmlproducts/flash/captions.html">Captions</loc> on
    											the Adobe site. </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
         <p>The following are not supported directly in Expression Encoder templates.
    					To use these formats, application authors would have to write parsing
    					logic, as shown in Example 2: </p>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p> MPEG Part 17 / 3GPP Timed Text. For more information, see <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.iso.org/iso/iso_catalogue/catalogue_tc/catalogue_detail.htm?csnumber=39478">ISO/IEC
    					14496-17:2006</loc> on ISO site. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Other formats that have not realized wide adoption, for example
    						Universal Subtitle Format. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> In addition to these formats, other formats for device-specific
    							recorded media (such as DVD encoded tracks) could be cross-purposed
    							for use by streaming/online media. </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
         <p>Rather than build the parsing logic for all these formats into the
    					Silverlight runtime, or choosing just one of these formats to support,
    					the Silverlight design for text captioning at the core level instead
    					makes the <obj>TimelineMarkers</obj> property of a <obj>MediaElement</obj> writeable,
    					independently of the value of <prop>Source</prop>. The format of
    					each <obj>TimelineMarker</obj> in the collection is very simple:
    					a time value expressed in the format, and the text value of the text
    					for that synchronized caption. The time format for <obj>TimelineMarkers</obj> is
    					documented as <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                 href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/system.windows.media.timelinemarker.time%28VS.95%29.aspx">TimelineMarker
    						reference on MSDN</loc>. Converting timed text formats to <obj>TimelineMarkers</obj> form
    					as consumed by the Silverlight core can be done by following any of
    					the following application design patterns: </p>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p> Authoring the project using Expression Encoder, and using the
    					Expression MediaPlayerTemplate as the media player UI. In this case,
    					Expression produces a Silverlight application that includes assemblies
    					that are generated from code templates. The default build of the
    					project provides a working library that handles all tasks related
    					to timed-text format conversion, from the formats as documented at <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/ff723862%28Expression.40%29.aspx">About
    						Captioning (Expression documentation on MSDN)</loc>. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> The templates of an Expression Encoder project can also be edited,
    							either editing the XAML for the UI by altering the template, or by
    							altering the C# code files that define various aspects of the media
    							player logic, including the timed text format parsers. Then the project
    							can be rebuilt using the desired customizations. Using this technique,
    							it is possible to adapt the code to support timed text formats that
    							are not directly supported in the Expression Encoder project UI. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Using a 3rd party media player implementation that also includes
    								a codebase for processing timed text formats, producing <obj>TimelineMarkers</obj>,
    								and displaying the captions in the player-specific UI. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Including a library that handles just the format parsing, and
    									using APIs of this library as part of the Silverlight application
    									code-behind. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Writing all logic that is necessary for timed text parsing AND
    										application UI display, and including it all in the main Silverlight
    										application library. </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </section>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Using Expression Encoder and Expression Blend to produce
    					a Silverlight media player project from tool output and templates</head>
         <description>
            <p>By far the simplest technique for incorporating existing timed-text
    						information is to use Microsoft Expression Encoder and the media player
    						templates that an Expression Encoder project produces by default. You
    						can use timed text in any of the following formats: DFXP, SAMI, SRT,
    						SUB, and LRC. Associating a caption file with a media source is done
    						as an "import" operation in the Expression Encoder tool.
    						However, the   "import" does not necessarily mean that the
    						timed text file is integrated into the media stream; Silverlight authors have the option
    						to preserve the file separation. This is useful if the application is obtaining
    						timed text from a third party source in real-time, or if Silverlight authors have a
    						production pipeline that makes it difficult to have the captioning
    						ready in time to be encoded in the stream along with the audio-visual
    						source files. For third-party timed text files that are served directly
    						from the third party's HTTP servers, it can be useful to supply a dummy
    						URL in the initial project encoding. The output of the Expression Encoder
    						project parameterizes many of the project settings at the HTML level.
    						This makes it possible to change the URL at any time prior to deployment
    						without having to rebuild the project. The following code is the HTML
    						output of a sample Expression Encoder project. Note the CaptionSources
    						node in the initparams; that is the information item that informs the
    						Expression Encoder templates where to find the timed text file. </p>
            <codeblock xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[     <object data="data:application/x-silverlight," type="application/x-silverlight" width="100%" height="100%">
       <param name="source" value="MediaPlayerTemplate.xap"/>
       <param name="onerror" value="onSilverlightError" />
       <param name="autoUpgrade" value="true" />
       <param name="minRuntimeVersion" value="4.0.50401.0" />
       <param name="enableHtmlAccess" value="true" />
       <param name="enableGPUAcceleration" value="true" />
       <param name="initparams" value='playerSettings = 
         <Playlist>
           <AutoLoad>true</AutoLoad>
           <AutoPlay>true</AutoPlay>
           <DisplayTimeCode>false</DisplayTimeCode>
           <EnableOffline>false</EnableOffline>
           <EnablePopOut>false</EnablePopOut>
           <EnableCaptions>true</EnableCaptions>
           <EnableCachedComposition>true</EnableCachedComposition>
           <StretchNonSquarePixels>NoStretch</StretchNonSquarePixels>
           <StartMuted>false</StartMuted>
           <StartWithPlaylistShowing>false</StartWithPlaylistShowing>
           <Items>
             <PlaylistItem>
             <AudioCodec></AudioCodec>
             <Description></Description>
             <FileSize>2797232</FileSize>
             <IsAdaptiveStreaming>false</IsAdaptiveStreaming>
             <MediaSource>thebutterflyandthebear.wmv</MediaSource>
             <ThumbSource></ThumbSource>
             <Title>thebutterflyandthebear</Title>
             <DRM>false</DRM>
             <VideoCodec>VC1</VideoCodec>
             <FrameRate>30.00012000048</FrameRate>
             <Width>508</Width>
             <Height>384</Height>
             <AspectRatioWidth>4</AspectRatioWidth>
             <AspectRatioHeight>3</AspectRatioHeight>
             <CaptionSources>
               <CaptionSource Language="English" LanguageId="eng" Type="Captions" Location="thebutterflyandthebear.eng.capt.dfxp"/>
             </CaptionSources>
           </PlaylistItem>
         </Items>
      </Playlist>'/>       
   </object>
   ]]></codeblock>
            <p>The templates include a library that handles any parsing requirements
    						for the chosen timed text format, both at the level of getting the
    						basic text and timing into the <obj>TimelineMarkers</obj> used
    						by the run-time <obj>MediaElement</obj>, and for preserving
    						a subset of format information that can reasonably be crossmapped
    						from the formatting paradigm of the source (typically HTML/CSS) into
    						the Silverlight text object model of the text element that displays
    						the captions in the running Silverlight application. </p>
            <p>The following is a brief description of the procedure for creating
    						a project that incorporates a separate timed text file. </p>
            <olist>
               <item>
                  <p> From the initial Expression Encoder screen, select New Project
    						from the File menu. </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p> In the <emph role="strong">Load a new project</emph> dialog, select <emph role="strong">Silverlight
    							Project</emph>. </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p> From the File menu, select Import. Choose the primary media source
    								file the project will use. </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p> In the Text tab, find the listing for the media source file. Click
    									the <emph role="strong">+</emph> icon to the right of the file name. This opens
    									a file dialog. </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p> Choose a timed text file to add to the project. </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p> Build the project. By default the project produces a complete
    										output folder. The folder includes the media player template XAP,
    										the timed text file as a separate file, and additional libraries
    										and XAPs that support the basic template and/or the timed text capabilities. </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p> Optionally, use the features in the Templates tab of Expression
    											Encoder to generate a template copy. You can edit the template copy
    											in other tools such as Expression Blend or Visual Studio, to change
    											the layout or behavior from the default media player template. Template
    											editing can address requirements such as applying a particular branding
    											or "look" to the player user interface. </p>
               </item>
            </olist>
            <p>The following is a screenshot of the Expression Encoder (version 4)
    						interface. The <emph role="strong">+</emph> icon mentioned in Step 4 is highlighted
    						in this screenshot with a red diamond. The <emph role="strong">Templates</emph> tab
    						mentioned in Step 7 is on the right side, top-middle. Note that all
    						tabs of an Expression user interface are dockable; the orientations
    						shown here are the default, but could be in different locations on
    						any given computer or configuration. </p>
            <p>
               <image>
                  <img xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       source="/WAI/WCAG20/Techniques/working-examples/SL28/encoder_scr.png"
                       height="768"
                       width="1024"/>
                  <alt>Expression Encoder screenshot</alt>
               </image> 
            </p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Code parses timed text; MediaElement handles MarkerReached,
    				displays marker text in application-defined TextBox</head>
         <description>
            <p>This example defines a very simple media player class that includes
    						a display surface, basic controls, and a text display for captions
    						as part of its default template. The usage code for this control in
    						XAML is simple, but only because the majority of the implementation
    						is present in the definition of the media player class. </p>
            <p>
    					The following is example usage XAML: </p>
            <codeblock xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[ <local:SimpleMediaPlayerWithTT Width="480" Height="360" CaptionUri="testttml.xml" MediaSourceUri="/xbox.wmv" />
    					]]></codeblock>
            <p>Note the attributes CaptionUri and SimpleMediaPlayerWithTT. Each
    						of these is a custom property of the media control class TTReader.
    						CaptionUri in particular references a URL, in this case a local URL
    						from the same server that serves the Silverlight XAP. The timed text
    						file could come from a different server also, but comes from a local
    						server in this example to conform to the behavior of the test file. </p>
            <p>The following is the generic.xaml default template for the media player
    						control. The template is mainly relevant for showing the named elements
    						that are shown in the initialization code. </p>
            <codeblock xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[               <ControlTemplate TargetType="local:SimpleMediaPlayerWithTT">
                   <Border Background="{TemplateBinding Background}"
                           BorderBrush="{TemplateBinding BorderBrush}"
                           BorderThickness="{TemplateBinding BorderThickness}">
                       <Grid x:Name="vroot">
                           <Grid.RowDefinitions>
                               <RowDefinition Height="*"/>
                               <RowDefinition Height="50"/>
                               <RowDefinition Height="80"/>
                           </Grid.RowDefinitions>
                           <MediaElement x:Name="player" AutoPlay="False"/>
                           <StackPanel Orientation="Horizontal" Height="50" Grid.Row="1">
                               <Button x:Name="player_play">Play</Button>
                               <Button x:Name="player_pause">Pause</Button>
                               <Button x:Name="player_stop">Stop</Button>
                           </StackPanel>
                           <ScrollViewer x:Name="scroller" Height="50" Grid.Row="2">
                           <TextBox IsReadOnly="True" x:Name="captions"/>
                           </ScrollViewer>
                       </Grid>
                   </Border>
               </ControlTemplate>
               ]]></codeblock>
            <p>The following is the initialization code that is for general infrastructure. <function>OnApplyTemplate</function> represents
    					the code wiring to the template-generated UI. </p>
            <codeblock xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[   public class SimpleMediaPlayerWithTT : Control
   {
       MediaElement player;
       TextBox captions;
       public SimpleMediaPlayerWithTT()
       {
           this.DefaultStyleKey = typeof(SimpleMediaPlayerWithTT);
       }
       public override void OnApplyTemplate()
       {
           base.OnApplyTemplate();
           player = this.GetTemplateChild("player") as MediaElement;
           captions = this.GetTemplateChild("captions") as TextBox;
           scroller = this.GetTemplateChild("scroller") as ScrollViewer;
           //event hookups and prop inits
           player.MediaOpened += new RoutedEventHandler(OnMediaOpened);
           player.MediaFailed += new EventHandler<ExceptionRoutedEventArgs>(OnMediaFailed);
           player.Source = this.MediaSourceUri;
           player.MarkerReached+=new TimelineMarkerRoutedEventHandler(player_MarkerReached);
           Button player_play = this.GetTemplateChild("player_play") as Button;
           player_play.Click += new RoutedEventHandler(player_play_click);
           Button player_pause = this.GetTemplateChild("player_pause") as Button;
           player_pause.Click += new RoutedEventHandler(player_pause_click);
           Button player_stop = this.GetTemplateChild("player_stop") as Button;
           player_stop.Click += new RoutedEventHandler(player_stop_click);
       }
       // mediaelement in template events
       void OnMediaOpened(object sender, RoutedEventArgs e)
       {
           LoadCaptions(captionUri);
       }
       void OnMediaFailed(object sender, ExceptionRoutedEventArgs e)
       {
       }
       void player_MarkerReached(object sender, TimelineMarkerRoutedEventArgs e)
       {
           captions.SelectedText = e.Marker.Text + "\n";
           scroller.ScrollToVerticalOffset(scroller.ScrollableHeight);
       }
       void player_play_click(object sender, RoutedEventArgs e)
       {
           player.Play();
       }
       void player_pause_click(object sender, RoutedEventArgs e)
       {
           player.Pause();
       }
       void player_stop_click(object sender, RoutedEventArgs e)
       {
           player.Stop();
       }
       // properties
       private Uri captionUri;
       public Uri CaptionUri
       {
           get { return captionUri; }
           set { captionUri = value; }
       }
       private Uri msUri;
       public Uri MediaSourceUri
       {
           get { return msUri; }
           set { msUri = value; }
       }
       ]]></codeblock>
            <p>The following is the logic that is particular to obtaining the separate
    						caption file. Some of this logic is referenced in the preceding template-specific
    						event handlers. This example uses the asynchronous <obj>WebClient</obj> technique
    						to request the file result of the <prop>CaptionUri</prop>. Make
    						sure to use <prop>AutoPlay</prop>=false or some other means to allow
    						time for the caption file to download before attempting to play the
    						media file. </p>
            <codeblock xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[       private void LoadCaptions(Uri captionURL)
       {
           WebClient wc = new WebClient();   // Web Client to download data files
           if (captionURL != null)
           {
               wc.DownloadStringCompleted +=
                   new DownloadStringCompletedEventHandler(OnDownloadStringCompleted);
               wc.DownloadStringAsync(captionURL);
           }
       }
       private void OnDownloadStringCompleted(object sender, DownloadStringCompletedEventArgs e)
       {
           if (!e.Cancelled && e.Error == null && e.Result != "")
           {
               string xml = e.Result.Trim();
               ParseCaptionData(new StringReader(xml));
           }
       }
       ]]></codeblock>
            <p>The actual parsing can be done using a combination of the "XML
    						to Linq" facilities of an optional Silverlight library, and
    						standard .NET Framework string format APIs from the Silverlight core.
    						An implementation is NOT provided here, due to length considerations.
    						TTML supports a number of profiles and capabilities. The basic pattern
    						to follow in the implementation is to obtain the necessary text and
    						timing information, and to pass it to a function that might resemble
    						the following code template. This code template takes the raw information,
    						generates a new <obj>TimelineMarker</obj>, and adds it to the
    						collection assigned to the active <obj>MediaElement</obj> as
    						identified by "player" in the application. </p>
            <codeblock xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[       public void AddMediaMarker(string time, string type, string data)
       {
           TimelineMarker marker = new TimelineMarker();
           marker.Time = new TimeSpan(0,0,(Convert.ToInt32(time.Trim())/1000));
           // this logic could vary depending on how time is formatted in the input string; this one assumes raw milliseconds
           marker.Type = type;
           marker.Text = data.Trim();
           player.Markers.Add(marker);
       }
]]></codeblock>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc189078(VS.95).aspx">Audio
    					and Video Overview</loc> 
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/system.windows.controls.mediaelement%28VS.95%29.aspx">MediaElement
    					Class</loc> 
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/system.windows.media.timelinemarker%28VS.95%29.aspx">TimelineMarker.Time</loc> 
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" href="http://amp.codeplex.com/">Accessible
    						Media Project</loc> - a reference implementation MediaPlayer control
    						from the Silverlight product team that includes several accessibility
    						features including captioning; note that the codebase might not be
    						updated to Silverlight version 4 </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </see-also>
   </resources>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="SL17"/>
      <relatedtech idref="SL16"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p> Using a browser that supports Silverlight, open an HTML page that
    					references a Silverlight application through an object tag. That
    					application plays media that is expected to have text captioning. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Check that the text area in the textbox shows captions for the
    						media, and that the captions synchronize with media in an expected
    						way. </p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <p>#2 is true. </p>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
   <admin>
      <source>
         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
              href="http://trace.wisc.edu/wcag_wiki/index.php?title=Using_Separate_Text-Format_Text_Captions_for_MediaElement_Content"/>
      </source>
   </admin>
</technique>
