<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="SL32">
   <short-name>Using Silverlight Text Elements for Appropriate Accessibility Role</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p use-id="silverlight.applicability.general"/>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="ensure-compat-rsv" relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <ua-issues>
      <ua-issue use-id="silverlight.ua-issue.general"/>
      <ua-issue>
         <p>JAWS version 12 misreports a read-only <obj>RichTextBox</obj> as   "edit",
    				despite it reporting its role as "document" to both UIA and
    				MSAA. Text is still read by JAWS 12, but users might expect that they
    				would be able to enter text in an element that JAWS 12 reports as edit,
    				whereas in fact they cannot enter text. </p>
      </ua-issue>
   </ua-issues>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to choose a Silverlight text container
    				that provides appropriate behavior and accessibility roles for different
    				types of text content. How those roles interact with existing assistive
    				technologies that are interpreting Silverlight under the larger concept
    				of being an "HTML control part" is also a factor in which
    				Silverlight text container should be used in an application's composition. </p>
      <p>Text containers can identified by role to accessibility frameworks,
    				and each type of Silverlight text container uses a different role.
    				Application authors should choose text containers that combine the
    				desired behavior in the user interface with an accessibility role that
    				can be consumed by existing assistive technology implementations. </p>
      <p>The Silverlight core libraries define the following classes that are
    				specifically intended as text containers: </p>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p> 
               <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/system.windows.controls.richtextbox%28VS.95%29.aspx">RichTextBox</loc> 
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 
               <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/system.windows.controls.textbox%28VS.95%29.aspx">TextBox</loc> 
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 
               <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/system.windows.controls.textblock%28VS.95%29.aspx">TextBlock</loc> 
            </p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
      <section id="SL32_programmatic">
         <head> UI Automation programmatic access </head>
         <p>For programming information that is relevant for how Silverlight application
    					authors produce the application, each text container has its own object
    					model/API. That API is documented on MSDN, specifically for each class <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                 href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/system.windows.controls.textbox%28VS.95%29.aspx">TextBox</loc>; <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                 href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/system.windows.controls.richtextbox%28VS.95%29.aspx">RichTextBox</loc>; <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                 href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/system.windows.controls.textblock%28VS.95%29.aspx">TextBlock</loc>.)
    					However, rather than using the Silverlight-specific object models,
    					most assistive technologies that are capable of reporting on Silverlight
    					will choose to use UI Automation (or MSAA) to obtain information about
    					the Silverlight elements in general. Text containers within the Silverlight
    					content are identified through UIA accessibility roles. This is because
    					the assistive technologies can use UI Automation to query for ANY relevant
    					text items from the content (and chrome) of the user agent / browser
    					host, not just those that come from Silverlight. That can include the
    					HTML content, items created from scripting, CSS or other plugin-internal
    					object models and so on. In other words, text from Silverlight is integrated
    					into the overall UI Automation view of the user agent host as the top-level
    					application in a platform view. Different types of "text" in
    					a general sense might appear as different UI Automation patterns, as
    					is described below. </p>
      </section>
      <section id="SL32_textbox">
         <head> TextBox </head>
         <p>A <obj>TextBox</obj> within the Silverlight content area is
    					reported to UI Automation as an Edit role (through MSAA, as Editable
    					Text). </p>
         <p>Edit controls are expected to implement the <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                 href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/system.windows.automation.provider.ivalueprovider%28VS.95%29.aspx">Value
    					pattern</loc> for UIA, so that the value of the edit area can be queried
    					or set by a client. Assistive technologies can use this value as
    					a text-string value for screen readers or other purposes. </p>
         <p>In typical user interface design, a form with an input field also
    					includes a label or other explanatory text that is proximally close
    					to the input field. In order to maintain proper reading order, the
    					label should typically appear immediately before the input field. This
    					general model should also be used for Silverlight user interface design.
    					For more information on labeling for <obj>TextBox</obj> controls,
    					see <specref ref="SL26"/>. </p>
      </section>
      <section id="SL32_richtextbox">
         <head> RichTextBox </head>
         <p>A <obj>RichTextBox</obj> within the Silverlight content area
    					is reported to UI Automation and MSAA as a Document role. </p>
         <p>A <obj>RichTextBox</obj> can either be set to be a read-only
    					control, or left as a read-write control. In the latter case, users
    					can insert a text cursor and make changes to the text. It is more common
    					in Silverlight programming to set the <obj>RichTextBox</obj> to
    					be read-only; in this scenario the reason for using <obj>RichTextBox</obj> is
    					because <obj>TextBlock</obj> did not offer the range of text
    					formatting options that are possible from a <obj>RichTextBox</obj>. </p>
         <p>In UIA, a document is generally expected to support the <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                 href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/system.windows.automation.provider.itextprovider%28VS.95%29.aspx">Text
    					pattern</loc> for UI Automation. However, to read the text from a <obj>RichTextBox</obj>,
    					the assistive technology does not necessarily have to implement code
    					that handles the entirety of the information that the Text pattern
    					reports. </p>
      </section>
      <section id="SL32_text-pattern">
         <head> More about the Text pattern </head>
         <p>The Text pattern provides APIs to iterate over the internal structure
    					of a document and return text ranges. Each such text range can be queried
    					for specific properties, and can return its plain text string value
    					to UI Automation. Ranges can also be programmatically adjusted by the <obj>TextPattern</obj>/<obj>TextRange</obj> APIs.
    					The following is a snippet of a Silverlight-specific UI Automation
    					tree utility to give a general idea of the APIs involved. Note that
    					these are not specifically Silverlight APIs; they are .NET Framework
    					APIs. .NET Framework or Windows Automation APIs are generally what
    					is used for programming a UI Automation client, which runs on a platform
    					runtime rather than the Silverlight runtime. Using the Text pattern
    					is generally what is necessary in order for an assistive technology
    					to obtain a comprehensive view of the "value" for a document
    					role object. </p>
         <codeblock xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[private void FindTheTextPatterns_Click(object sender, RoutedEventArgs e)
{
   if (allSilverlight != null && allSilverlight.Count>0)
   {
       //for simplicity just processing item 0, not assuming more than one SL control
       //on the page because this app controls the page being loaded
       AutomationElementCollection documentsList = allSilverlight[0].FindAll(TreeScope.Descendants,
           new PropertyCondition(AutomationElement.ControlTypeProperty,ControlType.Document)
   );
   for (int j=0; j< documentsList.Count;j++) {
       TextPattern targetTextPattern = 
         documentsList[j].GetCurrentPattern(TextPattern.Pattern) as TextPattern;
       if (targetTextPattern!=null) {
           TextPatternRange tr = targetTextPattern.DocumentRange;
           MessageBox.Show(tr.GetText(Int16.MaxValue));
       }
   }
}
private void GetAllSilverlight()
{
   allSilverlight = this._clientAppRootInstance.FindAll(TreeScope.Descendants,
      new PropertyCondition(AutomationElement.ClassNameProperty, "MicrosoftSilverlight"));
}
]]></codeblock>
         <p>MSAA has only limited possibilities for interacting with a Document
    				role, and MSAA code for attempting to do so is not shown. </p>
      </section>
      <section id="SL32_textblock">
         <head> TextBlock </head>
         <p>
            <obj>TextBlock</obj> is reported as a Text role in UI Automation. <obj>TextBlock</obj> has
    					several important characteristics: </p>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p> A <obj>TextBlock</obj> is always read-only; only the application
    					author can declare the text, users cannot change it. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> A <obj>TextBlock</obj> is not considered to be a true control
    						in the Silverlight object model (it is not a class derived from <obj>Control</obj>).
    						The practical implications of this to accessibility scenarios is
    						that a <obj>TextBlock</obj> is not in the default tab sequence,
    						cannot be manually added to any tab sequence, and cannot be keyboard-focused
    						either programatically or by the user. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> 
                  <obj>TextBlock</obj> has a deliberately limited range of
    							block / span formatting options. If the application author desires
    							a wider range of formatting options, for example supporting a "Paragraph" metaphor
    							for blocks of text, a read-only <obj>RichTextBox</obj> should
    							be used instead. </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
         <p>If the user relies solely on navigating a Silverlight application
    					using the TAB sequence, such navigation will skip over any <obj>TextBlock</obj> in
    					the interface. This could have implications for how users who use screen
    					readers can interact with the Silverlight content. Screen readers typically
    					read text only from the currently focused element in cases where the
    					user is moving through the TAB sequence or changing focus within the
    					application, and thus cannot read the text from a <obj>TextBlock</obj> in
    					such a mode. However, most screen readers also have modes for reading
    					text that is not necessarily focusable. These are generally the same
    					modes that screen readers use for a conventional non-interactive HTML
    					document text. For example, some screen readers support a mode that
    					reads text by line, or by word. These modes can read text from a <obj>TextBlock</obj>. </p>
      </section>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Structure from a container that has non-semantic role
    					in UI Automation, and TextBlock for text</head>
         <description>
            <p>If viewed as a UI Automation tree, the <obj>StackPanel</obj> and <obj>Grid</obj> do
    						not exist explicitly in the tree view, because they do not serve a
    						semantic role (only a presentation role). Rather, the tree consists
    						of the items that report some kind of semantic control type. The semantic
    						children of the containers are still reported in the order that they
    						were declared, when viewed as children of the next semantic container
    						upwards in the tree, and despite the containers themselves being abstracted
    						out of the tree. This defines the reading order. This example is a
    						large block of text with intentionally simple formatting, where the
    						only formatting is to represent paragraphs as separate <obj>TextBlock</obj> elements
    						to support an adaptive layout, but no <obj>Run</obj> blocks within. </p>
            <p>When viewed with assistive technologies that represent the contents,
    						each <obj>TextBlock</obj> is a control type of Text. Screen readers
    						can use document reading modes such as virtual cursor modes to read
    						the content from each element and each element's content, following
    						the same reading order as is declared in the XAML. For example, in
    						JAWS 12, readers can read out this text container line by line using
    						(Jaws Key)+DownArrow. It is actually JAWS that determines the line
    						length, because the line length otherwise is defined only by the adaptive
    						layout at runtime, which is not reported to UIA. </p>
            <codeblock xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[  <StackPanel x:Name="LayoutRoot" Background="White">
          <TextBlock>Call me Ishmael. Some years ago--never mind how long precisely--
having little or no money in my purse, and
nothing particular to interest me on shore, I thought I would sail about a little 
and see the watery part of the world. It is a way I have of driving off the spleen 
and regulating the circulation. Whenever I find 
myself growing grim about the mouth; whenever it is a damp, drizzly November in 
my soul; whenever I find myself involuntarily pausing before coffin warehouses, 
and bringing up the rear of every funeral I meet;
and especially whenever my hypos get such an upper hand of me, that it requires a strong moral 
principle to prevent me from
deliberately stepping into the street, and methodically knocking people's hats off--then, 
I account it high time to get to sea as
soon as I can. This is my substitute for pistol and ball. With a philosophical flourish Cato 
throws himself 
upon his sword; I quietly take to the ship. There is nothing surprising in this. If they but knew it, 
almost all men in their degree, some time or other, cherish very nearly the same feelings towards the 
ocean with me.
          </TextBlock>
          <TextBlock>There now is your insular city of the Manhattoes, belted round by wharves as Indian isles 
          by coral reefs--
commerce surrounds it with her surf. Right and left, the streets take you waterward. 
Its extreme downtown is the battery, where
that noble mole is washed by waves, and cooled by breezes, which a few hours previous 
were out of sight of land. Look at the crowds of water-gazers there.
          </TextBlock>
          <TextBlock>Circumambulate the city of a dreamy Sabbath afternoon. Go from Corlears Hook 
          to Coenties Slip, and from thence, by Whitehall, northward.
What do you see?--Posted like silent sentinels all around the town, stand thousands 
upon thousands of mortal men fixed in ocean
reveries. Some leaning against the spiles; some seated upon the pier-heads; 
some looking over the bulwarks of ships from China; 
some high aloft in the rigging, as if striving to get a still better seaward peep. 
But these are all landsmen; of week days pent
up in lath and plaster--tied to counters, nailed to benches, clinched to desks. 
How  then is this? Are the green fields gone? What do they here?
          </TextBlock>
  </StackPanel>
]]></codeblock>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Text containers and their UIA representation</head>
         <description>
            <p>The following example is intended as sample XAML to view in an accessibility
    						framework viewer, to see the various names, roles, and patterns for
    						obtaining value. </p>
            <codeblock xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[   <StackPanel x:Name="LayoutRoot">
       <TextBox Text="This is a TextBox"/>
       <RichTextBox>
           <Paragraph>This is a RichTextBox.</Paragraph>
       </RichTextBox>
       <TextBlock Text="This is a TextBlock"/>
   </StackPanel>
]]></codeblock>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc645025(VS.95).aspx">Silverlight
    					Layout System</loc> 
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc707824(VS.95).aspx">Silverlight
    					Accessibility Overview</loc> 
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc189034(VS.95).aspx">Silverlight
    					Object Trees</loc> 
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Tools: <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://firstfloorsoftware.com/silverlightspy">SilverlightSpy</loc> or <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://uiautomationverify.codeplex.com/">UIAVerify</loc> 
               </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </see-also>
   </resources>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="G115"/>
      <relatedtech idref="G135"/>
      <relatedtech idref="G10"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p> Using a browser that supports Silverlight, open an HTML page that
    					references a Silverlight application through an object tag. To see
    					UI Automation, use Microsoft Windows as platform. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Use a verification tool that is capable of showing the full automation
    						tree. (For example, use UIAVerify or Silverlight Spy; see Resources
    						links.) </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Verify that <obj>TextBox</obj> elements in the Silverlight
    							user interface have the Edit role, that <obj>RichTextBox</obj> elements
    							have the Document role, and <obj>TextBlock</obj> has Text role
    							in UI Automation. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Verify that the text content can be programmatically determined
    								by techniques that are appropriate for that role. </p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <p>#3 and #4 are true. </p>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
   <admin>
      <source>
         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
              href="http://trace.wisc.edu/wcag_wiki/index.php?title=Using_Silverlight_Text_Elements_for_Appropriate_Accessibility_Role"/>
      </source>
   </admin>
</technique>
