<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="SL34">
   <short-name>Using the Silverlight Default Tab Sequence and Altering Tab Sequences
    			With Properties</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p use-id="silverlight.applicability.general"/>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="content-structure-separation-sequence" relationship="sufficient"/>
      <success-criterion idref="navigation-mechanisms-focus-order" relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <ua-issues>
      <ua-issue use-id="silverlight.ua-issue.general"/>
   </ua-issues>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to use the default Silverlight
    				tab sequence, or alternatively to apply the options that Silverlight
    				application authors can use for altering the tab sequence. Application
    				authors might alter the tab sequence in cases where the default tab
    				sequence is not desirable for some reason, and those reasons might
    				vary per application or application scenario. The tab sequence can
    				be altered in order to create a meaningful sequence in the tab order,
    				so that assistive technologies that rely on traversal of focusable
    				elements can use and determine the meaningful sequence. </p>
      <p>Silverlight uses structured definitions for defining its user interface
    				presentations, where the declaration order is significant because it
    				becomes the structure of the run-time visual tree. The structured definitions
    				also define the layout and presentation structure in most cases. The
    				structured definition concept is described in more detail in <specref ref="silverlight_notes"/>. </p>
      <p>The Silverlight development platform attempts to create an overall
    				system where the logical order of how elements are defined in XAML
    				and code, and then presented in a user interface, will also match a
    				logical tab sequence and logical reading order when presented to the
    				user. In many cases, a Silverlight application author can write an
    				application without necessarily worrying about the tab sequence, can
    				test the tab sequence during a verification and testing phase of development,
    				and will not need to set any specific properties to adjust the tab
    				sequence. As a broad generalization, a Silverlight tab sequence will
    				be constructed so that it traverses elements left to right, and top
    				to bottom, and will behave similarly to how HTML would behave if the
    				HTML analogs of Silverlight elements were constructed and presented
    				in the same way. However, there are specific Silverlight controls that
    				deliberately alter the tab sequence, or whose elements are made keyboard-accessible
    				through a keyboard navigation technique other than TAB. For more information,
    				see <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
              href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc903954(VS.95).aspx">Focus
    				Overview on MSDN</loc>. </p>
      <section id="SL34_tab-sequence">
         <head> How Silverlight implements tab sequence concepts </head>
         <p>The Silverlight programming model defines a <obj>Control</obj> class
    					that is a base class of many of the practical controls that produce
    					a Silverlight application user interface. One of the behaviors of the <obj>Control</obj> class
    					is that only a <obj>Control</obj> can receive keyboard focus
    					as a discrete element within the Silverlight content area. </p>
         <p>When a Silverlight application user interface is constructed from
    					the visual tree, a default tab sequence for all Silverlight content
    					is also constructed, using the same principles of order that were used
    					by the visible layout. This default tab sequence is usually adequate
    					as a tab sequence that supports users that press the TAB key to traverse
    					the UI. The same TAB sequence and/or the focusable state of controls
    					is also used by many assistive technologies or modes of assistive technologies
    					to construct the representation of the interface for the Silverlight
    					content. </p>
         <p>For cases where developers decide that the default tab sequence is
    					not adequate, the developer can take one of two approaches for changing
    					the tab sequence: </p>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p> Change other properties of the control where a change to the tab
    				sequence happens as a secondary effect. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Reorder the tab sequence directly. </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </section>
      <section id="SL34_control-properties">
         <head> Changing control properties </head>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p> Setting the <prop>Visibility</prop> property of a control
    					to <prop>Collapsed</prop> causes the control to no longer render
    					in the UI. As a secondary effect, that control is removed from the
    					tab sequence. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Setting the <prop>IsEnabled</prop> property of a control to
    						false causes the control to no longer be focusable by keyboard or
    						clickable by the mouse. In many cases, the visual appearance of the
    						control changes also, through a theme style. For example, the control
    						may appear as gray rather than black. As a secondary effect, that
    						control is removed from the tab sequence. </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </section>
      <section id="SL34_tab-properties">
         <head> Changing specific tab properties </head>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p> Setting the <prop>IsTabStop</prop> property of a control to
    					false causes the control to no longer be focusable by keyboard or
    					programmatic focus, and that control is removed from the tab sequence. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Setting the <prop>TabIndex</prop> property of a control to
    						a specific index causes the control to be inserted at that position
    						in the tab sequence. The default value of <prop>TabIndex</prop> is
    						Single.MaxValue, therefore any non-default value promotes that control
    						to be first in an otherwise default tab sequence. More typically,
    						authors would specify a <prop>TabIndex</prop> for any controls
    						that are involved in a deliberate segment of tab order re-ordering. </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </section>
      <section id="SL34_tab-order">
         <head> Tab order and language </head>
         <p>Left-to-right is the default only for languages that use left-to-right
    					reading order. For languages that use right-to-left reading order,
    					right-to-left is also the default tab order as implemented by Silverlight
    					runtime behavior. That language preference is declared by the acting <obj>CultureInfo</obj>.
    					For more information on <obj>CultureInfo</obj>, see <specref ref="SL27"/>. </p>
      </section>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Default tab order, based on ordering in the StackPanel</head>
         <description>
            <p>In this example, a <obj>StackPanel</obj> has a natural layout
    						order of top-to-bottom, and that will also be the tab order of each <obj>StackPanel</obj> child
    						element (FirstName, then LastName). </p>
            <codeblock xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[   <StackPanel x:Name="LayoutRoot" Background="White">
       <StackPanel Orientation="Horizontal">
           <TextBlock Name="lbl_FirstName">First name</TextBlock>
           <TextBox AutomationProperties.LabeledBy="{Binding ElementName=lbl_FirstName}" Name="tbFirstName" Width="100"/>
       </StackPanel>
       <StackPanel Orientation="Horizontal">
           <TextBlock Name="lbl_LastName">First name</TextBlock>
           <TextBox AutomationProperties.LabeledBy="{Binding ElementName=lbl_LastName}" Name="tbLastName" Width="100"/>
       </StackPanel>
   </StackPanel>
]]></codeblock>
            <p>This example is shown in operation in the <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    href="TabSequenceTestPage.html"
                    linktype="examples">working example of Tab Sequence</loc>.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Tab order, modified by TabIndex</head>
         <description>
            <p>A form is marked up using a data table that includes the fields of
    						the groom in the first column and the fields of the bride in the second
    						column. The order in the content is row by row but the author feels
    						it is more logical for users to navigate the form column by column.
    						This way, all the groom's criteria can be filled in before moving on
    						to the bride's criteria. The <prop>TabIndex</prop> attributes of
    						the Silverlight elements are used to specify a tab order that navigates
    						column by column. This example specifically illustrates how changing
    						tab order can change the meaningful sequence. </p>
            <codeblock xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[ <UserControl x:Class="TabSequence.MainPage"
 xmlns="http://schemas.microsoft.com/winfx/2006/xaml/presentation"
 xmlns:x="http://schemas.microsoft.com/winfx/2006/xaml"
 >
   <StackPanel x:Name="LayoutRoot" Background="White">
       <TextBlock>he first column contains the search criteria 
 of the groom, the second column the search criteria of 
 of the bride</TextBlock>
       <Grid>
       <Grid.RowDefinitions>
         <RowDefinition/>
         <RowDefinition/>
         <RowDefinition/>
         <RowDefinition/>
       </Grid.RowDefinitions>
       <Grid.ColumnDefinitions>
         <ColumnDefinition/>
         <ColumnDefinition/>
         <ColumnDefinition/>
       </Grid.ColumnDefinitions>
       <TextBlock>Search criteria</TextBlock>
       <TextBlock Grid.Column="1">Groom</TextBlock>
       <TextBlock Grid.Column="2">Bride</TextBlock>
       <TextBlock Grid.Row="1">First name</TextBlock>
       <TextBox Grid.Row="1" Grid.Column="1" TabIndex="1"/>
       <TextBox Grid.Row="1" Grid.Column="2" TabIndex="4"/>
       <TextBlock Grid.Row="2">Last name</TextBlock>
       <TextBox Grid.Row="2" Grid.Column="1" TabIndex="2"/>
       <TextBox Grid.Row="2" Grid.Column="2" TabIndex="5"/>
       <TextBlock Grid.Row="3" >Place of birth</TextBlock>
       <TextBox Grid.Row="3" Grid.Column="1" TabIndex="3"/>
       <TextBox Grid.Row="3" Grid.Column="2" TabIndex="6"/>
       </Grid>
   </StackPanel>
 </UserControl>
 ]]></codeblock>
            <p>This example is shown in operation in the <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    href="TabSequence_TabIndexTestPage.html"
                    linktype="examples">working example of Tab Sequence TabIndex</loc>.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Tab order, modified by changing runtime Control properties</head>
         <description>
            <p>In this example, a radio button choice in a form controls whether
    						certain other fields in the form are relevant or not relevant. The
    						current radio button selection toggles the <prop>IsEnabled</prop> property
    						in such fields to enable or disable them based on how the user selected
    						the preceding logical element, which also affects whether the fields
    						appear in the further tab sequence. The following is UI definition
    						in XAML. </p>
            <codeblock xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[<UserControl x:Class="TabSequence.MainPage"
   xmlns="http://schemas.microsoft.com/winfx/2006/xaml/presentation"
   xmlns:x="http://schemas.microsoft.com/winfx/2006/xaml"
>
   <StackPanel x:Name="LayoutRoot" Background="White">
       <TextBlock>Registration</TextBlock>
       <Grid>
       <Grid.RowDefinitions>
         <RowDefinition/>
         <RowDefinition/>
         <RowDefinition/>
         <RowDefinition/>
       </Grid.RowDefinitions>
       <Grid.ColumnDefinitions>
         <ColumnDefinition/>
         <ColumnDefinition/>
         <ColumnDefinition/>
       </Grid.ColumnDefinitions>
           <StackPanel Orientation="Horizontal">
               <RadioButton GroupName="Registration" Checked="RadioButton_CheckedG">Guest</RadioButton>
               <RadioButton GroupName="Registration" Checked="RadioButton_CheckedC">Custom</RadioButton>
           </StackPanel>
               <TextBlock Grid.Row="1">First name</TextBlock>
           <TextBox x:Name="tb_fn" IsEnabled="false" Grid.Row="1" Grid.Column="1" />
           <TextBlock Grid.Row="2">Last name</TextBlock>
           <TextBox  x:Name="tb_ln" IsEnabled="false" Grid.Row="2" Grid.Column="1" />
       </Grid>
   </StackPanel>
</UserControl>
]]></codeblock>
            <p>The following is event handler code. </p>
            <codeblock xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[       private void RadioButton_CheckedC(object sender, RoutedEventArgs e)
       {
           tb_fn.IsEnabled = true;
           tb_ln.IsEnabled = true;
       }
       private void RadioButton_CheckedG(object sender, RoutedEventArgs e)
       {
           tb_fn.IsEnabled = false;
           tb_ln.IsEnabled = false;
       }
       ]]></codeblock>
            <p>This example is shown in operation in the <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    href="TabSequence_EnabledTestPage.html"
                    linktype="examples">working example of Tab Sequence Enabled</loc>.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc189034(VS.95).aspx">Silverlight
    					Object Trees</loc> 
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc707824(VS.95).aspx">Silverlight
    					Accessibility Overview</loc> 
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc903954(VS.95).aspx">Focus
    						Overview</loc> 
               </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </see-also>
   </resources>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p> Using a browser that supports Silverlight, open an HTML page that
    					references a Silverlight application through an object tag. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Engage the screen reader. Press the TAB key to traverse the sequence
    						of elements inside the Silverlight content area. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Verify that the order in which elements are traversed in a tab
    							sequence is also the expected order of the elements as they are presented
    							visually, particularly in such cases where the order of each element
    							is significant per <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="content-structure-separation-sequence"
                       linktype="understanding">SC
    								1.3.2</loc>. </p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <p>#3 is true. </p>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
   <admin>
      <source>
         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
              href="http://trace.wisc.edu/wcag_wiki/index.php?title=Using_the_Silverlight_Default_Tab_Sequence_and_Altering_Tab_Sequences_With_Properties"/>
      </source>
   </admin>
</technique>
