<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="T1">
   <short-name>Using standard text formatting conventions for paragraphs</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>Plain text documents. Not applicable to technologies that contain markup.</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="content-structure-separation-programmatic"
                         relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to recognize a paragraph in a plain text document. A paragraph is a coherent block of text, such as a group of related sentences that develop a single topic or a coherent part of a larger topic. </p>
      <p>The beginning of a paragraph is indicated by
</p>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>the beginning of the content, that is, the paragraph is the first content in the document, or</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>exactly one blank line preceding the paragraph text</p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
      <p>The end of a paragraph is indicated by 
</p>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>the end of the content, that is, the paragraph is the last content in the document, or</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>one or more blank lines following the paragraph text</p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
      <p>A blank line contains zero or more non-printing characters, such as space or tab, followed by a new line.</p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <description>
            <p>Two paragraphs. Each starts and ends with a blank line.</p>
         </description>
         <code><![CDATA[
						
This is the first sentence in this
paragraph. Paragraphs may be long
or short.
   
    In this paragraph the first line is
indented. Indented and non-indented
sentences are allowed. White space within
the paragraph lines is ignored in
defining paragraphs. Only completely blank
lines are significant.

]]></code>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources/>
   <related-techniques/>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <p>For each paragraph:
							</p>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Check that the paragraph is preceded by exactly one blank line, or that the paragraph is the first content in the Web page</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Check that the paragraph is followed by at least one blank line, or that the paragraph is the last content in the Web page.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Check that no paragraph contains any blank lines</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>All checks above are all true for each paragraph.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
