<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="PDF1">
   <short-name>Applying text alternatives to images with the Alt entry in PDF documents</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>Tagged PDF documents with images</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="text-equiv-all" relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <ua-issues>
      <ua-issue id="pdf.ua-issue.general">
         <p>See <specref ref="pdf_notes"/> for information on user agent and assistive
    				technology support.</p>
      </ua-issue>
   </ua-issues>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to provide text alternatives for
    				images via an /Alt entry in the property list for a Tag. This is normally
    				accomplished using a tool for authoring PDF. </p>
      <p>PDF documents may be enhanced by providing alternative descriptions
    				for images, formulas, and other items that do not translate naturally
    				into text. In fact, such text alternatives are required for accessibility:
    				alternate descriptions are human-readable text that can be vocalized
    				by text-to-speech technology for the benefit of users with vision disabilities. </p>
      <p>When an image contains words that are important to understanding the
    				content, the text alternative should include those words. This will
    				allow the alternative to accurately represent the image. Note that
    				it does not necessarily describe the visual characteristics of the
    				image itself but must convey the same meaning as the image. </p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Adding an /Alt entry to an image using Adobe Acrobat
    				9 Pro's TouchUp Object Tool</head>
         <description>
            <p>This example is shown with Adobe Acrobat Pro. There are other software tools that perform similar functions. See the list of other software tools in <specref ref="pdf_notes_acc-sup_files_applications"/>.</p>
            <olist>
               <item>
                  <p> Choose Tools &gt; Advanced Editing &gt; TouchUp Object Tool </p>
                  <p>
                     <image>
                        <img xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                             source="/WAI/WCAG20/Techniques/working-examples/PDF1/textalt1.gif"
                             height="247"
                             width="358"/>
                        <alt>The TouchUp Object Tool in the Advanced Editing menu.</alt>
                     </image> 
                  </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>Access the context menu for the image and choose Properties. </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>On the TouchUp Properties dialog, select the Tag tab. </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>On the Tag panel, type the text alternative in the Alternate Text
    						text box. </p>
                  <p>
                     <image>
                        <img xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                             source="/WAI/WCAG20/Techniques/working-examples/PDF1/textalt2.gif"
                             height="231"
                             width="556"/>
                        <alt>The Tag Tab in the TouchUp Properties dialog.</alt>
                     </image> 
                  </p>
               </item>
            </olist>
            <p>This example is shown in operation in the <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    href="alt-entry-to-an-image.pdf"
                    linktype="examples">working example of Adding an /Alt entry to an image</loc>.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Adding an /Alt entry to an image using Adobe Acrobat
    					9 Pro's TouchUp Reading Order Tool</head>
         <description>
            <p>This example is shown with Adobe Acrobat Pro. There are other software tools that perform similar functions. See the list of other software tools in <specref ref="pdf_notes_acc-sup_files_applications"/>.</p>
            <olist>
               <item>
                  <p> Choose Tools &gt; Advanced Editing &gt; TouchUp Reading Order
    					Tool </p>
                  <p>
                     <image>
                        <img xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                             source="/WAI/WCAG20/Techniques/working-examples/PDF1/textalt3.gif"
                             height="227"
                             width="358"/>
                        <alt>The TouchUp Reading Order Tool in the Advanced Editing menu.</alt>
                     </image> 
                  </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>The TouchUp Reading Order dialog will be displayed. </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>Right-click on the image and choose Edit Alternate Text. </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>The Alternate Text dialog will be displayed. </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>Type the text alternative in the Alternate Text text box. </p>
                  <p>
                     <image>
                        <img xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                             source="/WAI/WCAG20/Techniques/working-examples/PDF1/textalt4.gif"
                             height="222"
                             width="467"/>
                        <alt>The Alternate Text box.</alt>
                     </image> 
                  </p>
               </item>
            </olist>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Adding an /Alt entry to an image in PDF documents generated
    				using Microsoft Word</head>
         <description>
            <p>This example is shown with Microsoft Word. There are other software tools that perform similar functions. See the list of other software 
tools in <specref ref="pdf_notes_acc-sup_files_applications"/>.</p>
            <section id="PDF1_word_2003">
               <head> Word 2000-2003 </head>
               <olist>
                  <item>
                     <p> Right-click on the image and choose Format Picture </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p> Select the Web tab </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p> Type the alternative text into the text box provided and then
    						click OK. </p>
                  </item>
               </olist>
               <p>
                  <image>
                     <img xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                          source="/WAI/WCAG20/Techniques/working-examples/PDF1/word2003alt.gif"
                          height="291"
                          width="416"/>
                     <alt>The Web tab in the Format Picture dialog.</alt>
                  </image> 
               </p>
            </section>
            <section id="PDF1_word_2007">
               <head> Word 2007 </head>
               <olist>
                  <item>
                     <p> Right-click on the image and choose Size </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p> Select the Alt Text tab </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p> Type the alternative text into the text box provided and then
    						click OK. </p>
                  </item>
               </olist>
               <p>
                  <image>
                     <img xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                          source="/WAI/WCAG20/Techniques/working-examples/PDF1/word2007alt.gif"
                          height="272"
                          width="362"/>
                     <alt>The Alt Text tab in the Size dialog.</alt>
                  </image> 
               </p>
            </section>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Adding an /Alt entry to an image in PDF documents generated
    				using OpenOffice.org Writer 2.2</head>
         <description>
            <p>This example is shown with Open Office.org Writer. There are other software tools that perform similar functions. See the list of other software 
tools in <specref ref="pdf_notes_acc-sup_files_applications"/>.</p>
            <olist>
               <item>
                  <p> Access the context menu for the image and choose Picture... </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p> Select the Options tab </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p> Type the alternative text into Alternate (Text Only) text box
    						and click OK. </p>
               </item>
            </olist>
            <p>
               <image>
                  <img xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       source="/WAI/WCAG20/Techniques/working-examples/PDF1/ooalt.jpg"
                       height="439"
                       width="556"/>
                  <alt>The Options tab in the Picture... dialog.</alt>
               </image> 
            </p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Adding a text alternative to an image in a PDF document
    				using an /Alt entry</head>
         <description>
            <p>The /Alt property used on an image of mountains with a moon and trees
    						typically would be used like this (typically accomplished by an authoring
    						tool): </p>
            <codeblock xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[/Figure <</Alt (Sketch of Mountains with moon rising over trees) >>]]></codeblock>
            <p>The image might also be represented by a tag with a different name.
    						A different name might be used because the tag name is written in
    						a language other than English or because a specific tool uses a different
    						name for some other reason. In this situation, it is also necessary
    						that the RoleMap contained within the StructTreeRoot for the PDF
    						document contain an entry which explicitly maps the name of the tag
    						used for the image with the standard structure type used in PDF documents
    						(in this case, Figure). If the RoleMap contains only an entry mapping
    						Shape tags to Figure tags, the rolemap information would appear as
    						follows: </p>
            <codeblock xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[/RoleMap << /Shape /Figure >>]]></codeblock>
            <p>In this case, the usage of the /Alt entry as follows would also
    					be correct: </p>
            <codeblock xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[/Shape <</Alt (Crater Lake in the summer, with the blue sky, clouds and crater walls perfectly reflected in the lake) >>
    					]]></codeblock>
            <p>Note that the /Alt entry in property lists can be combined with
    						other entries. </p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p> Section 14.9.4 (Replacement Text) in <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.adobe.com/content/dam/Adobe/en/devnet/pdf/pdfs/PDF32000_2008.pdf">PDF
    				1.7 (ISO 32000-1)</loc> 
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://webaim.org/techniques/acrobat/acrobat">Acrobat
    					and Accessibility</loc> 
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://partners.adobe.com/public/developer/en/pdf/PDFReference16.pdf#page=892">PDF
    					Reference 1.6, 10.8.2 Alternate Descriptions</loc> 
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.adobe.com/accessibility/products/acrobat.html">PDF and Accessibility</loc>
               </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </see-also>
   </resources>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="G94"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p> Verify the images which need equivalents have /Alt entries on
    					an enclosing tag by one of the following:</p>
               <ulist>
                  <item>
                     <p> Read the PDF document with a screen reader, listening to hear
	    						that the equivalent text is read when tabbing to the non-text
	    						object (if it is tabbable) or hearing the alternative text read
	    						when reading the content line-by-line. </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p> Using a PDF editor, check that a text alternative is displayed for each
	    							image. </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p> Use a tool which is capable of showing the /Alt entry value,
	    								such as aDesigner, to open the PDF document and view the GUI
	    								summary to read the text alternatives for images. </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p> Use a tool that exposes the document through the accessibility
	    						API and verify that images have required text equivalents. </p>
                  </item>
               </ulist>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p> Check 1 is true for each image in the document which needs a text
    					equivalent. </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
   <admin>
      <source>
         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
              href="http://trace.wisc.edu/wcag_wiki/index.php?title=Applying_text_alternatives_to_images_with_the_Alt_entry_in_PDF_documents"/>
      </source>
   </admin>
</technique>
