<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="PDF18">
   <short-name>Specifying the document title using the Title entry in the document
    			information dictionary of a PDF document</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p use-id="pdf.applicability.general"/>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="navigation-mechanisms-title" relationship="cosufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <ua-issues>
      <ua-issue use-id="pdf.ua-issue.general"/>
   </ua-issues>
   <description>
      <p>The intent of this technique is to show how a descriptive title for
    				a PDF document can be specified for assistive technology by using the
    				/Title entry in the document information dictionary and by setting
    				the DisplayDocTitle flag to True in a viewer preferences dictionary.
    				This is typically accomplished by using a tool for authoring PDF. </p>
      <p>Document titles identify the current location without requiring users
    				to read or interpret page content. User agents make the title of the
    				page easily available to the user for identifying the page. For instance,
    				a user agent may display the page title in the window title bar or
    				as the name of the tab containing the page. </p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Setting the document title in the metadata and specifying
    					that the title be displayed in the title bar using Adobe Acrobat 9 Pro</head>
         <description>
            <p>This example is shown with Adobe Acrobat Pro. There are other software tools that perform similar functions. See the list of other software tools in <specref ref="pdf_notes_acc-sup_files_applications"/>.</p>
            <p>Open the PDF document in Adobe Acrobat Pro: </p>
            <olist>
               <item>
                  <p> Select File &gt; Properties </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p> Select the Description tab to view the metadata in the document,
    						including the document information dictionary </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p> Modify the Title field to add or change the document's Title entry </p>
               </item>
            </olist>
            <p>
               <image>
                  <img xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       source="/WAI/WCAG20/Techniques/working-examples/PDF18/title-entry.jpg"
                       height="673"
                       width="610"/>
                  <alt>Viewing the Title field in the Description tab of the Properties dialog. The document title is entered in the field.</alt>
               </image> 
            </p>
            <p>Note that, with Adobe Acrobat installed, you can also enter and read
    						the data properties information from the desktop. Access the file's
    						context menu, choose Properties, and select the PDF tab. Any information
    						you type or edit in this dialog box also appears in the Document Properties
    						Description when you open the file. </p>
            <p>To display the document title in the title bar of a user agent: </p>
            <olist>
               <item>
                  <p> Select File &gt; Properties </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p> Select the Initial View tab </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p> In the Window Options section, select Document Title in the Show
    						pull-down list. </p>
               </item>
            </olist>
            <p>
               <image>
                  <img xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       source="/WAI/WCAG20/Techniques/working-examples/PDF18/doc-title.jpg"
                       height="671"
                       width="610"/>
                  <alt>Specifying that the document title be displayed in the title bar. In the Window Options, Show Document Title is selected.</alt>
               </image> 
            </p>
            <p>The title is displayed in the title bar, as shown in the image below. </p>
            <p>
               <image>
                  <img xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       source="/WAI/WCAG20/Techniques/working-examples/PDF18/title-bar.jpg"
                       height="34"
                       width="492"/>
                  <alt>Image of the Adobe Acrobat Pro title bar with the title of the document displayed.</alt>
               </image> 
            </p>
            <p>This example is shown in operation in the <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    href="title-bar.pdf"
                    linktype="examples">working example of displaying document title in the title bar</loc>.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <head>A /Title entry in the document information dictionary
    				of a PDF document</head>
         <description>
            <p>The following code fragment illustrates code that is typical for providing
    						a /Title entry in a document information dictionary that contains a
    						document title. </p>
            <codeblock xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[1 0 obj   
   << /Title (Applying Guerrilla Tactics to Usability Testing by People with Disabilities)    
      /Author (Mary Smith) 
      /CreationDate (D:19970915110347-08'00')    
   >>   
endobj
]]></codeblock>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.adobe.com/accessibility/products/acrobat.html">PDF and Accessibility</loc>
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Section 14.3.3 (Document Information Dictionary) in <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.adobe.com/content/dam/Adobe/en/devnet/pdf/pdfs/PDF32000_2008.pdf">PDF
    					1.7 (ISO 32000-1)</loc> 
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> 
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://partners.adobe.com/public/developer/en/pdf/PDFReference16.pdf#page=794">PDF
    					Reference 1.6, TITLE entry of the document information dictionary</loc> 
               </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </see-also>
   </resources>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="G88"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Verify that the title for the document is correctly specified and
    					displayed in the user agent title bar by applying one of the following:</p>
               <ulist>
                  <item>
                     <p> Open the PDF document with a screen reader, listening to hear
    						that the document title is read correctly. </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p> Using a PDF editor, check that the document title is specified.
    							Select the Initial View tab to check that the title will be displayed. </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p> Use a tool which is capable of showing the /Title entry value
    								in the document catalog to open the PDF document and view the
    								/Title entry and /DisplayDocTitle flag settings. </p>
                  </item>
               </ulist>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>#1 is true. </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
   <admin>
      <source>
         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
              href="http://trace.wisc.edu/wcag_wiki/index.php?title=Specifying_the_document_title_using_the_Title_entry_in_the_document_information_dictionary_of_a_PDF_document"/>
      </source>
   </admin>
</technique>
