<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="PDF2">
   <short-name>Creating bookmarks in PDF documents</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p id="pdf.applicability.general">Tagged PDF documents</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="navigation-mechanisms-mult-loc" relationship="advisory"/>
   </applies-to>
   <ua-issues>
      <ua-issue use-id="pdf.ua-issue.general"/>
   </ua-issues>
   <description>
      <p>The intent of this technique is to make it possible for users to locate
    				content using bookmarks (<emph>outline entries</emph> in an Outline dictionary)
    				in long documents. </p>
      <p>A person with cognitive disabilities may prefer a hierarchical outline
    				that provides an overview of the document rather than reading and traversing
    				through many pages. This is also a conventional means of navigating
    				a document that benefits all users. </p>
     <p>This technique is advisory because bookmarks in a PDF support navigation within a document, but since a multi-page PDF document is not regarded as a "set of web pages" this technique is not sufficient to meet Success Criteria 2.4.5.</p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Converting a table of contents created with Microsoft
    					Word 2007 and creating bookmarks for Adobe Reader 9 and Acrobat 9 Pro</head>
         <description>
            <p>This example is shown with Microsoft Word and Adobe Acrobat Pro. There are other software tools that perform similar functions. See the list of other software 
tools in <specref ref="pdf_notes_acc-sup_files_applications"/>.</p>
            <olist>
               <item>
                  <p> Create a table of contents at the beginning of the Word document. </p>
                  <p>
                     <image>
                        <img xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                             source="/WAI/WCAG20/Techniques/working-examples/PDF2/word-toc.jpg"
                             height="150"
                             width="363"/>
                        <alt>Reference tab on Word ribbon, showing Table of Contents tool.</alt>
                     </image> 
                  </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p> Use Save as... &gt; Adobe PDF to convert the Word document to
    						PDF, specifying both of the following:</p>
                  <ulist>
                     <item>
                        <p> Enable Accessibility and Reflow with Tagged Adobe PDF </p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <p> Convert Word Headings into Bookmarks </p>
                     </item>
                  </ulist>
               </item>
            </olist>
            <p>The table-of-contents entries in the converted document will be linked
    						to the headings in the document. </p>
            <p>In addition, the headings will appear as PDF Bookmarks in the left-hand
    						Navigation pane. </p>
            <p>
               <image>
                  <img xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       source="/WAI/WCAG20/Techniques/working-examples/PDF2/bookmarks.jpg"
                       height="249"
                       width="937"/>
                  <alt>PDF document showing the Table of Contents and Bookmarks created from the headings in a Word document.</alt>
               </image>  
            </p>
            <p>If the document provides a glossary and/or index, these sections
    						should have headings that appear in the table of contents (and thus
    						as bookmarks in the Navigation pane). The table of contents also
    						should be marked up with a heading so it is bookmarked as well. </p>
            <p>If this markup has not been done in the authoring tool, Adobe Acrobat
    						Pro can be used to provide the tags. See <specref ref="PDF9"/> if
    							you need to modify converted headings or add new ones. </p>
            <p>This example is shown in operation in the <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    href="bookmarks.docx"
                    linktype="examples">working example of creating bookmarks with Word 2007</loc>.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Converting a table of contents created with OpenOffice.org
    					Writer 2.2 and creating bookmarks for Adobe Reader 9 and Acrobat 9
    					Pro</head>
         <description>
            <p>This example is shown with OpenOffice.org Writer and Adobe Acrobat Pro and Reader. There are other software tools that perform similar functions. See the list of other software 
tools in <specref ref="pdf_notes_acc-sup_files_applications"/>.</p>
            <olist>
               <item>
                  <p> Create a table of contents at the beginning of the OpenOffice.org
    						Writer document:</p>
                  <ulist>
                     <item>
                        <p> Insert &gt; Indexes and Tables... &gt; Indexes and Tables &gt; Insert
    							Index/Table </p>
                     </item>
                  </ulist>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p> Use File &gt; Export as PDF... to convert the document to PDF,
    						specifying Tagged PDF in the Options dialog. </p>
               </item>
            </olist>
            <p>
               <image>
                  <img xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       source="/WAI/WCAG20/Techniques/working-examples/PDF2/oo-toc.jpg"
                       height="583"
                       width="944"/>
                  <alt>Image of the Insert Index/Table dialog in OpenOffice.org Writer.</alt>
               </image> 
            </p>
            <p>The table-of-contents entries in the converted document will be linked
    						to the headings in the document, and will appear as PDF Bookmarks in
    						the left-hand Navigation pane. The OpenOffice.org Table of Contents
    						and Bookmarks look the same as they appeared in Example 1. </p>
            <p>This example is shown in operation in the <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    href="bookmarks.odt"
                    linktype="examples">working example of creating bookmarks with OpenOffice Writer</loc>.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Adding bookmarks using Adobe Acrobat 9 Pro after conversion</head>
         <description>
            <p>This example is shown with Adobe Acrobat Pro. There are other software tools that perform similar functions. See the list of other software 
tools in <specref ref="pdf_notes_acc-sup_files_applications"/>.</p>
            <p>After conversion to tagged PDF, you may decide to add bookmarks that
    						were not automatically generated. Like the converted bookmarks, tagged
    						bookmarks use the underlying structural information in the document. </p>
            <olist>
               <item>
                  <p> In the Bookmarks panel, choose the options menu, then choose New
    						Bookmarks From Structure... </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p> From the Structure Elements dialog, select the elements you want
    							specified as tagged bookmarks. </p>
               </item>
            </olist>
            <p>The image below shows the Bookmarks options menu. </p>
            <p>
               <image>
                  <img xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       source="/WAI/WCAG20/Techniques/working-examples/PDF2/bookmark1.jpg"
                       height="521"
                       width="358"/>
                  <alt>The Bookmarks options menu.</alt>
               </image> 
            </p>
            <p>The next image shows the selection of links in the document for bookmarking. </p>
            <p>
               <image>
                  <img xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       source="/WAI/WCAG20/Techniques/working-examples/PDF2/bookmark2.jpg"
                       height="369"
                       width="506"/>
                  <alt>The tagged elements that can be used for bookmarking, with 'links' selected.</alt>
               </image> 
            </p>
            <p>The tagged bookmarks are nested under a new, untitled bookmark. Access
    						the context menu for the new bookmark and select the Rename option
    						to rename the new bookmark, as shown in the following image. </p>
            <p>
               <image>
                  <img xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       source="/WAI/WCAG20/Techniques/working-examples/PDF2/link-bookmark.jpg"
                       height="309"
                       width="943"/>
                  <alt>The bookmarks for the hyperlink in the document.</alt>
               </image> 
            </p>
            <p>This example is shown in operation in the <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    href="bookmarks.pdf"
                    linktype="examples">working example of creating bookmarks with Acrobat Pro</loc>.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Creating bookmarks with the outline hierarchy</head>
         <description>
            <p>The following code fragment illustrates part of an outline hierarchy
    						used to create bookmarks This is typically accomplished by an authoring
    						tool. </p>
            <codeblock xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[121 0 obj
 << /Type /Outlines
    /First 22 0 R
    /Last 29 0 R
    /Count 6
 >>
endobj
22 0 obj
 << /Title (Applying Guerrilla Tactics to Usability Testing by People with Disabilities)
    /Parent 21 0 R
    /Next 29 0 R
    /First 25 0 R
    /Last 28 0 R
    /Count 4
    /Dest [3 0 R /XYZ 0 792 0]
 >>
endobj
25 0 obj
 << /Title (Getting started)
    /Parent 22 0 R
    /Next 26 0 R
    /Dest [3 0 R /XYZ null 701 null]
 >>
endobj
]]></codeblock>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p> Section 12.3.3 (Document Outline) in <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.adobe.com/content/dam/Adobe/en/devnet/pdf/pdfs/PDF32000_2008.pdf">PDF
    					1.7 (ISO 32000-1)</loc> 
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.adobe.com/accessibility/products/acrobat.html">PDF and Accessibility</loc>
               </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </see-also>
   </resources>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="G64"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p> Check that the Bookmarks panel displays bookmarks. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Check that the bookmarks link to the correct sections in the document. </p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>Check #1 and Check #2 are true. </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
   <admin>
      <source>
         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
              href="http://trace.wisc.edu/wcag_wiki/index.php?title=Creating_bookmarks_in_PDF_documents"/>
      </source>
   </admin>
</technique>
