<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="PDF22">
   <short-name>Indicating when user input falls outside the required format or
    			values in PDF forms</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p use-id="pdf.applicability.general"/>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="minimize-error-identified" relationship="sufficient"/>
      <success-criterion idref="minimize-error-suggestions" relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <ua-issues>
      <ua-issue use-id="pdf.ua-issue.general"/>
   </ua-issues>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to notify the user when user
    				input to a field that requires a specific, required format (e.g.,
    				date fields) is not submitted in that format. </p>
      <p>If the required format is not used, an alert dialog describes the
    				nature of the error in text. This may be accomplished through scripting
    				created by the author (see, for example, <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
              href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2010/NOTE-WCAG20-TECHS-20101014/SCR18">SCR18:
    					Providing client-side validation and alert</loc>). User agents, such
    				as Adobe LiveCycle can provide automatic alerts (as described in
    				the examples below). </p>
      <note>
         <p>Once the user dismisses the alert dialog,
    				it may be helpful if the script positions the keyboard focus on
    				the field where the error occurred, although some users may expect
    				the focus to remain on the last control focused prior to the alert
    				appearing. Authors should exercise care to ensure that any movement
    				of the focus will be expected. For example, if the alert announces
    				an error in a phone number format, positioning the focus on the
    				phone number field when the alert is dismissed can be regarded as
    				helpful and expected. In some cases, however, this may not be possible.
    				If multiple input errors occur on the page, an alternative approach
    				to error notification should be implemented. </p>
      </note>
      <p>Ensuring that users are aware an error has occurred, can determine
    				what is wrong, and can correct it are key to software usability
    				and accessibility. Meeting this objective helps ensure that all
    				users can complete for-based transactions with ease and confidence. </p>
      <section>
         <head>Labels for required formats in form controls</head>
         <p>It is also important that users are aware that an error <emph role="strong">may</emph> occur.
    					You can incorporate this information in labels; for example, "Date
    					(MM/DD/YYYY)." See <specref ref="PDF10"/>. </p>
      </section>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Providing validation for an input field format using
    					Adobe Acrobat 9 Pro</head>
         <description>
            <p>This example is shown with Adobe Acrobat Pro. There are other software
    						tools that perform similar functions. See the list of other software
    						tools in <specref ref="pdf_notes_acc-sup_files_applications"/>. </p>
            <p>Many fields -- telephone number, postal code, date -- must have
    						data entered in a specific format or pattern. </p>
            <olist>
               <item>
                  <p> Access the context menu for the form control that requires
    						a specific format. </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p> Select Properties... </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p> In the Format tab, select the Format Category (in this case,
    							Date). The Date Options appear. </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p> Select the format for this form control (in this case, mm/dd/yyyy). </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p> In the General tab, specify "Date (mm/dd/yyyy)" for
    								the Name and Tooltip for the control. </p>
               </item>
            </olist>
            <p>
               <image>
                  <img xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       source="/WAI/WCAG20/Techniques/working-examples/PDF22/dateformat.jpg"
                       height="611"
                       width="661"/>
                  <alt>Specifying a required format for an input field format using Adobe Acrobat 9 Pro </alt>
               </image> 
            </p>
            <p>When a user types a recognized date format, it is converted automatically
    						to the specified format. If the date format or value is not recognized,
    						an error alert appears and provides further information, as shown
    						in the image below. </p>
            <p>
               <image>
                  <img xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       source="/WAI/WCAG20/Techniques/working-examples/PDF22/dateerror.jpg"
                       height="210"
                       width="501"/>
                  <alt>Error alert for date with unrecognized format or value.</alt>
               </image> 
            </p>
            <p>This example is shown in operation in the <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    href="required-fields.pdf"
                    linktype="examples">working example of Required Fields in Acrobat</loc>.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Providing validation for an input field format using
    					Adobe LiveCycle Designer ES 8.2.1</head>
         <description>
            <p>This example is shown with Adobe LiveCycle Designer. There are
    						other software tools that perform similar functions. See the list
    						of other software tools in <specref ref="pdf_notes_acc-sup_files_applications"/>. </p>
            <olist>
               <item>
                  <p> Select the form control that has a required format. </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p> In the Object palette, click the Validation Pattern... button. </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p> Because this is a date field the Patterns-Date Field dialog
    						appears. Select the pattern or format you want users to enter.
    						Then click OK.</p>
                  <p>
                     <image>
                        <img xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                             source="/WAI/WCAG20/Techniques/working-examples/PDF22/form-validation.jpg"
                             height="510"
                             width="903"/>
                        <alt>Using LiveCycle to specify form fields that require pattern validation</alt>
                     </image> 
                  </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p> In the Object palette, use the Validation Pattern Message box
    							to type a warning message. Be sure to include the required pattern.
    							This message appears when a user tries to submit the form using
    							an invalid date format. </p>
               </item>
            </olist>
            <p>This example is shown in operation in the <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    href="required-fields-lc.pdf"
                    linktype="examples">working example of Required Fields in LiveCycle Designer</loc>.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Validating a required date format in a PDF form using
    				JavaScript using Adobe Acrobat Pro 9</head>
         <description>
            <p>This example is shown with Adobe Acrobat Pro. There are other software
    						tools that perform similar functions. See the list of other software
    						tools in <specref ref="pdf_notes_acc-sup_files_applications"/>. </p>
            <p>The following JavaScript code illustrates the use of a script to
    						validate form fields, in this case, a date field. To add this script
    						to the form field, open the Text Field Properties dialog, as shown
    						in Example 1, and select Edit in the Validate tab: </p>
            <p>
               <image>
                  <img xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       source="/WAI/WCAG20/Techniques/working-examples/PDF22/jscript.jpg"
                       height="462"
                       width="506"/>
                  <alt> Text Field Properties dialog, with the Validate tab open to specify JavaScript validation code.</alt>
               </image> 
            </p>
            <codeblock xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[// JavaScript code for date mask format MM/DD/YYYY
var re = /^[mdy0-9]{2}\/[mdy0-9]{2}\/[mdy0-9]{4}$/
//Allow blank space in field
if (event.value !="") {
  if (re.test(event.value) == false) {
    app.alert ({
       cTitle: "Incorrect Format",
       cMsg: "Please enter date using mm/dd/yyyy format"
    });
  }
}
]]></codeblock>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p> 
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.adobe.com/devnet/acrobat/javascript.html">JavaScript
    					for Acrobat</loc> 
               </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </see-also>
   </resources>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="G89"/>
      <relatedtech idref="SCR18"/>
      <relatedtech idref="PDF23"/>
      <relatedtech idref="PDF10"/>
      <relatedtech idref="PDF5"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <p>For each form field that requires specific input, verify that validation
    					information and instructions are provided by applying the following: </p>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p> Check that the format or value that is required is indicated
    					in the form control's label. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Use an erroneous format or value and move off the field: make
    						sure that an alert describing the error is provided. </p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>#1 and #2 are true. </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
   <admin>
      <source>
         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
              href="http://trace.wisc.edu/wcag_wiki/index.php?title=Indicating_when_user_input_falls_outside_the_required_format_or_values_in_PDF_forms"/>
      </source>
   </admin>
</technique>
