<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="PDF4">
   <short-name>Hiding decorative images with the Artifact tag in PDF documents</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p use-id="pdf.applicability.general"/>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="text-equiv-all" relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <ua-issues>
      <ua-issue use-id="pdf.ua-issue.general"/>
   </ua-issues>
   <description>
      <p>The purpose of this technique is to show how purely decorative images
    				in PDF documents can be marked so that they can be ignored by Assistive
    				Technology by using the /Artifact tag. This is typically accomplished
    				by using a tool for authoring PDF. </p>
      <p>In PDF, artifacts are generally graphics objects or other markings
    				that are not part of the authored content. Examples of artifacts include
    				page header or footer information, lines or other graphics separating
    				sections of the page, or decorative images. </p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Marking a background image as an artifact using Adobe
    					Acrobat 9 Pro's TouchUp Reading Order Tool</head>
         <description>
            <p>This example is shown with Adobe Acrobat Pro. There are other software tools that perform similar functions. See the list of other software tools in <specref ref="pdf_notes_acc-sup_files_applications"/>.</p>
            <p>The TouchUp Reading Order Tool can be used to mark an image as "Background," which
    						removes it from the document tag structure. </p>
            <olist>
               <item>
                  <p> Open the TouchUp Reading Order Tool in Acrobat Pro: Advanced &gt; Accessibility &gt; TouchUp
    						Reading Order </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p> Select the decorative image in the document </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p> In the TouchUp Reading Order Tool, click the Background button
    							to remove the selected image from the tag structure </p>
               </item>
            </olist>
            <p>The screenshot below illustrates this example. </p>
            <p>
               <image>
                  <img xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       source="/WAI/WCAG20/Techniques/working-examples/PDF4/turo_background.gif"
                       height="501"
                       width="267"/>
                  <alt>screen shot showing use of the TouchUp Reading Order panel to remove an image from the tag tree</alt>
               </image> 
            </p>
            <p>This example is shown in operation in the <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    href="decorative-image.docx"
                    linktype="examples">working example of creating a decorative image (Word file)</loc> and <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    href="decorative-image.pdf"
                    linktype="examples">working example of marking a background image as an artifact (PDF file)</loc>.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Marking an image as an artifact in a PDF document using
    				an /Artifact tag or property list</head>
         <description>
            <p>The PDF specification allows images to be marked as "artifacts" as
    						defined in Section 14.8.2.2 (Real Content and Artifacts) in <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    href="http://www.adobe.com/content/dam/Adobe/en/devnet/pdf/pdfs/PDF32000_2008.pdf">PDF
    							1.7 (ISO 32000-1)</loc>. An artifact is explicitly distinguished from
    						real content by enclosing it in a marked-content sequence with the
    						/Artifact tag. </p>
            <p>/Artifact </p>
            <codeblock xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[BMC  ...  EMC    ]]></codeblock>
            <p>or </p>
            <p>/Artifact propertyList </p>
            <codeblock xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[BDC  ...  EMC  ]]></codeblock>
            <p>The first is used to identify a generic artifact; the second is
    						used for artifacts that have an associated property list. Note, to
    						aid in text reflow, artifacts should be defined with property lists
    						whenever possible. Artifacts lacking a specified bounding box are
    						likely to be discarded during reflow. </p>
            <p>Property list entries for artifacts include Type, BBox, Attached,
    						and Subtype. </p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p> Section 14.8.2.2 (Real Content and Artifacts) in <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.adobe.com/content/dam/Adobe/en/devnet/pdf/pdfs/PDF32000_2008.pdf">PDF
    					1.7 (ISO 32000-1)</loc> 
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.adobe.com/accessibility/products/acrobat.html">PDF and Accessibility</loc>
               </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </see-also>
   </resources>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>For an image that is purely decorative, use one of the following
    					to verify that it is marked as an artifact:</p>
               <ulist>
                  <item>
                     <p> Read the PDF document with a screen reader, listening to hear
    						that the decorative image is not announced when 
reading the content line-by-line. </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p> Using a PDF editor, make sure the decorative image is marked as an artifact. </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p> Reflow the document and make sure the
    								decorative image does not appear on the page. </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p> Use a tool that is capable of showing the /Artifact entry
    									or property list, such as aDesigner, to open the PDF document
    									and verify that decorative images are marked as artifacts. </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p> Use a tool
that exposes the document through the accessibility API and verify that the
decorative image is not exposed through the API. </p>
                  </item>
               </ulist>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>#1 is true. </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
   <admin>
      <source>
         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
              href="http://trace.wisc.edu/wcag_wiki/index.php?title=Hiding_decorative_images_with_the_Artifact_tag_in_PDF_documents"/>
      </source>
   </admin>
</technique>
