<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="PDF5">
   <short-name>Indicating required form controls in PDF forms</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>Tagged PDF documents with forms</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="minimize-error-identified" relationship="sufficient"/>
      <success-criterion idref="minimize-error-cues" relationship="cosufficient"/>
      <success-criterion idref="minimize-error-suggestions" relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <ua-issues>
      <ua-issue use-id="pdf.ua-issue.general"/>
   </ua-issues>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to notify the user when a field
    				that must be completed has not been completed in a PDF form. Required
    				fields are implemented using the /Ff entry in the form field's dictionary
    				(see Table 220 in Section 12.7 (Interactive Forms) of <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
              href="http://www.adobe.com/content/dam/Adobe/en/devnet/pdf/pdfs/PDF32000_2008.pdf">PDF
    					1.7 (ISO 32000-1)</loc>. This is normally accomplished using a tool for
    				authoring PDF. </p>
      <p>If errors are found, an alert dialog describes the nature of the error
    				in text. This may be accomplished through scripting created by the
    				author (see, for example, <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
              href="SCR18"
              linktype="techniques">SCR18:
    					Providing client-side validation and alert</loc>). User agents, such
    				as Adobe Acrobat Pro and LiveCycle, can provide automatic alerts (as
    				described in the examples below). </p>
      <p>
         <emph role="strong">Note</emph>: once the user dismisses the alert dialog, it
    				may be helpful if the script positions the keyboard focus on the field
    				where the error occurred, although some users may expect the focus
    				to remain on the last control focused prior to the alert appearing.
    				Authors should exercise care to ensure that any movement of the focus
    				will be expected. For example, if the alert announces a missing required
    				phone number, positioning the focus on the phone number field when
    				the alert is dismissed can be regarded as helpful and expected. In
    				some cases, however, this may not be possible. If multiple input errors
    				occur on the page, another approach must be taken to error reporting. 
(See, for example, the <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
              href="http://www.adobe.com/devnet/acrobat/javascript.html">Adobe scripting resources.</loc>) </p>
      <p>Ensuring that users are aware an error has occurred, can determine
    				what is wrong, and can correct it are keys to software usability and
    				accessibility. Meeting this objective helps ensure that all users can
    				complete transactions with ease and confidence. </p>
      <section id="PDF5_labels">
         <head> Labels for required form controls </head>
         <p>It is also important that users are aware that an error <emph role="strong">may</emph> occur.
    				You can incorporate this information in labels; for example,   "Date
    				(required)" or the use of a red asterisk to indicate required
    				fields. (Make sure that a legend appears on each form with required
    				fields, e.g., "* = required field".) See <specref ref="PDF10"/>. </p>
      </section>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Creating a required field in a PDF form using Adobe Acrobat
    					9 Pro</head>
         <description>
            <p>This example is shown with Adobe Acrobat Pro. There are other software tools that perform similar functions. See the list of other software tools in <specref ref="pdf_notes_acc-sup_files_applications"/>.</p>
            <olist>
               <item>
                  <p> Access the context menu of the field and select the Properties
    						dialog. </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p> If the field is required, check the Required box. This checkbox
    							forces the user to fill in the selected form field. If the user attempts
    							to submit the form while a required field is blank, an error message
    							appears and the empty required form field is highlighted. </p>
               </item>
            </olist>
            <p>
               <image>
                  <img xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       source="/WAI/WCAG20/Techniques/working-examples/PDF5/form4.jpg"
                       height="388"
                       width="642"/>
                  <alt>The Properties dialog for a form field. The Required box is checked.</alt>
               </image> 
            </p>
            <p>This example is shown in operation in the <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    href="required-fields.pdf"
                    linktype="examples">working example of creating a required field in Acrobat</loc>.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Creating a required field in a PDF form using Adobe LiveCycle
    				Designer ES 8.2.1</head>
         <description>
            <p>This example is shown with Adobe LiveCycle Designer. There are other software tools that perform similar functions. See the list of other software tools in <specref ref="pdf_notes_acc-sup_files_applications"/>.</p>
            <olist>
               <item>
                  <p> Access the context menu of the form control, select Palettes,
    						and select Object. </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p> Select "User entered - Required" from the Type pulldown. </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p> Enter an error message in the "Empty Message" field.
    							This message appears when a user tries to submit the form without
    							entering a value in the required field. </p>
               </item>
            </olist>
            <p>If the user attempts to submit the form with a required field left
    						blank, the Empty Message text appears and the empty required field
    						is highlighted. </p>
            <p>The image below shows the Adobe LiveCycle Object palette with the
    						required selection. </p>
            <p>
               <image>
                  <img xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       source="/WAI/WCAG20/Techniques/working-examples/PDF5/lc-required2.gif"
                       height="468"
                       width="345"/>
                  <alt>Image of Adobe LiveCycle Object palette showing the 'User entered - Required' selection.</alt>
               </image> 
            </p>
            <p>You can also add explicit text to the form label to indicate required
    					fields (e.g., "(Required)"). </p>
            <p>This example is shown in operation in the <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    href="required-fields-lc.pdf"
                    linktype="examples">working example of creating a required field in LiveCycle Designer</loc>.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Adding a required text field in a PDF form using the /Tx
    				field type and Ff flag</head>
         <description>
            <p>The following code fragment illustrates code that is typical for the
    						object definitions for a typical text field. Note that the text field
    						is required, using the Ff flag. This is typically accomplished by an
    						authoring tool. </p>
            <codeblock xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[<< /AP -dict-                                                   
   /DA /Helv  0 Tf 0 g
   /DR -dict-
   /F 0x4
   /FT Tx              % FT key set to Tx for Text Field
   /Ff 0x2             % Ff integer 0x2 value indicates required
   /P -dict-
   /Rect -array-
   /StructParent 0x1
   /Subtype Widget
   /T First            % Partial field name First
   /TU First name (required)  % TU tool tip value serves as short description
   /Type Annot
   /V Pat Jones
>>
...
<Start Stream>
 BT
  /P <</MCID 0 >>BDC
  /CS0 cs 0  scn 
  /TT0 1 Tf
    -0.001 Tc 0.003 Tw 11.04 0 0 11.04 72 709.56 Tm
    [(P)-6(le)-3(as)10(e)-3( )11(P)-6(rin)2(t)-3( Y)8(o)-7(u)2(r N)4(a)11(m)-6(e)]TJ
  0 Tc 0 Tw 9.533 0 Td
  ( )Tj
  -0.004 Tc 0.004 Tw 0.217 0 Td
  [(\()-5(R)-4(e)5(q)-1(u)-1(i)-3(r)-3(e)-6(d)-1(\))]TJ
 EMC
  /P <</MCID 1 >>BDC
  0 Tc 0 Tw 4.283 0 Td
  [( )-2( )]TJ
   EMC
   /ArtifactSpan <</MCID 2 >>BDC
   0.002 Tc -0.002 Tw 0.456 0 Td
  [(__)11(___)11(___)11(___)11(___)11(_)11(____)11(___)11(___)11(__)]TJ
  0 Tc 0 Tw 13.391 0 Td
  ( )Tj
  EMC
 ET
<End Stream>
]]></codeblock>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p> Section 12.7 (Interactive Forms) in <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.adobe.com/content/dam/Adobe/en/devnet/pdf/pdfs/PDF32000_2008.pdf">PDF
    				1.7 (ISO 32000-1)</loc> 
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> 
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://partners.adobe.com/public/developer/xml/index_arch.html">Adobe
    					XML Forms Architecture (XFA)</loc> 
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.adobe.com/accessibility/products/acrobat.html">PDF and Accessibility</loc>
               </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </see-also>
   </resources>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="G83"/>
      <relatedtech idref="H90"/>
      <relatedtech idref="SCR18"/>
      <relatedtech idref="PDF23"/>
      <relatedtech idref="PDF10"/>
      <relatedtech idref="PDF22"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <p>For each form field that is required, verify that validation information
    					and instructions are provided by applying the following: </p>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p> Check that the required status is indicated in the form control's
    					label. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Leave the field blank and submit the form. Check that an alert
    						describing the error is provided. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Use a tool that exposes the document through the accessibility
    							API, and verify that the required property is indicated. </p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>#1, #2, and #3 are true. </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
   <admin>
      <source>
         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
              href="http://trace.wisc.edu/wcag_wiki/index.php?title=Indicating_required_form_controls_in_PDF_forms"/>
      </source>
   </admin>
</technique>
