<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="PDF8">
   <short-name>Providing definitions for abbreviations via an E entry for a structure
    			element</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>Tagged PDF documents containing abbreviations or acronyms</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="meaning-located" relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <ua-issues>
      <ua-issue use-id="pdf.ua-issue.general"/>
   </ua-issues>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to provide an expansion or definition
    				of an abbreviation for the first occurrence of the abbreviation. For
    				example, a reference to an abbreviation, such as   "WCAG," should
    				be available as   "Web Content Accessibility Guidelines (WCAG)" on
    				its first occurrence in a document. </p>
      <p>This is done by setting expansion text using an /E entry for a structure
    				element, and is normally accomplished using a tool for authoring PDF.
    				A Span structure element is typically used to tag the abbreviation,
    				but the /E entry is valid with any structure element. </p>
      <p>This technique is applicable for any abbreviation, including acronyms
    				and initialisms. Note that on the first occurrence of the abbreviation,
    				both the abbreviation and the expansion text must be provided. This
    				will aid recognition of later use of the abbreviation. </p>
      <p>PDF documents may be enhanced by providing expansions for abbreviations.
    				In fact, such expansions are required for accessibility to ensure understanding
    				by people who have difficulty decoding words; rely on screen magnification
    				(which may obscure context); have limited memory; or who have difficulty
    				using context to aid understanding. </p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Adding an /E entry to an abbreviation using Adobe Acrobat
    					9 Pro's Tags panel</head>
         <description>
            <p>This example is shown with Adobe Acrobat Pro. There are other software tools that perform similar functions. See the list of other software tools in <specref ref="pdf_notes_acc-sup_files_applications"/>.</p>
            <p>In a tagged PDF document: </p>
            <olist>
               <item>
                  <p> Select the Tags panel, using Views &gt; Navigation Panes &gt; Tags </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>Select the first instance of the abbreviated text that needs to be expanded. If the selected text is part of a larger tag, access the Tags panel options menu, select Create Tag from Selection, and create a new Span tag. In this example, the text "WCAG2" (within the LBody tag) has been enclosed in a Span tag.</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p> In the Tags panel, access the context menu for the spanned text
    							and select Properties... to open the TouchUp Properties dialog for
    							the Span tag. </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p> On the Content tab of the TouchUp Properties dialog, enter the
    								expansion text, followed by the originally selected text. </p>
               </item>
            </olist>
            <p>The following image illustrates this technique: </p>
            <p>
               <image>
                  <img xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       source="/WAI/WCAG20/Techniques/working-examples/PDF8/abbr.jpg"
                       height="662"
                       width="521"/>
                  <alt>The addition of expansion text to an abbreviation using the Tags panel. The text 'WCAG2.0' has been selected and a Span tag created for it. The expansion text 'Web Content Accessibility Guidelines (WCAG) 2.0' is entered as the expansion of 'WCAG2.0' using the TouchUp Properties dialog </alt>
               </image> 
            </p>
            <p>This example is shown in operation in the <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    href="headers-definitions.docx"
                    linktype="examples">working example of Providing definitions for Abbreviations (Word document)</loc>, <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    href="headers-definitions.odt"
                    linktype="examples">working example of Providing definitions for Abbreviations (OpenOffice document)</loc>, and <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    href="headers-definitions.pdf"
                    linktype="examples">working example of Providing definitions for Abbreviations (PDF document)</loc>.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Using a /Span structure element with an /E entry to define
    				an abbreviation</head>
         <description>
            <p>The following code fragment illustrates code that is typical for using
    						the /Span structure element to define an abbreviation. </p>
            <p>This example uses the sentence "Sugar is commonly sold in 5 lb
    						bags." The abbreviation "lb" is tagged as a /Span structure
    						element with an /E entry (typically accomplished by an authoring tool). </p>
            <codeblock xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[ 1 0 obj                                  % structure element
   << /Type /StructElemen
            /S /Span                      % element type
            /P ...                        % Parent in structure hierarchy
            /K << /Type /MCR
                        /Page 2 0 R       % Page containing marked-content sequence
                        /MCID 0           % Marked content identifier for "lb"
               >>
            /E  (pound, lb)
    >>
 endobj
]]></codeblock>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Using a /TH structure element with an /E entry to define
    				an abbreviation</head>
         <description>
            <p>As noted in the Description, the /E entry is valid with any structure
    						element. </p>
            <p>The following code fragment illustrates code that is typical for using
    						an /E entry to define an abbreviation. </p>
            <p>A table that contains columns for each month uses abbreviations as
    						the values of column headers. The expansion for each abbreviation is
    						provided as the /E entry of the /TH structure element (typically accomplished
    						by an authoring tool). </p>
            <codeblock xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[ 1 0 obj                                  % structure element
   << /Type /StructElemen
            /S /TH                        % element type
            /P ...                        % Parent in structure hierarchy
            /K << /Type /MCR
                        /Page 2 0 R       % Page containing marked-content sequence
                        /MCID 0           % Marked content identifier for "Dec"
               >>
            /E  (December, Dec)
    >>
 endobj
]]></codeblock>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p> Section 14.9.5 (Expansion of Abbreviations and Acronyms) in <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.adobe.com/content/dam/Adobe/en/devnet/pdf/pdfs/PDF32000_2008.pdf">PDF
    					1.7 (ISO 32000-1)</loc> 
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> 
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/dd318521%28VS.85%29.aspx">Microsoft
    							Inspect.exe tool</loc> 
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.adobe.com/accessibility/products/acrobat.html">PDF and Accessibility</loc>
               </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </see-also>
   </resources>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="G102"/>
      <relatedtech idref="G55"/>
      <relatedtech idref="G62"/>
      <relatedtech idref="G70"/>
      <relatedtech idref="G97"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p> Verify that the first occurrence of abbreviations that require
    					expansion text have /E entries on an enclosing tag by one of the
    					following and that both the abbreviation and the expansion text are
    					provided:</p>
               <ulist>
                  <item>
                     <p> In Windows, use Microsoft's Inspect.exe tool, or some other
    						tool that allows inspection of the MSAA interface, to locate
    						the text of the abbreviation in the document tree and ensure
    						that the value of the abbreviation is in the expansion text. </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p> In a PDF editor, locate the tag
    							for the text that is the abbreviation, and check that an expansion
    							or definition is provided for each abbreviation in the Expansion
    							Text field in the corresponding tag's properties. </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p> Read the PDF document with a screen reader, listening to hear
    								that on the first occurrence, the abbreviation and expansion
    								are read when the screen reader reads the content line-by-line. </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p> Use a tool that is capable of showing the /E entry value,
    									such as aDesigner to open the PDF document and view the GUI summary
    									to read the text expansions for abbreviations. </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p> Use a tool that exposes the document through the accessibility
    										API and verify that the text expansion of the abbreviation is
    										properly implemented. </p>
                  </item>
               </ulist>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>Check #1 is true. </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
   <admin>
      <source>
         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
              href="http://trace.wisc.edu/wcag_wiki/index.php?title=Providing_definitions_for_abbreviations_via_an_E_entry_for_a_structure_element"/>
      </source>
   </admin>
</technique>
