<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="F1">
   <short-name>Failure of Success Criterion 1.3.2 due to changing the meaning of content by
                    positioning information with CSS</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>All technologies that support CSS.</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="content-structure-separation-sequence" relationship="failure"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>This describes the failure condition that results when CSS, rather than
                        structural markup, is used to modify the visual layout of the content, and
                        the modified layout changes the meaning of the content. Using the
                        positioning properties of CSS2, content may be displayed at any position on
                        the user's viewport. The order in which items appear on a screen may be
                        different than the order they are found in the source document. Assistive
                        technologies rely on the source code or other programmatically determined
                        order to render the content in the correct sequence. Thus, it is important
                        not to rely on CSS to visually position content in a specific sequence if this sequence results in a meaning that is different from the programmatically determined reading order. 
          </p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group role="failure">
         <description>
            <p>The following example demonstrates how CSS has been improperly used
                                to create a set of columns. In addition, the text appears visually
                                in the browser in a different order than in the markup. </p>
            <p>In this example a class is defined for each object that is being
                                positioned. When style sheets are applied, the text appears in two
                                columns. Elements of class "menu1" (Products) and "menu2"
                                (Locations) appear as column headings. "Telephones, Computers, and
                                Portable MP3 Players" are listed under Products and "Idaho" and
                                "Wisconsin" are listed under Locations (note the different order for
                                Idaho and Wisconsin in the source code order). </p>
            <p>Since appropriate structural elements have not been used, when style
                                sheets are not applied, all of the text appears in one line in the
                                source order, "Products Locations Telephones Computers Portable MP3
                                Players Wisconsin Idaho." </p>
            <p>Here is the HTML content:</p>
         </description>
         <code role="html401"><![CDATA[
<div class="box">      
     <span class="menu1">Products</span>       
     <span class="menu2">Locations</span>       
     <span class="item1">Telephones</span>       
     <span class="item2">Computers</span>       
     <span class="item3">Portable MP3 Players</span>       
     <span class="item5">Wisconsin</span>       
     <span class="item4">Idaho</span>
</div>
]]></code>
         <description>
            <p>Here are the styles for the above content:</p>
         </description>
         <code role="html401"><![CDATA[
.menu1 { 
     position: absolute; 
     top: 3em; 
     left: 0em;     
     margin: 0px; 
     font-family: sans-serif;     
     font-size: 120%; 
     color: red; 
     background-color: white 
}        
.menu2 { 
     position: absolute; 
     top: 3em; 
     left: 10em;     
     margin: 0px; 
     font-family: sans-serif;     
     font-size: 120%; 
     color: red; 
     background-color: white 
}      
.item1 { 
     position: absolute; 
     top: 7em; 
     left: 0em; 
     margin: 0px 
}      
.item2 { 
     position: absolute; 
     top: 8em; 
     left: 0em; 
     margin: 0px 
}      
.item3 { 
     position: absolute; 
     top: 9em; 
     left: 0em; 
     margin: 0px 
}      
.item4 { 
     position: absolute; 
     top: 7em; 
     left: 14em; 
     margin: 0px 
}      
.item5 { 
     position: absolute; 
     top: 8em; left: 14em; 
     margin: 0px 
}      
#box { 
     position: absolute; 
     top: 5em; 
     left: 5em 
} 
]]></code>
         <description>
            <p>A better solution for this content would be to use more meaningful
                                elements, such as a table or a definition list.</p>
            <ulist>
               <item>
                  <p> 
                     <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                          href="cssposfailure.html"
                          linktype="examples">Example
                                            of CSS positioning failure</loc>
									         </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p> 
                     <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                          href="cssposfailurenostyle.html"
                          linktype="examples">Example of CSS positioning failure with styles
                                        removed</loc>
									         </p>
               </item>
            </ulist>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources/>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="C6"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <p>For content which uses CSS for positioning: </p>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Remove the style information from the document or turn off use of
                                    style sheets in the user agent.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Check that the reading order of the content is correct and the
                                    meaning of the content is preserved.</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>If step #2 is false, then this failure condition applies and the
                                    content fails this Success Criterion.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
