<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="F13">
   <short-name>Failure of Success Criterion 1.1.1 and 1.4.1 due to having a text alternative that does not
                    include information that is conveyed by color differences in the image</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>All technologies.</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="text-equiv-all" relationship="failure"/>
      <success-criterion idref="visual-audio-contrast-without-color" relationship="failure"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to describe the failure that occurs when
                        an image uses color differences to convey information, but the text alternative for the
                        image does not convey that information. This can cause problems for people
                        who are blind or colorblind because they will not be able to perceive the
                        information conveyed by the color differences.</p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>A bar chart of sales data is provided as an image. The chart includes
                                yearly sales figures for four employees in the Sales Department. The
                                text alternative for the image says, "The following bar chart
                                displays the yearly sales figures for the Sales Department. Mary
                                sold 3.1 Million; Fred, 2.6 Million; Bob, 2.2 Million; and Andrew,
                                3.4 Million. The red bars indicate sales that were below the yearly
                                quota". This text alternative fails to provide the information which
                                is conveyed by the color red in the image. The alternative should
                                indicate which people did not meet the sales quota rather than
                                relying on color.</p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
   </examples>
   <resources/>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="G94"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <p>For all images in the content that convey information by way of color differences: </p>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Check that the information conveyed by color differences is not included in
                                    the text alternative for the image.</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>If step #1 is true, then this failure condition applies and
                                    content fails the Success Criterion.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
