<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="F14">
   <short-name>Failure of Success Criterion 1.3.3 due to identifying content only by its shape or
                    location</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>All technologies.</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="content-structure-separation-understanding"
                         relationship="failure"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to show how identifying content only by
                        its visual shape or location makes content difficult to understand and operate.
                        When only visual identification or location is used, users with visual
                        disabilities may find it difficult to locate content since they cannot see
                        the screen or may perceive only a small portion of the screen at one time.
                        Also, location of content can vary if page layout varies due to variations
                        in font, window, or screen size.</p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>The navigation instructions for a site state, "To go to next page,
                                press the button to the right. To go back to previous page, press
                                the button to the left." </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>A user is reading a news article in an on-line newspaper. The article
                                contains an illustration and additional links for more information.
                                Within the text of the article is a statement, "Please see sidebar
                                to the left of the illustration for links to additional
                                information." An assistive technology user would have difficulty
                                finding the illustration and the sidebar. Some alternatives would be
                                to include the list of links within the text; to provide an in-page
                                link within the text which links to the sidebar; to provide a
                                heading for the sidebar which can be used for navigation and refer
                                to the heading in the instructions.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>A user is completing an on-line survey. There are three buttons at
                                the bottom of the survey form. The instructions state, "Press the
                                square button to exit the survey without saving, Press the triangle
                                button to save in-progress survey results. You may return later to
                                complete the survey. Press the round button to submit the survey
                                results." A screen reader user or a user unable to distinguish shapes cannot determine which button is
                                square, triangular, or round. The buttons must have additional
                                information to indicate their functions or their shapes.</p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
   </examples>
   <resources/>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="G96"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Examine the Web page for textual references to content within the
                                    Web page. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Check that the references do not rely on only the visual shape or
                                    location of the content.</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>If step #2 is false, then this failure condition applies and the
                                    content fails this Success Criterion.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
