<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="F15">
   <short-name>Failure of Success Criterion 4.1.2 due to implementing custom controls that do not use an accessibility API for the technology, or do so incompletely</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p> Applies to all technologies that support an accessibility API. </p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="ensure-compat-rsv" relationship="failure"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p> When standard controls from accessible technologies are used, they usually are programmed in a way that uses and supports the accessibility API. If custom controls are created, however, then it is up to the programmer to be sure that the newly created control supports the accessibility API. If this is not done, then assistive technologies will not be able to understand what the control is or how to operate it or may not even know of its existence.</p>
      <note>
         <p>For technologies that support it, WAI-ARIA can be used to expose a custom control's role, name, value, states, and properties via the accessibility API for the technology.</p>
      </note>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group role="failure">
         <description>
            <p>A music player is designed with custom controls that look like
                                musical notes that are stretched for volume, tone etc. The
                                programmer does not make the new control support the Accessibility
                                API. As a result - the controls cannot be identified or controlled
                                from AT. </p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p> 
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/ms696082.aspx">Active Accessibility Checker (AccExplorer)</loc> 
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.w3.org/TR/wai-aria/">Accessible Rich Internet Applications (WAI-ARIA) 1.0</loc>
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="https://www.w3.org/WAI/ARIA/apg/">WAI-ARIA  Authoring Practices Guide</loc> 
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.w3.org/TR/aria-in-html/">Using WAI-ARIA in HTML</loc> 
               </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </see-also>
   </resources>
   <related-techniques/>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p> Using the accessibility checker for the technology (or if
                                    that is not available, inspect the code or test with an
                                    assistive technology), check the controls to see if they support
                                    the accessibility API. </p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p> If step #1 is false, then this failure condition applies and the
                                    content fails this Success Criterion </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
