<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="F17">
   <short-name>Failure of Success Criterion 1.3.1 and 4.1.1 due to insufficient information in DOM to determine
                    one-to-one relationships (e.g., between labels with same id) in HTML</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p> Applies to the Document Object Model (DOM) for HTML and XHTML</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="content-structure-separation-programmatic"
                         relationship="failure"/>
      <success-criterion idref="ensure-compat-parses" relationship="failure"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p> The objective of this technique is to ensure that Web pages can be
                        interpreted consistently by user agents, including assistive technology. If
                        it is ambiguous, different user agents including assistive technologies
                        could present different information to their users. Users of assistive
                        technology for example may have different information presented to them than
                        users of other mainstream user agents. Some elements and attributes in
                        markup languages are required to have unique values, and if this requirement
                        is not honored, the result can be irregular or not uniquely resolvable
                        content. For example, when id attribute values are not unique, they are
                        particularly problematic when referenced by labels, headers in data tables,
                        or used as fragment identifiers, as user agents do not have enough
                        information to  determine essential relationships (i.e., to determine
                        which label goes with which item). </p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group role="failure">
         <description>
            <ulist>
               <item>
                  <p> A label element whose for attribute value is an idref that
                                        points to a non-existent id </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p> An id attribute value that is not unique. </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p> An accesskey attribute value that is not unique </p>
               </item>
            </ulist>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources/>
   <related-techniques/>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p> Check for id and accesskey values which are not unique within
                                    the document. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Check that attribute values that have an idref value have a
                                    corresponding id value. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>For tables that use the axis attribute, check that all values
                                    listed in the axis attribute have a corresponding id value in a
                                    table header cell in the same table.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>For client-side image maps, check that the value of the usemap
                                    attribute has a corresponding id value if the usemap attribute
                                    is not a URI.</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>If step #1, step #3 or step #4 is true or step #2 is false, then this failure
                                    condition applies and the content fails the success
                                criterion.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
