<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="F19">
   <short-name>Failure of Conformance Requirement 1 due to not providing a method for the user to find the alternative conforming version of a non-conforming Web page</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p> Sites that provide alternative, WCAG-conforming versions of nonconforming
                        primary content.</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <conformance-criterion idref="cc1" relationship="failure"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p> This failure technique describes the situation in which an alternate, conforming version of the content is provided, but there is no direct way for a user to tell that it is available or where to find it. Such content fails the Success Criterion because the user cannot find the conforming version.</p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p> A link or a search takes a user directly to one of the nonconforming
                                pages in the Web site. There is neither an indication that an
                                alternate page is available, nor a path to the alternate page from
                                the nonconforming page. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Nonconforming pages on the Web site inform the user that a
                                conforming version is available and provide a link to the home page.
                                However, the user must search the site for the conforming version of
                                the page, so the functionality does not meet the requirements of the
                                Success Criterion. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> A user is able to use the nonconforming Web site for most pages. But
                                when the user is not able to access a particular page, there is no
                                way to find the conforming version of the page. </p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
   </examples>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="G136"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p> Identify a nonconforming page that has an alternative conforming
                                    version. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Determine if the nonconforming page provides a link to the
                                    conforming version. </p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p> If step #2 is false, the content fails the Success Criterion. </p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
