<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="F2">
   <short-name>Failure of Success Criterion 1.3.1 due to using changes in text presentation to convey information without using the appropriate markup or text</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>All technologies that support images or presentation markup.</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="content-structure-separation-programmatic"
                         relationship="failure"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>This document describes a failure that occurs when a change in the appearance of text conveys meaning without using appropriate semantic markup. This failure also applies to images of text that are not enclosed in the appropriate semantic markup.</p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group role="failure">
         <head>Using CSS to style the <el>p</el> element to look like a heading</head>
         <description>
            <p>The author intended to make a heading but didn't want the look of the default HTML heading. So they used CSS to style the P element to look like a heading and they called it a heading. But they failed to use the proper HTML heading element. Therefore, the Assisitive Technology could not distinguish it as a heading.</p>
         </description>
         <code role="html401"><![CDATA[
 <style type="text/css">
 .heading1{
        font-family: Times, serif;
        font-size:200%;
        font-weight:bold;
 }
 </style>

 <p class="heading1">Introduction</p>
 <p>This introduction provides detailed information about how to use this 
 ........
 </p>
]]></code>
         <description>
            <note>
               <p>In this case, the proper approach would be to use CSS to style the <el>H1</el> element in HTML.</p>
            </note>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group role="failure">
         <head>Images of text used as headings where the images are not marked up with heading tags</head>
         <description>
            <p>Chapter1.gif is an image of the words, "Chapter One" in a Garamond font sized at 20 pixels. This is a failure because at a minimum the img element should be enclosed within a header element. A better solution would be to eliminate the image and to enclose the text within a header element which has been styled using CSS.</p>
         </description>
         <code role="html401"><![CDATA[
<img src="Chapter1.gif" alt="Chapter One">
 
<p>Once upon a time in the land of the Web.....
</p>
]]></code>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group role="failure">
         <head>Using CSS to visually emphasize a phrase or word without conveying that emphasis semantically</head>
         <description>
            <p>The following example fails because the information conveyed by using the CSS <code><![CDATA[font-weight]]></code> property to change to a bold font is not conveyed through semantic markup or stated explicitly in the text.</p>
            <p>Here is a CSS class to specify bold:</p>
            <codeblock xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[
.yell {
  font-weight:bold;
  text-transform: uppercase;
}
]]></codeblock>
            <p>And here is the corresponding HTML:</p>
            <codeblock role="html401" xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[
<p>
 "I said, <span class="yell">no</span>, not before dinner!", 
 was the exasperated response when Timmy asked his mother for the 
 fourth time for an ice cream cone. 
 </p>
]]></codeblock>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources/>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="H42"/>
      <relatedtech idref="H49"/>
      <relatedtech idref="G115"/>
      <relatedtech idref="G117"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>For images of text:</p>
               <olist>
                  <item>
                     <p>Check if any images of text are used to convey structural information of the document.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>Check that the proper semantic structure (e.g., HTML headings) is used with the text to convey the information.</p>
                  </item>
               </olist>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>For styled text that conveys information:</p>
               <olist>
                  <item>
                     <p>Check if there is any styled text that conveys structural information.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>Check that in addition to styling, the proper semantic structure is used with the text to convey the information.</p>
                  </item>
               </olist>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>If check #1.1 is true, then #1.2 is true.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>If check #2.1 is true, then #2.2 is true.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
