<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="F22">
   <short-name>Failure of Success Criterion 3.2.5 due to opening windows that are not requested by the
                    user</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>General </p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="consistent-behavior-no-extreme-changes-context"
                         relationship="failure"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p> Failure due to opening new windows when the user does not expect them. New
                        windows take the focus away from what the user is reading or doing. This is
                        fine when the user has interacted with a piece of User Interface and expects
                        to get a new window, such as an options dialogue. The failure comes when
                        pop-ups appear unexpectedly. </p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group role="failure">
         <head/>
         <description>
            <p>When a user navigates to a page, a new window appears over the
                                existing user agent window, and the focus is moved to the new
                                window.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group role="failure">
         <head/>
         <description>
            <p> A user clicks on a link, and a new window appears. The original link
                                has no associated text saying that it will open a new window. </p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group role="failure">
         <head/>
         <description>
            <p>A user clicks on the body of a page and a new window appears. No
                                indication that the area that was clicked has functionality is
                                present. </p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group role="failure">
         <head/>
         <description>
            <p>A user clicks on undecorated text within the page and a new window
                                appears. The page has no visible indication that the area is functional.    </p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources/>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="SCR24"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p> Load the Web page. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Check if new (additional) windows open. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Find every actionable element, such as links and buttons, in the
                                    Web page. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Activate each element. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Check if activating the element opens a new window. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Check if elements that open new windows have associated text
                                    saying that will happen. The text can be displayed in the link,
                                    or available through a hidden association such as an HTML title
                                    attribute. </p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p> If step #2 is true, the failure condition applies and the content
                                    fails the Success Criterion </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> If step #5 is true and step #6 is false, the failure condition applies and
                                    the content fails the Success Criterion </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
