<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="F31">
   <short-name>Failure of Success Criterion 3.2.4 due to using two different labels for the same function on different Web pages within a set of Web pages </short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p> Applies to all technologies. </p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="consistent-behavior-consistent-functionality"
                         relationship="failure"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p> Components that have the same function in different Web pages are more
                        easily recognized if they are labeled consistently. If the naming is not
                        consistent, some users may get confused. </p>
      <note>
         <p>Text alternatives that are "consistent" are not always "identical." For
                            instance, you may have an graphical arrow at the bottom of a Web page
                            that links to the next Web page. The text alternative may say "Go to
                            page 4." Naturally, it would not be appropriate to repeat this exact
                            text alternative on the next Web page. It would be more appropriate to
                            say "Go to page 5". Although these text alternatives would not be
                            identical, they would be consistent, and therefore would not be failures
                            for this Success Criterion.</p>
      </note>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group role="failure">
         <head/>
         <description>
            <p> One of the most common examples of using inconsistent labels for
                                components with the same function is to use a button that says
                                "search" in one page and to use a button that says "find" on another
                                page when they both serve the identical function. </p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group role="failure">
         <head/>
         <description>
            <p>An online authoring tool that uses a button with "Save page" on one
                                page and "Save" on another page, in both cases for the same
                                function. </p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources/>
   <related-techniques/>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p> In a set of Web pages, find components with the same function
                                    that are repeated in multiple Web pages. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> For each component with the same function found in step #1, check
                                    that the naming is consistent. </p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <p> If step #2 is false then this failure condition applies and content fails
                            the Success Criterion. </p>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
