<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="F32">
   <short-name>Failure of Success Criterion 1.3.2 due to using white space characters to control
                    spacing within a word</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>All technologies.</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="content-structure-separation-sequence" relationship="failure"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to describe how using white space characters, such as space, tab, line break, or carriage return, to format individual words visually can be a failure to present meaningful sequences properly. When blank characters are inserted to control letter spacing within a word, they may change the interpretation of the word or cause it not to be programmatically recognized as a single word. 
          </p>
      <p>Inserting white space characters into an initialism is not an example of this
                        failure, since the white space does not change the interpretation of the
                        initialism and may make it easier to understand.</p>
      <p>The use of white space between words for visual formatting is not a failure,
                        since it does not change the interpretation of the words.</p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group role="failure">
         <head>Failure due to adding white space in the middle of a word</head>
         <description>
            <p>This example has white spaces within a word to space out the letters
                                in a heading. Screen readers may read each letter individually
                                instead of the word "Welcome."</p>
         </description>
         <code role="html401"><![CDATA[
<h1>W e l c o m e</h1>
]]></code>
         <description>
            <p>&amp;nbsp; can also be used to add white space, producing similar
                                failures:</p>
         </description>
         <code role="html401"><![CDATA[
<h1>H&nbsp;E&nbsp;L&nbsp;L&nbsp;O</h1>
]]></code>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group role="failure">
         <head>White space in the middle of a word changing its meaning</head>
         <description>
            <p>In Japanese, Han characters (Kanji) may have multiple readings that
                                mean very different things. In this example, the word is read
                                incorrectly because screen readers may not recognize these
                                characters as a word because of the white space between the
                                characters. The characters mean "Tokyo," but screen readers say
                                "Higashi Kyo".</p>
         </description>
         <code role="html401"><![CDATA[
<h1>東　京</h1>
]]></code>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group role="failure">
         <head>Using line break characters to format vertical text</head>
         <description>
            <p>In the row header cell of a data table containing Japanese text,
                                authors often create vertical text by using line break characters.
                                However screen readers are not able to read the words in vertical
                                text correctly because the line breaks occur within the word. In the
                                following example, "東京都"(Tokyo-to) will be read "Higashi Kyo
                                Miyako".</p>
         </description>
         <code role="html401"><![CDATA[
<table>
<caption>表1.　都道府県別一覧表</caption>
<tr>
<td></td>
<th scope="col">（見出しセル 1.）</th>
<th scope="col">（見出しセル 2.）</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th scope="row">東<br />京<br />都</th>
<td>（データセル 1.）</td>
<td>（データセル 2.）</td>
</tr>
・・・・・・
</table>
]]></code>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources/>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="C8"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <p>For each word that appears to have non-standard spacing between
                            characters: </p>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Check whether any words in the text of the content contain white
                                    space characters .</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>If step #1 is true, then this failure condition applies and the
                                    content fails this Success Criterion.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
