<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="F33">
   <short-name>Failure of Success Criterion 1.3.1 and 1.3.2 due to using white space characters to
                    create multiple columns in plain text content</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>All technologies.</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="content-structure-separation-programmatic"
                         relationship="failure"/>
      <success-criterion idref="content-structure-separation-sequence" relationship="failure"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to describe how using white space
                        characters, such as space, tab, line break, or carriage return, to format columns of
                        data in text content is a failure to use structure properly. Assistive
                        technologies will interpret content in the reading order of the current
                        language. Using white space characters to create multiple columns does not
                        provide the information in a natural reading order. Thus, the assistive
                        technology user will not be presented with the information in an
                        understandable manner.</p>
      <p>Plain text is not suitable for displaying multiple columns of text. Modify
                        the content to present the data in a different layout. Alternatively, use a
                        technology that provides structural elements to represent columnar data.</p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group role="failure">
         <description>
            <p>The following example incorrectly uses white space characters to
                                format a paragraph into a two column format.</p>
         </description>
         <code role="html401"><![CDATA[
Web Content Accessibility Guidelines      including blindness and low vision, 
2.0 (WCAG 2.0) covers a wide range of     deafness and hearing loss, learning 
issues and recommendations for making     difficulties, cognitive limitations, limited 
Web content more accessible. This         movement, speech difficulties, and 
document contains principles,             others. Following these guidelines will 
guidelines, Success Criteria, benefits,   also make your Web content more 
and examples that define and explain      accessible to the vast majority of users, 
the requirements for making Web-based     including older users. It will also enable
information and applications accessible.  people to access Web content using 
"Accessible" means usable to a wide       many different devices - including a 
range of people with disabilities,        wide variety of assistive technologies.
]]></code>
         <description>
            <p>If this table was to be interpreted and spoken by a screen reader it
                                would speak the following lines:</p>
            <ulist>
               <item>
                  <p>Web Content Accessibility Guidelines including blindness and
                                        low vision,</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>2.0 (WCAG 2.0) covers a wide range of deafness and hearing
                                        loss, learning</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>issues and recommendations for making difficulties, cognitive
                                        limitations, limited</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>Web content more accessible. This movement, speech
                                        difficulties, and</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>(additional lines eliminated for brevity) </p>
               </item>
            </ulist>
            <p>If the text were reflowed, or changed from a fixed to a variable
                                font, or increased in size until lines no longer fit on the page,
                                similar interpretation issues would arise in the visual
                                presentation.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources/>
   <related-techniques/>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Examine the document for data or information presented in
                                    columnar format.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Check whether the columns are created using white space
                                    characters to lay out the information.</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>If step #2 is true, then this failure condition applies and the
                                    content fails these Success Criteria.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
