<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="F34">
   <short-name>Failure of Success Criterion 1.3.1 and 1.3.2 due to using white space characters to
                    format tables in plain text content</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>All technologies.</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="content-structure-separation-programmatic"
                         relationship="failure"/>
      <success-criterion idref="content-structure-separation-sequence" relationship="failure"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to describe how using white space
                        characters, such as space, tab, line break, or carriage return, to format tables in text
                        content is a failure to use structure properly. When tables are created in
                        this manner there is no way to indicate that a cell is intended to be a
                        header cell, no way to associate the table header cells with the table data
                        cells, or to navigate directly to a particular cell in a table.</p>
      <p>In addition, assistive technologies will interpret content in the reading
                        order of the current language. Using white space to organize data in a
                        visual table does not provide the information in a natural reading order in
                        the source of the document. Thus, the assistive technology user will not be
                        presented with the information in a logical reading order.</p>
      <p>Plain text is not suitable for displaying complex information like tables
                        because the structure of the table cannot be perceived. Rather than using
                        visual formatting to represent tabular relations, 
            tabular information would need to be presented using a different technology or presented linearly. (See Presenting tabular information in plain text)</p>
      <!-- BBC: The above should link to the undrafted technique by the same name in 1.3.1-->
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group role="failure">
         <description>
            <p>The following example incorrectly uses white space to format a Menu
                                as a visual table.</p>
         </description>
         <code role="html401"><![CDATA[
Menu
         Breakfast        Lunch           Dinner

Monday   2 fried eggs    tomato soup     garden salad
         bacon           hamburger       Fried Chicken
         toast           onion rings     green beans
                         Oatmeal cookie  mashed potatoes

Tuesday   Pancakes       vegetable soup  Caesar salad
          sausage        hot dogs        Spaghetti with meatballs
          orange juice   potato salad    Italian bread
                         brownie         ice cream
]]></code>
         <description>
            <p>If this table was to be interpreted and spoken by a screen reader it
                                would speak the following lines:</p>
            <ulist>
               <item>
                  <p>Menu</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>Breakfast Lunch Dinner</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>Monday 2 fried eggs tomato soup garden salad</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>bacon hamburger Fried Chicken</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>toast onion rings green beans</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>Oatmeal cookie mashed potatoes</p>
               </item>
            </ulist>
            <p>This reading order does not make sense since there is no structure in
                                the table for the assistive technology to identify it as a table. If
                                the text were reflowed, or changed from a fixed to a variable font,
                                or increased in size until lines no longer fit on the page, similar
                                issues would arise in the visual presentation.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources/>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="H51"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Examine the document for visually formatted tables.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Check whether the tables are created using white space characters
                                    to layout the tabular data.</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>If step #2 is true, then this failure condition applies and the
                                    content fails these Success Criteria.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
