<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="F36">
   <short-name>Failure of Success Criterion 3.2.2 due to automatically submitting a form and
                    presenting new content without prior warning when the last field in the form is
                    given a value</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>HTML and XHTML</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="consistent-behavior-unpredictable-change" relationship="failure"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>Forms are frequently designed so that they submit automatically when the user
                        has filled in all the fields, or when focus leaves the last field. There are
                        two problems with this approach. First is that a disabled user who needs
                        more context may move focus away from the field to the directions on how to
                        fill in the form, or to other text, accidentally submitting the form. The
                        other is that, with some form elements, the value of the field changes as
                        each item is navigated with the keyboard, again accidentally submitting the
                        form. It is better to rely on the standard form behavior of the submit
                        button and enter key. </p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group role="failure">
         <head/>
         <description>
            <p> This failure example submits a form when the user leaves the last
                                field of a three-field telephone number form. The form will submit
                                if the user leaves the field after editing it, even navigating
                                backwards in the tab order. Developers should not use this method to
                                submit a form, and should instead use a submit button, or rely on
                                the form's default behavior of submitting when the user hits enter
                                in a text field. </p>
         </description>
         <code><![CDATA[ 
<form method="get" id="form1">
  <input type="text" name="text1" size="3" maxlength="3"> - 
  <input type="text" name="text2" size="3" maxlength="3"> - 
  <input type="text" name="text3" size="4" maxlength="4" onchange="form1.submit();">
</form> ]]></code>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group role="failure">
         <head/>
         <description>
            <p>This is a  example that submits a form when the user
                                selects an option from the menu when there is no warning of this behavior in advance. The form will submit as soon as an item from the menu is selected. A user using a keyboard will not be able to navigate past the first item in the menu. Blind users and users with hand tremors can easily make a mistake on which item on the dropdown menu to choose and they are taken to the wrong destination before they can correct it.  </p>
         </description>
         <code><![CDATA[ 
<form method="get" id="form2">
 <input type="text" name="text1">
  <select name="select1" onchange="form2.submit();">
    <option>one</option>
    <option>two</option>
    <option>three</option>
    <option>four</option>
  </select>
</form>]]></code>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also/>
   </resources>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p> Enter data in all fields on page starting at top. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Enter data in last field and exit from it (tab out of it).</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Check whether leaving the last field causes change of
                                context.</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p> If step #3 is true, then this failure condition applies and content
                                    fails the Success Criterion. </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
