<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="F38">
   <short-name>Failure of Success Criterion 1.1.1 due to not marking up decorative images in HTML in a way that allows assistive technology to ignore them</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>HTML and XHTML</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="text-equiv-all" relationship="failure"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p> This describes a failure condition for text alternatives for images that
                        should be ignored by AT. If there is no alt attribute at all assistive
                        technologies are not able to ignore the non-text content. The alt attribute
                        must be provided and have a null value (i.e., <code><![CDATA[alt=""]]></code> ) to avoid a failure of this Success Criterion. </p>
      <p>This describes a failure condition for text alternatives for images that should be ignored by assistive technology (AT). If an image has the attribute <code><![CDATA[role="presentation"]]></code>, it will be ignored by AT. However, if it does not have <code><![CDATA[role="presentation"]]></code>, and if there is no <att>alt</att> attribute at all assistive technologies are not able to ignore the image. For decorative images which need to be ignored by AT, either <code><![CDATA[role="presentation"]]></code> must be used or the alt attribute must be provided and have a null value (i.e., <code><![CDATA[alt=""]]></code>) to avoid a failure of this Success Criterion.</p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>Decorative images that have no <att>alt</att>
                                attribute <phrase>and no <att>role</att> attribute</phrase>
            </p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
   </examples>
   <resources/>
   <related-techniques/>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <p>For any <el>img</el> element that is used for purely decorative content:</p>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Check whether the element has no <att>role</att> attribute or has a <att>role</att> attribute value that is not <attval>presentation</attval>.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Check whether the element has no <att>alt</att> attribute or has an <att>alt</att> attribute with a value that is not null.</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>If step #1 is true and if step #2 is true, this failure condition applies and content fails the Success Criterion.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
