<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="F39">
   <short-name>Failure of Success Criterion 1.1.1 due to providing a text alternative that is not null (e.g., alt="spacer" or alt="image") for images that should be ignored by assistive technology</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p> Applies to HTML and XHTML.</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="text-equiv-all" relationship="failure"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>This technique describes a failure condition for images that should
            be ignored by assistive technologies. A text alternative for an image
            should convey the meaning of the image. When an image is used for decoration,
            spacing or other purpose that is not part of the meaningful content
            in the page then the image has no meaning and should be ignored by
            assistive technologies. </p>
      <p>Providing a null text alternative (i.e., <code><![CDATA[alt=""]]></code> )
            will allow assistive technology to ignore the image and avoid a failure
            of this Success Criterion. </p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group role="failure">
         <head>Decorative images that have no <att>alt</att> attribute</head>
         <description>
            <p>An image is used to create a blank space between content, where the
                spacing itself is not meaningful to the content. The image has an alt
                text value of "spacer". This image fails the Success Criterion
                because the text alternative does not serve an equivalent purpose.
                The image is meant to be ignored but its alternative text "spacer" is
                announced by screen readers and displayed in some alternate color schemes. </p>
            <codeblock xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[<div>Tree type: <img src="spacer.gif" width="100" height="1" alt="spacer"/>Cedrus deodara</div>
]]></codeblock>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources/>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="H37"/>
      <relatedtech idref="C9"/>
      <relatedtech idref="F38"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p> Identify any img elements that are used for decoration, spacing
              or other purpose that is not part of the meaningful content in the
              page </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Check that the alt attribute for these elements is null. </p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p> If step #2 is false, this failure condition applies and the content
              fails the Success Criterion. </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
