<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="F4">
   <short-name>Failure of Success Criterion 2.2.2 due to using text-decoration:blink without a
                    mechanism to stop it in less than five seconds</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>Cascading Style Sheets.</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="time-limits-pause" relationship="failure"/>
   </applies-to>
   <ua-issues>
      <ua-issue name="IE" version="*">
         <p>The <code><![CDATA[blink]]></code> value of the <code><![CDATA[text-decoration]]></code> property
                            is not supported by Internet Explorer. It is supported in
                            Netscape/Mozilla family browsers. Not tested in others (e.g., Safari,
                            Opera).</p>
      </ua-issue>
   </ua-issues>
   <description>
      <p>CSS defines the <code><![CDATA[blink]]></code> value for the <code><![CDATA[text-decoration]]></code>
                        property. When used, it causes any text in elements with this property to
                        blink at a predetermined rate. This cannot be interrupted by the user, nor
                        can it be disabled as a user agent preference. The blinking continues as
                        long as the page is displayed. Therefore, content that uses
                            <code><![CDATA[text-decoration:blink]]></code> fails the Success Criterion because
                        blinking can continue for more than three seconds.</p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group role="failure">
         <description>
            <p>A product list page uses the <code><![CDATA[text-decoration:blink]]></code> style
                                on an element to draw attention to sale prices. This fails the
                                Success Criterion because users cannot control the blink.</p>
         </description>
         <code><![CDATA[
<p>My Great Product <span style="text-decoration:blink">Sale! $44,995!</span></p>
]]></code>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p> 
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.w3.org/TR/CSS2/text.html#propdef-text-decoration">CSS 2 text-decoration property</loc> 
               </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </see-also>
   </resources>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="SCR22"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Examine inline styles, internal stylesheets, and external
                                    stylesheets for the <code><![CDATA[text-decoration]]></code> property with a
                                    value of "blink".</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>If the property is used, determine if the ID, class, or element
                                    identified by selectors on which this property is defined are
                                    used in the document.</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>If step #1 and step #2 are true, the content fails the success
                                criterion.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
