<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="F41">
   <short-name>Failure of Success Criterion 2.2.1, 2.2.4, and 3.2.5 due to using meta refresh to reload the page</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>HTML and XHTML</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="time-limits-required-behaviors" relationship="failure"/>
      <success-criterion idref="time-limits-postponed" relationship="failure"/>
      <!-- Bruces raises concern this mapping could mislead people, should expand technique to clarify -->
      <success-criterion idref="consistent-behavior-no-extreme-changes-context"
                         relationship="failure"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p> 
         <code><![CDATA[meta]]></code>
						   <code><![CDATA[http-equiv]]></code> of refresh is often used to periodically refresh
                        pages or to redirect users to another page. If the time interval is too
                        short, and there is no way to turn auto-refresh off, people who are blind will not have enough time to make their screen
                        readers read the page before the page refreshes unexpectedly and causes the
                        screen reader to begin reading at the top. Sighted users may also be
                        disoriented by the unexpected refresh.</p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group role="failure">
         <description>
            <p> This is a deprecated example that changes the user's page at regular
                                intervals. Content developers should not use this technique to
                                simulate "push" technology. Developers cannot predict how much time
                                a user will require to read a page; premature refresh can disorient
                                users. Content developers should avoid periodic refresh and allow
                                users to choose when they want the latest information. (The number
                                in the <code><![CDATA[content]]></code> attribute is the refresh interval in
                                seconds.)</p>
         </description>
         <code><![CDATA[
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" lang="en">
  <head>     
    <title>HTML Techniques for WCAG 2.0</title>     
    <meta http-equiv="refresh" content="60" />   
  </head>   
  <body>
    ...     
  </body> 
</html>
]]></code>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <related-techniques />
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p> Find <code><![CDATA[meta]]></code> elements in the document. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>For each <code><![CDATA[meta]]></code> element, check if it contains
               the <code><![CDATA[http-equiv]]></code> attribute with value "refresh" (case-insensitive) and
               the <code><![CDATA[content]]></code> attribute with a number (representing seconds) equals to or greater than 0 and without "; url=" (case-insensitive). </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>check to see if there is a mechanism to turn off the refresh. </p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>If step 2 is true and step 3 is false then this failure condition applies and content
                                    fails these Success Criteria. </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
