<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="F43">
   <short-name>Failure of Success Criterion 1.3.1 due to using structural markup in a way that does
                    not represent relationships in the content</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>HTML and XHTML</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="content-structure-separation-programmatic"
                         relationship="failure"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to describe a failure that occurs when
                        structural markup is used to achieve a presentational effect, but indicates
                        relationships that do not exist in the content. This is disorienting to
                        users who are depending on those relationships to navigate the content or to
                        understand the relationship of one piece of the content to another. Note
                        that the use of HTML tables for layout is not an example of this failure as
                        long as the layout table does not include improper structural markup such as
                            <code><![CDATA[<th>]]></code> or <code><![CDATA[<caption>]]></code>
                        elements.</p>
      <note>
         <p>Though an element's semantic meaning is generally exposed to AT, the WAI-ARIA presentation role can be used to suppress the native semantics of an element so that they are not mapped to the accessibility API. Setting an element's <att>role</att> to presentation may avoid this failure by hiding that element's semantics from the user.</p>
      </note>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group role="failure">
         <head>A heading used only for visual effect</head>
         <description>
            <p>In this example, a heading element is used to display an address in a
                                large, bold font. The address does not identify a new section of the
                                document, however, so it should not be marked as a heading.</p>
         </description>
         <code role="html401"><![CDATA[
<p>Interested in learning more? Write to us at</p> 
<h4>3333 Third Avenue, Suite 300 · New York City</h4>

<p>And we'll send you the complete informational packet absolutely Free!</p>
]]></code>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group role="failure">
         <head>Using heading elements for presentational effect</head>
         <description>
            <p>In this example, heading markup is used in two different ways: to
                                convey document structure and to create visual effects. The
                                <code><![CDATA[h1]]></code> and <code><![CDATA[h2]]></code> elements are used appropriately
                                to mark the beginning of the document as a whole and the beginning
                                of the abstract. However, the <code><![CDATA[h3]]></code> and <code><![CDATA[h4]]></code>
                                elements between the title and the abstract are used only for visual
                                effect — to control the fonts used to display the authors' names and
                                the date.</p>
         </description>
         <code role="html401"><![CDATA[
<h1>Study on the Use of Heading  Elements in Web Pages</h1>
<h3>Joe Jones and Mary Smith<h3>
<h4>March 14, 2006</h4>
<h2>Abstract</h2>
<p>A study was conducted in early 2006 ...
</p>
]]></code>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group role="failure">
         <head>Using <el>blockquote</el> elements to provide additional
                            indentation</head>
         <description>
            <p>The following example uses <code><![CDATA[blockquote]]></code> for text that is
                                not a quotation to give it prominence by indenting it when displayed
                                in graphical browsers.</p>
         </description>
         <code role="html401"><![CDATA[
<p>After extensive study of the company Web site, the task force 
identified the following common problem.</p>

<blockquote>
<p>The use of markup for presentational effects made Web 
pages confusing to screen reader users.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The committee lists particular examples of the problems 
introduced by this practice below.</p>
]]></code>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group role="failure">
         <head>Using the <code><![CDATA[fieldset]]></code> and <code><![CDATA[legend]]></code> elements to
                            give a border to text</head>
         <code role="html401"><![CDATA[
<fieldset>
<legend>Bargain Corner</legend>
<p>Buy today, and save 20%</p>
</fieldset>
]]></code>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources/>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="F46"/>
      <relatedtech idref="G115"/>
      <relatedtech idref="H39"/>
      <relatedtech idref="H42"/>
      <relatedtech idref="H73"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Check that the element's semantic meaning is exposed to assistive technology and appropriate for the content of the element.</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>If check #1 is false then this failure condition applies.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
