<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="F49">
   <short-name>
          Failure of Success Criterion 1.3.2 due to using an HTML layout table that does not make sense when linearized  </short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>HTML and XHTML</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="content-structure-separation-sequence" relationship="failure"/>
   </applies-to>
   <ua-issues>
      <ua-issue name="" version="">
         <p>Early screen readers literally read Web content from the screen, which
                            lead to problems when tables were used for layout where one table cell
                            was meant to be read in its entirety before reading the next table cell.
                            Today's screen readers work with the underlying markup, which means that
                            they do read a table cell in its entirety before moving on to the next
                            cell, but layout tables may still inadvertently introduce problems with
                            the natural reading order of the content.</p>
      </ua-issue>
   </ua-issues>
   <description>
      <p>Although WCAG 2 does not prohibit the use of layout tables, CSS-based layouts are recommended in order to retain the defined semantic meaning of the HTML <el>table</el> elements and to conform to the coding practice of separating presentation from content. If a layout table is used, however, it is important that the content make sense when linearized.
          </p>
      <p>This failure occurs when a meaningful sequence of content conveyed through
                        presentation is lost because HTML tables used to control the visual
                        placement of the content do not “linearize" correctly. Tables present
                        content in two visual dimensions, horizontal and vertical. However, screen
                        readers present this two-dimensional content in linear order of the content
                        in the source, beginning with the first cell in the first row and ending
                        with the last cell in the last row. The screen reader reads the table from
                        top to bottom, reading the entire contents of each row before moving to the
                        next row. The complete content of each cell in each row is spoken—including
                        the complete content of any table nested within a cell. This is called
                        linearization.</p>
      <p>Suppose that a Web page is laid out using a table with 9 columns and 22 rows.
                        The screen reader speaks the content of the cell at Column 1, Row 1 followed
                        by the cells in columns 2, 3, 4 and so on to column 9. However, if any cell
                        contains a nested table, the screen reader will read the entire nested table
                        before it reads the next cell in the original (outer) table. For example, if
                        the cell at column 3, row 6 contains a table with 6 columns and 5 rows, all
                        of those cells will be read before Column 4, Row 6 of the original (outer)
                        table. As a result, the meaningful sequence conveyed through visual
                        presentation may not be perceivable when the content is spoken by a screen
                        reader.</p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group role="failure">
         <head>A layout table that does not linearize correctly</head>
         <description>
            <p>An advertisement makes clever use of visual positioning, but changes
                                meaning when linearized.</p>
         </description>
         <code role="html401"><![CDATA[
<table>
<tr>
  <td ><img src="logo.gif" alt="XYZ mountaineering"></td>
  <td rowspan="2" valign="bottom">top!</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td>XYZ gets you to the</td>
</tr>
</table>]]></code>
         <description>
            <p>The reading order from this example would be: </p>
            <ulist>
               <item>
                  <p>XYZ mountaineering top! </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>XYZ gets you to the</p>
               </item>
            </ulist>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group role="failure">
         <head>A layout table that separates a meaningful sequence when linearized</head>
         <description>
            <p>A Web page from a museum exhibition positions a navigation bar
                                containing a long list of links on the left side of the page. To the
                                right of the navigation bar is an image of one of the pictures from
                                the exhibition. To the right of the image is the kind of "placard"
                                text you'd see on the wall next to the object if you were at the
                                museum. Below that text is a heading that says "Description," and
                                below that heading is a description of the image. The image, placard
                                text, Description heading, and text of the description form a
                                meaningful sequence.</p>
            <p>A layout table is used to position the elements of the page. The
                                links in the navigation bar are split into different cells in the
                                leftmost column.</p>
         </description>
         <code role="html401"><![CDATA[
<table>
<tr>
	<td><a href="#">Link 1</a></td>
	<td rowspan="20"><img src="img.png" alt="Museum Picture"></td>
	<td rowspan="6"><img src="placard.png" alt="Placard text"></td> 
</tr> 
<tr>
	<td><a href="#">Link 2</a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td><a href="#">Link 3</a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td><a href="#">Link 4</a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td><a href="#">Link 5</a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td><a href="#">Link 6</a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td><a href="#">Link 7</a></td>
	<td rowspan="2"><h2>Image Heading</h2></td> 
</tr> 
<tr>
	<td><a href="#">Link 8</a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
	<td><a href="#">Link 9</a></td>
	<td rowspan="12">Description of the image</td> 
</tr> 
<tr>
	<td><a href="#">Link 10</a></td>
</tr>
 ...
<tr>
	<td><a href="#">Link 20</a></td>
</tr>
</table>
]]></code>
         <description>
            <p>The reading order from this example would be: </p>
            <ulist>
               <item>
                  <p>Link 1</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>Image</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>Placard Text</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>Link 2</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>Link 3</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>Link 4</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>Link 5</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>Link 6</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>Link 7</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>Image Heading</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>Link 8</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>Link 9</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>Link 10</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>...</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>Link 20</p>
               </item>
            </ulist>
            <p>Because the navigation bar links are interleaved with the content
                                describing the image, screen readers cannot present the content in a
                                meaningful sequence corresponding to the sequence presented
                                visually.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources/>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="C6"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Linearize the content in either of the following ways: </p>
               <ulist>
                  <item>
                     <p>Present the content in source code order</p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>Remove the table markup from around the content</p>
                  </item>
               </ulist>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Check that the linear reading order matches any meaningful
                                    sequence conveyed through presentation.</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>If check #2 is false, then this failure condition applies and the
                                    content fails this Success Criterion.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
