<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="F62">
   <short-name>Failure of Success Criterion 1.3.1 and 4.1.1 due to insufficient information in DOM to determine
                    specific relationships in XML</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p> Applies to the Document Object Model (DOM) for XML. </p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="content-structure-separation-programmatic"
                         relationship="failure"/>
      <success-criterion idref="ensure-compat-parses" relationship="failure"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <ednote id="F62_note">
         <edtext>
            <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                 href="https://www.w3.org/2006/02/lc-comments-tracker/35422/NOTE-WCAG20-TECHS-20130905/2861">Comment LC-2861</loc> pointed out the two failure conditions are pretty separate. We might want to split this technique. However, <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                 href="https://www.w3.org/2006/02/lc-comments-tracker/35422/NOTE-WCAG20-TECHS-20130905/2860">Comment LC-2860</loc> resulted in deleting the second failure condition, so 2861 may need revisiting.</edtext>
      </ednote>
      <p> The objective of this technique is to ensure that Web pages can be
                        interpreted consistently by user agents, including assistive technology. If
                        specific relationships in a Web page are ambiguous, different user agents,
                        including assistive technologies, could present different information to
                        their users. Users of assistive technology, for example, may have different
                        information presented to them than users of other mainstream user agents.
                        Some elements and attributes in markup languages are required to have unique
                        values, and if this requirement is not honored, the result can be irregular
                        or not uniquely resolvable content. </p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group role="failure">
         <description>
            <ulist>
               <item>
                  <p> An id attribute value that is not unique. </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p> An SVG document uses <code><![CDATA[id]]></code> attributes on
                                            <code><![CDATA[title]]></code> elements (for alternative text) in
                                        order to reuse in other locations in the document. However,
                                        one of the <code><![CDATA[title]]></code> elements has an id that is
                                        also used elsewhere in the document, so the document is
                                        ambiguous. </p>
               </item>
            </ulist>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also/>
   </resources>
   <related-techniques/>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p> Check that elements or attributes that refer to unique
                                    identifiers inside the same document have a corresponding id
                                    value. </p>
            </item>
         </olist>
         <p> Note that for XML document types defined by a DTD, this refers to
                            attributes of type ID, IDREF or IDREFS. For XML document types defined
                            by a W3C XML Schema, this refers to elements or attributes of type ID,
                            IDREF or IDREFS. (For compatibility, the types ID, IDREF and IDREFS
                            should only be used on attributes, but using them for elements is
                            possible, according to <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                 href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xmlschema-2/#terminology">XML Schema Part
                                2: Datatypes Second Edition</loc>.) For other schema languages,
                            check the corresponding mechanisms for specifying IDs and references to
                            IDs. </p>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>If #1 is false, then this failure condition applies and
                                    the content fails Success Criterion 4.1.1. </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
