<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="F65">
   <short-name>Failure of Success Criterion 1.1.1 due to omitting the alt attribute or text alternative on img elements, area elements, and input elements of type "image"</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>HTML and XHTML</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="text-equiv-all" relationship="failure"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>This describes a failure condition for text alternatives on images. If there is no source of text to provide an alternative for the image then assistive technologies are not able to identify the image or to convey its purpose to the user. The <att>alt</att> attribute continues to be the preferred way to provide alternative text for images. Appropriate WAI-ARIA attributes may be used to provide alternative text, as long as they are accessibility supported.  For more information about accessibility support, see <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
              href="http://www.w3.org/WAI/GL/2014/WD-UNDERSTANDING-WCAG20-20140107/appendixB.html">Documenting Accessibility Support</loc>. The Accessible Rich Internet Applications (WAI-ARIA) 1.0 Specification describes the <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
              href="http://www.w3.org/TR/wai-aria/roles#textalternativecomputation"> Text Alternative Computation</loc>, for computing the text alternative from the HTML and WAI-ARIA attributes of an element.</p>
      <p>
Some Assistive Technologies attempt to compensate for the missing text alternatives by reading the file name of the image. But it is insufficient to rely simply on the file name for many reasons. For example, file names may not be descriptive (e.g., images/nav01.gif), and technology specifications do not require descriptive file names. And some Assistive Technologies do not read the file name if there is no text alternative provided via HTML attributes.
</p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group role="failure">
         <head>Missing text alternative</head>
         <description>
            <p>In the code example below, the person using a screen reader would not know the purpose of the image.</p>
         </description>
         <code role="html401"><![CDATA[
<img src="../images/animal.jpg" />
]]></code>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.w3.org/TR/html-aapi/#accessible-name-and-description-calculation"> HTML to Platform Accessibility APIs Implementation Guide: Accessible Name and Description Calculation</loc>
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.w3.org/TR/wai-aria/roles#textalternativecomputation"> Accessible Rich Internet Applications (WAI-ARIA) 1.0, Section 5.2.7.3. Text Alternative Computation</loc>
               </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </see-also>
   </resources>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="H67"/>
      <relatedtech idref="H37"/>
      <relatedtech idref="ARIA10"/>
      <!-- Using aria-labelledby to provide a text alternative for non-text content-->
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <p>Identify <el>img</el>, <el>area</el> and <el>input</el> elements of type <attval>image</attval>. For each of these elements:</p>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <phrase>Check if the <att>alt</att> attribute is present. 
									</phrase>
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <phrase>Check if <att>aria-labelledby</att> attribute is present AND references one or more id elements in the page AND check if <att>aria-labelledby</att> is <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                          href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2008/REC-WCAG20-20081211/#accessibility-supporteddef"> accessibility supported</loc>.</phrase>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <phrase>Check if the <att>aria-label</att> attribute is present AND check if <att>aria-label</att> is <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                          href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2008/REC-WCAG20-20081211/#accessibility-supporteddef">accessibility supported</loc>.</phrase>
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <phrase>Check if the <att>title</att> attribute is present AND check if <att>title</att> is <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                          href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2008/REC-WCAG20-20081211/#accessibility-supporteddef"> accessibility supported</loc>.</phrase>
               </p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>If all of #1, #2, #3 and #4 are false then this failure condition applies.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
