<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="F7">
   <short-name>Failure of Success Criterion 2.2.2 due to an object or applet, such as Java or Flash,
                    that has blinking content without a mechanism to pause the content that blinks
                    for more than five seconds</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>Technologies that support blinking content within an object, applet, or a
                        plug-in.</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="time-limits-pause" relationship="failure"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>When content that is rendered by a plug-in or contained in an applet blinks,
                        there may be no way for the user agent to pause the blinking. If neither the
                        plug-in, applet, nor the content itself provides a mechanism to pause the
                        content, the user may not have sufficient time to read the content between
                        blinks or it may be so distracting that the user will not be able to read
                        other content on the page.</p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>An applet displays an advertisement on a news site. The applet blinks
                                key words in the advertisement in order to call the user's attention
                                to it. The blinking cannot be paused through any user agent settings
                                and the applet does not provide a mechanism to stop it.</p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
   </examples>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="SCR22"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <p>For each page that has blinking content in a plugin or applet:</p>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Determine if the content continues to blink for longer than 5
                                    seconds.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Determine if there is a means to pause the blinking content.</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>If step #1 is true and step #2 is false, the content fails the success
                                    criterion.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
