<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="F70">
   <short-name>Failure of Success Criterion 4.1.1 due to incorrect use of start and end tags or attribute markup</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>Markup languages: HTML, XHTML, and other SGML or XML-based technologies.</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="ensure-compat-parses" relationship="failure"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this failure is to identify examples of markup errors in element tags that could cause assistive technology to be unable to generate a satisfactory model of the page. Different user agents may implement different heuristics to recover from errors, resulting in inconsistent presentations of the page between user agents.</p>
      <p>Some common types of problems with start and end tags that lead to this failure condition (though this is not an exhaustive list):</p>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>Opening and closing tags that are missing the opening &lt; and closing &gt; brackets.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>Closing tag missing the initial / to indicate it is a closing tag.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>Attribute values that have an opening quote but not a closing quote. Attribute values must be either fully quoted or, in some markup languages, may be unquoted.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>Lack of whitespace between attributes.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>Unquoted attribute values that have whitespace in the value.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>Failure to provide a closing element tag for elements that do not accept empty-element syntax.</p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group role="failure">
         <head>Missing angle brackets in XHTML</head>
         <description>
            <p>The following code fails because the opening tag is missing an angle bracket, and the intended boundary of the tag is unclear.</p>
         </description>
         <code role="xhtml"><![CDATA[
<p This is a paragraph</p>
]]></code>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group role="failure">
         <head>Missing slash on closing tag in XHTML</head>
         <description>
            <p>The following code fails because the closing tag is missing the slash, making it look like it is in fact another opening tag.</p>
         </description>
         <code role="xhtml"><![CDATA[
<p>This is a paragraph<p>
]]></code>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group role="failure">
         <head>Unbalanced attribute quoting</head>
         <description>
            <p>The following code fails because the attribute value is missing the closing quote, which makes the boundary of the attribute-value pair unclear.</p>
         </description>
         <code role="xhtml"><![CDATA[
<input title="name type="text">
]]></code>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group role="failure">
         <head>Lack of whitespace between attributes</head>
         <description>
            <p>The following code fails because the there is not whitespace between attributes, which makes the boundary between attribute-value pairs unclear.</p>
         </description>
         <code role="xhtml"><![CDATA[
<input title="name"type="text">
]]></code>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group role="failure">
         <head>Unquoted attribute with whitespace value</head>
         <description>
            <p>The following code fails because an attribute value is not quoted and contains whitespace, which makes the boundary of the attribute-value pair unclear.</p>
         </description>
         <code role="xhtml"><![CDATA[
<input title=Enter name here type=text>
]]></code>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group role="failure">
         <head>Missing end tags in XHTML</head>
         <description>
            <p>The following code fails because the closing tag of the first paragraph is missing, making it unclear whether the second paragraph is a child or sibling of the first.</p>
         </description>
         <code role="xhtml"><![CDATA[
<p>This is a paragraph
<p>This is another paragraph</p>
]]></code>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <related-techniques/>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Check the source code of pages implemented in markup languages.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Check whether any opening tags, closing tags or attributes are malformed.</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>If check #2 is true, then the failure condition applies and the content does not meet this Success Criterion.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
