<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="F76">
   <short-name>Failure of Success Criterion 3.2.2 due to not advising, or providing a link to the advice prior to the control that causes a change in context or not providing advice that is programatically associated with the control.</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>Applies to all technologies.</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="consistent-behavior-unpredictable-change" relationship="failure"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>Without being advised prior to encountering a control, unexpected change of context due to change of user interface setting can sometimes confuse users.  Users must receive advice of the behavior prior to such an encounter.  Providing the advice in a way in which the user may not have the opportunity to review before encountering the change may leave opportunity for confusion.</p>
      <p>Failure examples:</p>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>Not providing instruction on the Web page preceding the user interface element that causes change of context by change of setting.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>Not providing advise, or not providing a link to advice (which could be part of an instruction manual) prior to encountering the control, or not providing a programatic association to the advice on the control (i.e., using <att>aria-describedby</att>) represent failures of 3.2.2. In the case of a multi-step process, it would be a failure not to provide instruction at a part of the process prior to the step where they may encounter such change of context.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>Not providing mandatory instruction about the change of context in the case of intranet Web application.</p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
   </description>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <p>For every occurrence of a change of context due to change of user interface setting</p>
		 <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Is there advise about the behavior  prior encountering of the change of context</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Is there a link to advice(as part of an instruction manual, or direct advice) prior to encountering of the change of context</p>
            </item>
			<item>
+			   <p>Are instructions programmatically associated with the control (i.e., using <att>aria-describedby</att>)</p>
+			</item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>If #1 is true and #2 or #3 are false, then this failure condition applies and content fails the Success Criterion.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
