<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="F76">
   <short-name>Failure of Success Criterion 3.2.2 due to providing instruction material about the change of context by change of setting in a user interface element at a location that users may bypass</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>Applies to all technologies.</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="consistent-behavior-unpredictable-change" relationship="failure"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>Without prior instruction, unexpected change of context due to change of user interface setting can sometimes confuse users.  Users must receive instruction prior to such encounter.  Providing the instruction in a way in which the user may not have the opportunity to review may leave opportunity for confusion.</p>
      <p>Failure examples:</p>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>Not providing instruction on the Web page preceding the user interface element that causes change of context by change of setting.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>Not providing instruction at a part of the process prior to the step where they may encounter such change of context, in case of a multi-step process in which users must go through particular steps to reach the user interface element where change of setting would cause a change of context.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>Not providing mandatory instruction about the change of context in the case of intranet Web application.</p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
   </description>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Find occurrence of change of context due to change of user interface setting</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Find instructional material that all users must review prior encountering of the change of context.</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>If #1 is true and #2 is false, then this failure condition applies and content fails the Success Criterion.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
