<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="F92">
   <short-name>Failure of Success Criterion 1.3.1 due to the use of role presentation on content which conveys semantic information</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>HTML and XHTML</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="content-structure-separation-programmatic"
                         relationship="failure"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>This failure occurs when a role of presentation is applied to an element whose purpose is to convey information or relationships in the content. Elements such as <el>table</el>, can convey information about the content contained in them via their semantic markup. The WAI-ARIA role of <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
              href="http://www.w3.org/TR/wai-aria/roles#presentation">
            <attval>presentation</attval>
         </loc> on the other hand, is intended to suppress semantic information of content from the accessibility API and prevent user agents from conveying that information to the user. Use of the <attval>presentation</attval> role for content which should convey semantic information may prevent the user from understanding that content.
</p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group role="failure">
         <head/>
         <description>
            <p>In this example, tabular data is marked up with <code><![CDATA[role=presentation]]></code>. Though design layout tables can be marked up in such a way, data tables need to retain their semantic information and should therefore not be marked up with <code><![CDATA[role=presentation]]></code>.</p>
            <p>Example Code:</p>
            <codeblock xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[
<table role="presentation">
   <caption>Fruits and their colors</caption>
   <tr>
     <th>Name</th>
     <th>Color</th>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td scope="row">banana</td>
    <td>yellow</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td scope="row">orange</td>
    <td>orange</td>
   </tr>
  </table>
                            ]]></codeblock>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.w3.org/TR/wai-aria/roles#presentation">The Roles Model</loc>
               </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </see-also>
   </resources>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Check if an element which conveys information, structure, or relationships through its semantic markup
</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Element has the attribute <code><![CDATA[role="presentation"]]></code>.
</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>If check #2 is true, then this failure condition applies and the content fails the Success Criterion.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
