<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="FLASH8">
   <short-name>Adding a group name to the accessible name of a form control</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p use-id="flash.applicability.general"/>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="content-structure-separation-programmatic"
                         relationship="sufficient"/>
      <success-criterion idref="minimize-error-cues" relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <ua-issues>
      <ua-issue use-id="flash.ua-issue.general"/>
   </ua-issues>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to provide a semantic grouping for   related form controls. This allows users to understand the relationship   of the controls and interact with the form more quickly and   effectively. </p>
      <p>In Flash, when related form controls are grouped, this grouping   can be indicated by adding the group's name to each form control's   accessible name. </p>
      <p>Grouping controls is most important for related radio buttons and   checkboxes. A set of radio buttons or checkboxes is related when they   all submit values for a single named field. They work in the same way as   selection lists, allowing the user to choose from a set of options,   except selection lists are single controls while radio buttons and   checkboxes are multiple controls. Because they are multiple controls, it   is particularly important that they be grouped semantically so they can   be more easily treated as a single control. Often, user agents will   present the value of the legend before the label of each control, to   remind users that they are part of the same group. </p>
      <p>It can also be useful to group other sets of controls that are   not as tightly related as sets of radio buttons and checkboxes. For   instance, several fields that collect a user's address might be grouped   together with a legend of "Address". </p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Adding a group name to the accessible name of radio buttons</head>
         <description>
            <p>This example shows how the group name for radio buttons in a group   can be made accessible by adding it to each button's accessible name: </p>
            <olist>
               <item>
                  <p> Add radio button components to the stage: </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p> Enter each button's label using its <prop>label</prop> property </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p> Add the visual group label to the left or above the buttons   added in step 1 </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p> Select each radio button. In the Accessibility panel, add the   group name to the "Name" field; </p>
               </item>
            </olist>
            <p>Flash will concatenate the group name with each button's individual   name, such as "gender male". </p>
            <p>This approach is illustrated in the screenshot below: </p>
            <p>
								       <image>
                  <img xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       source="/WAI/WCAG20/Techniques/working-examples/FLASH8/groupname.png"
                       height="236"
                       width="584"/>
                  <alt>Using the Accessibility panel to add a group name to a form control</alt>
               </image>
							     </p>
            <note>
               <p>To make the radio buttons in this example accessible, the   following two lines need to be added to the movie's script: <code xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[import fl.accessibility.RadioButtonAccImpl;
RadioButtonAccImpl.enableAccessibility();]]></code>
								       </p>
            </note>
            <p>For an illustration of this approach, see the <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    href="radio_button_group_as3.html"
                    linktype="examples">working version of Adding a group name to the accessible name of radio buttons</loc>. The <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    href="radio_button_group_as3.fla"
                    linktype="examples">source of Adding a group name to the accessible name of radio buttons</loc> is available.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Programmatically adding a group name with the accessible name of radio buttons</head>
         <description>
            <p>The code example below shows a basic proof of concept of a class that   automatically places a set of form controls inside a fieldset like   rectangle, including a legend. For each added control an <obj>AccessibilityProperties</obj>   object is created, and its <prop>name</prop> property is set to a   combination of the legend text and the actual form control label. </p>
         </description>
         <code xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[
package wcagSamples {
  import flash.display. *;
  import flash.text. *;
  import fl.controls. *
  import flash.accessibility. *;
  import fl.accessibility. *;
  
  
  /**
  *  Basic example that demonstrates how to simulate a fieldset, as provided
  *  in HTML. The FieldSet class takes a group of controls and places them 
  *  inside a fieldset rectangle with the legend text at the top. For each form 
  *  control, the legend text is prepended to the control's accessible name
  *
  *  Note: This is only a proof of concept, not a fully functional class
  *
  *  @langversion 3.0
  *  @playerversion Flash 10
  *
  */
  public class FieldSet extends Sprite {
    private var legend: String;
    private var bBox: Shape;
    private var currentY: int = 20;
    
    public static var LABEL_OFFSET_X: int = 20;
    public static var CONTROL_OFFSET_X: int = 110;
    
    /**
    *  CONSTRUCTOR
    *  Legend specifies the FieldSet's legend text, items is an array 
    *  describing the controls to be added to the FieldSet
    */
    
    public function FieldSet(legend: String, items: Array) {
      // enable accessibility for components used in this example
      RadioButtonAccImpl.enableAccessibility();
      CheckBoxAccImpl.enableAccessibility();
      
      //create FieldSet rectangle and legend
      legend = legend;
      bBox = new Shape();
      bBox.graphics.lineStyle(1);
      bBox.graphics.drawRect(10, 10, 300, 250);
      bBox.graphics.beginFill(0x0000FF, 1);
      addChild(bBox);
      
      var fieldSetLegend: TextField = new TextField();
      fieldSetLegend.text = legend;
      fieldSetLegend.x = 20;
      fieldSetLegend.y = 3;
      fieldSetLegend.background = true;
      fieldSetLegend.backgroundColor = 0xFFFFFF;
      fieldSetLegend.border = true;
      fieldSetLegend.borderColor = 0x000000;
      fieldSetLegend.autoSize = TextFieldAutoSize.LEFT;
      addChild(fieldSetLegend);
      
      // add controls
      for (var i = 0; i < items.length; i++) {
        processItem(items[i]);
      }
    }
    
    /**
    * Adds the control to the Fieldset and sets its accessible name. A 
    * control is represented as an array, containing the following values:
    * [0] : A string describing the component type 
    *   (can be "TextInput", TextArea", Checkbox" or "RadioGroup").
    * [1] : The label used to identify the control
    * [2] : If [0] is "RadioGroup", then [2] needs to contain an array of the 
    *    labels for each individual radio button. if [0] is "CheckBox", then 
    *    [1] can either be empty or a question (e.g. "Do you smoke?"), and 
    *    [2] the CheckBox label (e.g. "Yes").
    *
    */
    function processItem(item: Array) {
      if (item.length < 2)
      return;
      currentY += 30;
      var newControl;
      //create visual label
      var lbl: Label;
      lbl = new Label();
      lbl.text = item[1] + ": ";
      lbl.x = FieldSet.LABEL_OFFSET_X;
      lbl.y = currentY;
      lbl.width = FieldSet.CONTROL_OFFSET_X;
      lbl.autoSize = TextFieldAutoSize.RIGHT;
      lbl.wordWrap = true;
      addChild(lbl);
      
      switch (item[0]) {
        case "TextInput":
        case "TextArea":
        newControl = item[0] == "TextInput"? new TextInput(): new TextArea();
        newControl.x = FieldSet.CONTROL_OFFSET_X;
        //concatenate accessible name, combining legend and label
        setAccName(newControl, legend + " " + item[1]);
        break;
        case "CheckBox":
        newControl = new CheckBox();
        newControl.label = item[2];
        newControl.x = FieldSet.CONTROL_OFFSET_X;
        setAccName(newControl, legend + " " + item[1] + " " + item[2]);
        break;
        case "RadioGroup":
        if (item[2] && item[2].length > 0) {
          var radioGroup: RadioButtonGroup = new RadioButtonGroup(item[0]);
          var newBtn: RadioButton;;
          for (var i = 0; i < item[2].length; i++) {
            newBtn = new RadioButton();
            // concatenate the legend, the group label, and the button label
            setAccName(newBtn, legend + " " + item[1] + " " + item[2][i]);
            newBtn.label = item[2][i];
            newBtn.group = radioGroup;
            newBtn.x = FieldSet.CONTROL_OFFSET_X;
            newBtn.y = currentY;
            addChild(newBtn);
            if (i < item[2].length - 1)
            currentY += 30;
          }
        }
        break;
      }
      
      if (newControl) {
        newControl.y = currentY;
        addChild(newControl);
      }
    }
    
    /**
    * Creates an AccessibilityProperties object for an object and sets its name property
    */
    public function setAccName(obj, accName) {
      var accProps: AccessibilityProperties = new AccessibilityProperties();
      accProps.name = accName;
      obj.accessibilityProperties = accProps;
    }
  }
}]]></code>
         <description>
            <p>This example class can be initialized as follows: </p>
         </description>
         <code xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[var myFieldSet = new FieldSet("Personal Details",  // the legend 
  [["TextInput", "Name"],                          // text field
  ["RadioGroup", "Gender", ["Male", "Female"]],    // radio button group
  ["CheckBox", "Do you smoke", "yes"],             // checkbox
  ["TextArea", "Comments"],                        // text area
]);
addChild(myFieldSet);
]]></code>
         <description>
            <p>For an illustration of this approach, see the <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    href="grouped_form_controls.html"
                    linktype="examples">working version of Programmatically adding a group name with the accessible name of radio buttons</loc>. The <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    href="grouped_form_controls.zip"
                    linktype="examples">source of Programmatically adding a group name with the accessible name of radio buttons</loc> is available.</p>
            <note>
               <p>Adobe Flex allows you to perform this type of behavior by   using the &lt;form&gt;, &lt;formitem&gt; and &lt;formheading&gt;   elements </p>
            </note>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="FLASH25"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <p>When a Flash Movie contains grouped form controls, confirm that   either : </p>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p> The group's name is included in the Accessibility panel's   "name" field for each control. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Each control has an <prop>AccessibilityProperties.name</prop> property,   which contains both the group's name and the control's label text </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p> One of the above is true </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
   <admin>
      <source>
						   <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
              href="http://trace.wisc.edu/wcag_wiki/index.php?title=Adding_a_group_name_to_the_accessible_name_of_a_form_control"/>
					</source>
   </admin>
</technique>
