<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="FLASH3">
   <short-name>Marking objects in Flash so that they can be ignored by AT</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p use-id="flash.applicability.general"/>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="text-equiv-all" relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <ua-issues>
      <ua-issue use-id="flash.ua-issue.general"/>
   </ua-issues>
   <description>
      <p>The purpose of this technique is to show how images can be marked so that they can be ignored by Assistive Technology. </p>
      <p>The Flash Player supports the ability for authors to control  which graphics appear to assistive technologies using the <prop>silent</prop>  property of the accessibility object, as indicated in the examples  below. </p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Hiding a graphic in the Flash Professional authoring tool</head>
         <description>
            <p>The Flash Professional authoring tool's Accessibility panel lets  authors provide accessibility information to assistive technology and  set accessibility options for individual Flash objects or entire Flash  applications. </p>
            <olist>
               <item>
                  <p> To apply changes to accessibility properties for a graphic, it must be saved as a symbol in the movie's library. <emph role="strong">Note:</emph> Flash does not support text alternatives for graphic symbols. Instead,  the graphic must be converted to or stored in a movie clip or button  symbol. </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p> Bring up the Accessibility panel by selecting "Window &gt;  Other Panels &gt; Accessibility" in the application menu, or through  the shortcut ALT + F11. </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p> Select the graphic object </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p> If the 'Make object accessible' checkbox in the Accessibility  control panel is checked, uncheck this option to remove the graphic  from the accessiblity information conveyed to assistive technologies. </p>
               </item>
            </olist>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Applying textual alternatives programmatically in ActionScript 2.0</head>
         <description>
            <p>To manage an object's text equivalents programmatically using  ActionScript, the <prop>_accProps</prop> property must be used. This references an  object containing accessibility related properties set for the object.  The code example below shows a simple example of how the <prop>_accProps</prop>  property is used to remove an object from the accessibility information  for the movie using ActionScript. </p>
         </description>
         <code xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[// 'decorative_mc' is an instance placed on the movie's main timeline
_root.decorative_mc._accProps = new Object();
_root.decorative_mc._accProps.silent = true; ]]></code>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://help.adobe.com/en_US/AS2LCR/Flash_10.0/help.html?content=00000619.html">Flash 10 Documention _accProps property</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.eclipse.org/actf/downloads/tools/aDesigner/">aDesigner</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </see-also>
   </resources>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="G94"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p> Publish the SWF file </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Open the SWF file in Internet Explorer 6 or higher (using  Flash Player 6 or higher), or Firefox 3 or higher (using Flash Player 9  or higher) </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Use a tool which is capable of showing an object's accessibility information, such as ACTF aDesigner 1.0 to open the Flash movie. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> In the GUI summary panel, loop over each object which is  contained by the Flash movie and ensure the object that was designed to  be hidden does not appear in the tool's display. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Authors may also test with a screen reader, by reading the  Flash content and listening to hear that object is not mentioned when  the page is read. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Non-text objects that are coded to be hidden from assistive technologies are not available to assistive technology. </p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <p>Check #6 is true. </p>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
   <admin>
      <source>
						   <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
              href="http://trace.wisc.edu/wcag_wiki/index.php?title=Marking_objects_in_Flash_so_that_they_can_be_ignored_by_AT"/>
					</source>
   </admin>
</technique>
