<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="FLASH32">
   <short-name>Using auto labeling to associate text labels with form controls</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p use-id="flash.applicability.general"/>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="text-equiv-all" relationship="sufficient"/>
      <success-criterion idref="content-structure-separation-programmatic"
                         relationship="sufficient"/>
      <success-criterion idref="minimize-error-cues" relationship="sufficient"/>
      <success-criterion idref="ensure-compat-rsv" relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <ua-issues>
      <ua-issue use-id="flash.ua-issue.general"/>
   </ua-issues>
   <description>
      <p>Except for the <obj>CheckBox</obj> and <obj>RadioButton</obj> component, the built in Flash
    				components are not automatically provided an associated label. For
    				these components, label text has to be placed adjacent to their control
    				manually, using the <obj>Label</obj> component. If the 'auto-label' feature is
    				enabled in the Accessibility panel, then the Flash Player will automatically
    				associate the label text for the <obj>TextInput</obj> and <obj>TextArea</obj> components.
    				This means that for these components, it is not necessary to duplicate
    				the label text for the control using the Accessibility panel. The auto
    				label feature is enabled by default. </p>
      <p>Additionally, the auto label feature will enable the Flash Player
    				to automatically add text contained by Button symbols as the symbol's
    				accessible name. This will only work if the Button symbol only consists
    				of one layer, containing the text label. </p>
      <note>
         <p>Since auto-labeling associates labels without human intervention
    				the accuracy of the association should be verified. For more predictable
    				results authors are encouraged to explicitly add labels to all controls. </p>
      </note>
      <p>To auto labeling, perform the following steps: </p>
      <olist>
         <item>
            <p> Ensure that the textual descriptions for each form control within
    				the flash application are placed adjacent to the control itself. Text
    				eligible to be used for auto-labeling must not be set to be hidden
    				from assistive technology. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Select the movie stage, and open the Accessibility panel. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> Ensure that the 'Auto Label' option is checked. This will automatically
    					associate labels with their TextInput and TextArea controls, and
    					add text inside custom button symbols as their accessible name. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> If the auto label behavior is inappropriate to your Flash content,
    						uncheck the 'Auto label' option, and ensure that each control receives
    						a meaningful 'name' value in the Accessibility panel. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> To disable auto labeling for a particular object but not the whole
    							movie, convert the text to the 'dynamic text' type using the 'Property
    							inspector'. Then select it, and uncheck its 'Make object accessible'
    							option in the Accessibility panel. </p>
         </item>
      </olist>
      <note>
         <p>As an alternative to using the Accessibility panel, the auto
    				label feature can also be turned off by setting the <prop>AccessibilityProperties.noAutoLabel</prop>
    				to <propval>true</propval> for the stage object. </p>
      </note>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Using the "Auto Label" option in the Accessibility panel</head>
         <description>
            <p>This example shows two TextInput components, a TextArea component
    						and a custom button symbol instance. For the TextInput components,
    						a separate label element has been placed to the left of the control.
    						For the TextArea component, the label has been placed above the control.
    						For the custom button, the label text is placed inside the button symbol.
    						Because the "Auto Label" option is enabled in the Accessibility
    						panel, all these controls will be provided an accessible name based
    						on their label. </p>
            <p>The screenshot below illustrates the example: <image>
                  <img xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       source="/WAI/WCAG20/Techniques/working-examples/FLASH32/using_auto_label.png"
                       height="300"
                       width="593"/>
                  <alt>Using the Auto Label feature in the Flash Authoring Environment</alt>
               </image>
							     </p>
            <p>The results of this technique can be viewed in the <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    href="using_auto_labeling_to_associate_label_text_with_controls_as3.html"
                    linktype="examples">working version of Using the "Auto Label" option in the Accessibility panel</loc>. The <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    href="using_auto_labeling_to_associate_label_text_with_controls_as3.fla"
                    linktype="examples">source of Using the "Auto Label" option in the Accessibility panel</loc> is available.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="FLASH25"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <p>If a Flash form contains TextInput or TextArea components, or custom
    					button symbols with text labels, confirm that: </p>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p> The Auto Label option is enabled in the movie's Accessibility
    					panel </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Use a screen reader or MSAA checker to ensure that the label text
    					is indeed exposed as the control's accessible name </p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p> #1 and #2 are true </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
   <admin>
      <source>
						   <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
              href="http://trace.wisc.edu/wcag_wiki/index.php?title=Using_auto_labeling_to_associate_text_labels_with_form_controls"/>
					</source>
   </admin>
</technique>
