<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE div1
  SYSTEM "../xmlspec.dtd">
<div1 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" role="extsrc" id="consistent-behavior">
   <head>3.2</head>
   <div2 id="consistent-behavior-intent" role="glintent">
      <head>Intent</head>
      <p>The intent of this Guideline is to help users with disabilities by presenting content in a predictable order from Web page to Web page and by making the behavior of functional and interactive components predictable. It is difficult for some users to form an overview of the Web page: screen readers present content as a one-dimensional stream of synthetic speech that makes it difficult to understand spatial relationships. Users with cognitive limitations may become confused if components appear in different places on different pages.</p>
      <p>For example, people who use screen magnifiers see only part of the screen at any point in time; a consistent layout makes it easier for them to find navigation bars and other components. Placing repeated components in the same relative order within a set of Web pages allows users with reading disabilities to focus on an area of the screen rather than spending additional time decoding the text of each link. Users with limited use of their hands can more easily determine how to complete their tasks using the fewest keystrokes.</p>
   </div2>
   <div2 id="consistent-behavior-advisory" role="gladvisory">
      <head>Advisory techniques for Guideline N.N</head>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>
              Positioning labels to maximize predictability of relationships
              
            </p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
   </div2>
   <xi:include href="consistent-behavior-receive-focus.xml"/>
   <xi:include href="consistent-behavior-unpredictable-change.xml"/>
   <xi:include href="consistent-behavior-consistent-locations.xml"/>
   <xi:include href="consistent-behavior-consistent-functionality.xml"/>
   <xi:include href="consistent-behavior-no-extreme-changes-context.xml"/>
</div1>
