<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE div2
  SYSTEM "../xmlspec.dtd">
<div2 role="extsrc" id="consistent-behavior-receive-focus">
   <head>3.2.1</head>
   <div3 role="intent">
      <head>Intent of this Success Criterion</head>
      <p>The intent of this Success Criterion is to ensure that functionality is predictable as visitors navigate their way through a document. Any component that is able to trigger an event when it receives focus must not change the context.          Examples of changing context when a component receives focus include, but are not limited to:
          </p>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>forms submitted automatically when a component receives focus;</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>new windows launched when a component receives focus;</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>focus is changed to another component when that component receives focus;</p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
      <p>Focus may be moved to a control either via the keyboard (<abbr expansion="for example">e.g.</abbr> tabbing to a control) or the mouse (<abbr expansion="for example">e.g.</abbr> clicking on a text field). Moving the mouse over a control does not move the focus unless scripting implements this behavior. Note that for some types of controls, clicking on a control may also activate the control (<abbr expansion="for example">e.g.</abbr> button), which may, in turn, initiate a change in context.
					</p>
      <note>
         <p>What is meant by "component" here is also sometimes called "user interface element" or "user interface component''.</p>
      </note>
      <div4 role="benefits">
         <head>Benefits of this Success Criterion</head>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>This Success Criterion helps people with visual disabilities, cognitive limitations, and motor impairments by reducing the chance that a change of context will occur unexpectedly.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </div4>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="examples">
      <head>Examples for this Success Criterion</head>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <emph role="bold">Example 1:  A dropdown menu</emph>
							     </p>
            <p>A dropdown menu on a page allows users to choose between jump destinations. If the person uses the keyboard to move down to a choice and activates it (with a spacebar or enter key) it will jump to a new page.  However, if the person moves down to a choice and either hits the escape or the tab key to move out of the pulldown menu – it does not jump to a new screen as the focus shifts out of the dropdown menu. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <emph role="bold">
                  Example of a Failure:  A help dialog
                </emph>
							     </p>
            <p>
                When a field receives focus, a help dialog window describing the field and providing options opens. As a keyboard user tabs through the Web page, the dialog opens, moving the keyboard focus away from the control every time the user attempts to tab past the field.
              </p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="resources">
      <head/>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="techniques">
      <head>Techniques for Addressing Success Criterion 3.2.1</head>
      <div4 role="sufficient">
         <head/>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="G107"
                       linktype="general">Using "activate" rather than "focus" as a trigger for changes of context</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
         </olist>
         <note>
            <p>A change of content is not always a <loc href="context-changedef"
                    linktype="glossary">change of context</loc>. This success criterion is automatically met if changes in content are not also changes of context.</p>
         </note>
      </div4>
      <div4 role="tech-optional">
         <head>Additional Techniques (Advisory) for 3.2.1</head>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>Not causing persistent changes of state or value when a component receives focus, or providing an alternate means to reset any changes (future link)</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="G200"
                       linktype="general">Opening new windows and tabs from a link only when necessary</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="G201"
                       linktype="general">Giving users advanced warning when opening a new window</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </div4>
      <div4 role="failures">
         <head>Common Failures Identified by the Working Group</head>
         <ulist>
            <item role="script">
               <p>
									         <loc href="F52"
                       linktype="failure">Failure due to opening a new window as soon as a new page is loaded without prior warning</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item role="script">
               <p>
									         <loc href="F55"
                       linktype="failure">Failure due to using script to remove focus when focus is received</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </div4>
   </div3>
</div2>
