<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE div2
  SYSTEM "../xmlspec.dtd">
<div2 role="extsrc" id="ensure-compat-parses">
   <head>4.1.1</head>
   <div3 role="intent">
      <head>Intent of this Success Criterion</head>
      <p>The intent of this Success Criterion is to ensure that user agents, including assistive technologies, can accurately interpret and parse content. If the content cannot be parsed into a data structure, then different user agents may present it differently or be completely unable to parse it. Some user agents use "repair techniques" to render poorly coded content. 
            
          </p>
      <p>Since repair techniques vary among user agents, authors cannot assume that content will be accurately parsed into a data structure or that it will be rendered correctly by specialized user agents, including assistive technologies, unless the content is created according to the rules defined in the formal grammar for that technology. In markup languages, errors in element and attribute syntax and
failure to provide properly nested start/end tags lead to errors that
prevent user agents from parsing the content reliably.
            Therefore, the Success Criterion requires that the content can be parsed using only the rules of the formal grammar.
          </p>
      <note>
         <p>The concept of "well formed" is close to what is required here. However, exact parsing requirements vary amongst markup languages, and most non XML-based languages do not explicitly define requirements for well formedness. Therefore, it was necessary to be more explicit in the success criterion in order to be generally applicable to markup languages. Because the term "well formed" is only defined in XML, and (because end tags are sometimes optional) valid HTML does not require well formed code, the term is not used in this success criterion.</p>
         <p>With the exception of one success criterion (<specref ref="visual-audio-contrast-scale"/>, which specifically mentions that the effect specified by the success criterion must be achieved without relying on an assistive technology) authors can meet the success criteria with content that assumes use of an assistive technology (or access features in use agents) by the user, where such assistive technologies (or access features in user agents) exist and are available to the user.</p>
      </note>
      <div4 role="benefits">
         <head>Benefits of this Success Criterion</head>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>Ensuring that Web pages have complete start and end tags and are nested according to specification
                   helps ensure that assistive technologies can parse the content accurately and without crashing.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </div4>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="examples">
      <head>Examples for this Success Criterion</head>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="resources">
      <head>Resources for this Success Criterion </head>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="techniques">
      <head>Techniques for Addressing Success Criterion 4.1.1</head>
      <div4 role="sufficient">
         <head/>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="G134"
                       linktype="general">Validating Web pages</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="G192"
                       linktype="general">Fully conforming to specifications</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="H88" linktype="html">Using (X)HTML according to spec</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item role="html">
               <p>Ensuring that Web pages can be parsed  by using one of the following techniques:</p>
               <ulist>
                  <item>
                     <p>
											             <loc href="H74" linktype="html">Ensuring that  opening and closing tags are used according to specification</loc>
											             <emph role="bold">AND</emph>
											             <loc href="H93" linktype="html">Ensuring that <att>id</att> attributes are unique on a Web page</loc>
											             <emph role="bold">AND</emph>
											             <loc href="H94" linktype="html">Ensuring that elements do not contain duplicate attributes</loc>
										           </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
											             <loc href="H75" linktype="html">Ensuring that 
                        Web pages are well-formed</loc>
										           </p>
                  </item>
               </ulist>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc href="SL33"
                       linktype="silverlight"/>
               </p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </div4>
      <div4 role="tech-optional">
         <head>Additional Techniques (Advisory) for 4.1.1</head>
      </div4>
      <div4 role="failures">
         <head/>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="F70"
                       linktype="failure">Failure of 4.1.1 due to incorrect use of start and end tags or attribute markup</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="F77"
                       linktype="failure">Failure of 4.1.1 due to duplicate values of type ID</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </div4>
   </div3>
</div2>
