<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE div2
  SYSTEM "../xmlspec.dtd">
<div2 role="extsrc" id="ensure-compat-rsv">
   <head>4.1.2</head>
   <div3 role="intent">
      <head>Intent of this Success Criterion</head>
      <p>The intent of this Success Criterion is to ensure that Assistive Technologies (AT) can gather information about, activate(or set) and keep up to date on the status of user interface controls in the content.</p>
      <p>When standard controls from accessible technologies are used, this process is straightforward. If the user interface elements are used according to specification the conditions of this provision will be met. (See examples  of Success Criterion 4.1.2 below)</p>
      <p>If custom controls are created, however, or interface elements are programmed (in code or script) to have a different role and/or function than usual, then additional measures need to be taken to ensure that the controls provide important information to assistive technologies and allow themselves to be controlled by assistive technologies.</p>
      <p>A particularly important state of a user interface control is whether or not it has focus. The focus state of a control can be programmatically determined, and notifications about change of focus are sent to user agents and assistive technology. Other examples of user interface control state are whether or not a checkbox or radio button has been selected, or whether or not a collapsible tree or list node is expanded or collapsed.</p>
      <note>
         <p>Success Criterion 4.1.2 requires a programmatically determinable name for all user interface components. Names may be visible or invisible. Occasionally, the name must be visible, in which case it is identified as a label. Refer to the definition of name and label in the glossary for more information.</p>
      </note>
      <div4 role="benefits">
         <head>Benefits of this Success Criterion</head>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>Providing role, state, and value information on all user interface components enables compatibility with assistive technology, such as screen readers, screen magnifiers, and speech recognition software, used by people with disabilities.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </div4>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="examples">
      <head>Examples for this Success Criterion</head>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <emph role="bold">Accessible APIs </emph>
							     </p>
            <p>A Java applet uses the accessibility API defined by the language. </p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="resources">
      <head>Resources for this Success Criterion </head>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <loc href="http://www.w3.org/WAI/PF/roadmap/">Dynamic Accessible Web Content Roadmap</loc>
							     </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <loc href="http://www.w3.org/WAI/PF/GUI/">Role Taxonomy for Accessible Adaptable Applications</loc>
							     </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <loc href="http://www.w3.org/WAI/PF/adaptable/">States and Adaptable Properties Module</loc>
							     </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <loc href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/ms697707.aspx">Microsoft Active Accessibility, Version 2.0</loc>
							     </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <loc href="http://www.adobe.com/accessibility.htmlproducts/flash/best-practices.html">Adobe Flash accessibility design guidelines</loc>
							     </p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="techniques">
      <head>Techniques for Addressing Success Criterion 4.1.2</head>
      <div4 role="sufficient">
         <head/>
         <div5 role="situation">
            <head>Situation A: If using a standard user interface component in a markup language (e.g., HTML):</head>
            <olist>
               <item>
                  <p>
                     <loc href="ARIA14"
                          linktype="aria"/>
                  </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>
                     <loc href="ARIA16"
                          linktype="aria"/>
                  </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p> 
                     <loc href="G108"
                          linktype="general">Using markup features to expose the name and role, allow user-settable properties to be directly set, and provide notification of changes</loc> using technology-specific techniques below:</p>
                  <ulist>
                     <item>
                        <p>
												               <loc href="H91" linktype="html">Using HTML form controls and links</loc>
											             </p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <p>
												               <loc href="H44" linktype="html">Using label elements to associate text labels with form controls</loc>
											             </p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <p>
												               <loc href="H64" linktype="html">Using the title attribute of the frame element</loc>
											             </p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <p>
												               <loc href="H65" linktype="html">Using the title attribute to identify form controls when the label element cannot be used</loc>
											             </p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <p>
												               <loc href="H88" linktype="html">Using (X)HTML according to spec</loc>
											             </p>
                     </item>
                  </ulist>
               </item>
            </olist>
         </div5>
         <div5 role="situation">
            <head role="script">Situation B: If using script or code to re-purpose a standard user interface component in a markup language:</head>
            <olist>
               <item role="script">
                  <p>Exposing the names and roles, allowing user-settable properties to be directly set, and providing notification of changes using one of the following techniques:</p>
                  <ulist>
                     <item>
                        <p>
                           <loc href="ARIA16"
                                linktype="aria"/>
                        </p>
                     </item>
                  </ulist>
               </item>
            </olist>
         </div5>
         <div5 role="situation">
            <head>Situation C: If using a standard user interface component in a programming technology:</head>
            <olist>
               <item>
                  <p>
										           <loc href="G135"
                          linktype="general">Using the accessibility API features of a technology to expose the names and roles, allow user-settable properties to be directly set, and provide notification of changes</loc> using technology-specific techniques below:
									</p>
                  <ulist>
                     <item>
                        <p>
												               <loc href="FLASH32"
                                linktype="flash">Using auto labeling to associate text labels with form controls</loc>
											             </p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <p>
												               <loc href="FLASH29"
                                linktype="flash">Setting the label property for form components</loc>
											             </p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <p>
												               <loc href="FLASH30"
                                linktype="flash">Specifying accessible names for image buttons</loc>
											             </p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <p>
                           <loc href="PDF10" linktype="pdf"/>
                        </p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <p>
                           <loc href="PDF12" linktype="pdf"/>
                        </p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <p>
                           <loc href="SL26"
                                linktype="silverlight"/>
                        </p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <p>
                           <loc href="SL32"
                                linktype="silverlight"/>
                        </p>
                     </item>
                  </ulist>
               </item>
            </olist>
         </div5>
         <div5 role="situation">
            <head>Situation D: If creating your own user interface component in a programming language:</head>
            <olist>
               <item>
                  <p>
										           <loc href="G10"
                          linktype="general">Creating components using a technology that supports the accessibility API features of the platforms on which the user agents will be run to expose the names and roles, allow user-settable properties to be directly set, and provide notification of changes</loc> using technology-specific techniques below:
									</p>
                  <ulist>
                     <item>
                        <p>
                           <loc href="ARIA4" linktype="aria"/>
                        </p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <p>
                           <loc href="ARIA5" linktype="aria"/>
                        </p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <p>
                           <loc href="ARIA16"
                                linktype="aria"/>
                        </p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <p>
                           <loc href="SL6"
                                linktype="silverlight"/>
                        </p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <p>
                           <loc href="SL18"
                                linktype="silverlight"/>
                        </p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <p>
                           <loc href="SL20"
                                linktype="silverlight"/>
                        </p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <p>
                           <loc href="SL30"
                                linktype="silverlight"/>
                        </p>
                     </item>
                  </ulist>
               </item>
            </olist>
         </div5>
      </div4>
      <div4 role="tech-optional">
         <head>Additional Techniques (Advisory) for 4.1.2</head>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>Providing
labels for all form controls that do not have implicit labels (future link)
                </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </div4>
      <div4 role="failures">
         <head/>
         <ulist>
            <item role="script">
               <p>
									         <loc href="F59"
                       linktype="failure">Failure due to using script to make div or span a user interface control in HTML</loc>
								       </p>
               <note>
                  <p>This failure may be solved in the future using DHTML roadmap techniques.    </p>
               </note>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="F15"
                       linktype="failure">Failure due to implementing custom controls that do not use an accessibility API</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="F20"
                       linktype="failure">Failure due to not updating text alternatives when changes to non-text content occur</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="F68"
                       linktype="failure">Failure of 1.3.1 and 4.1.2 due to the association of label and user interface controls not being programmatically determinable</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="F79"
                       linktype="failure">Failure of Success Criterion 4.1.2 due to the focus state of a user interface component not being programmatically determinable or no notification of change of focus state available</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="F86"
                       linktype="failure">Failure of Success Criterion 4.1.2 due to not providing names for each part of a multi-part form field, such as a US telephone number</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="F89"
                       linktype="failure">Failure of 2.4.4 due to using null alt on an image where the image is the only content in a link</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </div4>
   </div3>
</div2>
