<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE div2
  SYSTEM "../xmlspec.dtd">
<div2 role="extsrc" id="keyboard-operation-trapping">
   <head>2.1.2</head>
   <div3 role="intent">
      <head>Intent of this Success Criterion</head>
      <p>The intent of this Success Criterion is to ensure that that content does not "trap" keyboard focus within subsections of content on a Web page. This is a common problem when multiple formats are combined within a page and rendered using plug-ins or embedded applications.</p>
      <p>There may be times when the functionality of the Web page restricts the focus to a subsection of the content, as long as the user knows how to leave that state and "untrap" the focus.</p>
      <div4 role="benefits">
         <head>Benefits of this Success Criterion</head>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>People who rely on a keyboard or keyboard interface to use the Web including people who are blind and people with physical disabilities.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </div4>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="examples">
      <head>Examples of this Success Criterion</head>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <emph role="bold">A calendar widget</emph>
							     </p>
            <p>A calendar widget allows users to add, remove or update items in their calendar using the keyboard. The controls in the widget are part of the tab order within the Web page, allowing users to tab through the controls in the widget as well as to any links or controls that follow.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <emph role="bold">A puzzle applet</emph>
							     </p>
            <p>Once a user tabs into an applet, further tabs and other keystrokes are handled by the applet. Instructions describing the keystroke used to exit the applet are provided prior to the applet as well as within the applet itself.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <emph role="bold">A modal dialog box</emph>
							     </p>
            <p>A Web application brings up a dialog box. At the bottom of the dialog are two buttons, Cancel and OK. When the dialog has been opened, focus is trapped within the dialog; tabbing from the last control in the dialog takes focus to the first control in the dialog. The dialog is dismissed by activating the Cancel button or the OK button.</p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="resources">
      <head/>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="techniques">
      <head>Technqiues for this Success Criterion</head>
      <div4 role="sufficient">
         <head>Sufficient Techniques</head>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="G21"
                       linktype="general">Ensuring that users are not trapped in content</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="FLASH17"
                       linktype="flash">Preventing a keyboard trap in Flash content</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </div4>
      <div4 role="tech-optional">
         <head>Advisory Techniques</head>
      </div4>
      <div4 role="failures">
         <head/>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="F10"
                       linktype="failure">Failure of Success Criterion 2.1.2 and Conformance Requirement 5 due to combining multiple content formats in a way that traps users inside one format type</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </div4>
   </div3>
</div2>
