<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE div2
  SYSTEM "../xmlspec.dtd">
<div2 role="extsrc" id="meaning-idioms">
   <head>3.1.3</head>
   <div3 role="intent">
      <head>Intent of this Success Criterion</head>
      <p>Certain disabilities make it difficult to understand nonliteral word usage and specialized words or usage. Certain disabilities make it difficult to understand figurative language or specialized usage. Providing such mechanisms is vital for these audiences. Specialized information intended for non-specialist readers is encouraged to satisfy this Success Criterion, even when claiming only Single-A or Double-A conformance. 
            
          </p>
      <div4 role="benefits">
         <head>Benefits of this Success Criterion</head>
         <p>This Success Criterion may help people with cognitive, language and learning disabilities who:</p>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>have difficulty decoding words</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>have difficulty understanding words and phrases</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>have difficulty using context to aid understanding</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
         <p>It would also help people with visual disabilities who:</p>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>lose context when zoomed-in with a screen magnifier</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </div4>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="examples">
      <head>Examples for this Success Criterion</head>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <emph role="bold">Text that includes a definition for a word used in an unusual way.</emph>
							     </p>
            <p>Organize the list or "cascade" of dictionaries and other resources so that the definition search will find the intended definitions instead of displaying definitions from other sources in the "cascade." (The "cascade" lists the dictionaries and other reference materials in the order most likely to bring up the right definition. This controls the order to follow when searching for definitions.)</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <emph role="bold">Including definitions in the glossary.</emph>
							     </p>
            <p>WCAG 2 uses the word "text" in a specific way. Thus, when the word "text" is used within WCAG 2 it is linked to the definition of "text" provided in a glossary within the same Web page.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <emph role="bold">The specific definition of a word is provided at the bottom of the page.</emph>
							     </p>
            <p>The internal link from the word to the corresponding definition is also provided within the page.
              </p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="resources">
      <head>Resources for this Success Criterion </head>
      <note>
         <p>The inclusion of a product or vendor name in the list below does not constitute an endorsement by the Web Content Accessibility Guidelines Working Group or the Web Accessibility Initiative of the World Wide Web Consortium. This list is provided simply for convenience and to give users an idea of what resources may be available</p>
      </note>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>Free bilingual dictionaries for a number of languages are available from the <loc href="http://www.freedict.org/">Freedict.org Web site</loc>. The dictionaries are of uneven quality and size as noted on the site. Retrieved 9 April 2005.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 
               <loc href="http://www.stars21.com/index.html?lang=en&amp;pname=african">The WorldStar Free Dictionaries, Translators and Search Engines</loc> site provides access to free on-line dictionaries and search engines in many languages. Retrieved 18 November 2005.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>More dictionaries are at <loc href="http://www.yourdictionary.com">your dictionary</loc>, <loc href="http://www.freelang.com">freelang.com</loc> (in English, Spanish and French!) and many other places.</p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="techniques">
      <head>Techniques for Addressing Success Criterion 3.1.3</head>
      <div4 role="sufficient">
         <head/>
         <div5 role="situation">
            <head>Situation A: If the word or phrase has a unique meaning within the Web page:</head>
            <olist>
               <item>
                  <p> 
                     <loc href="G101"
                          linktype="general">Providing the definition of a word or phrase used in an unusual or restricted way</loc> for the first occurrence of the word or phrase in a Web page using one of the following techniques:
</p>
                  <ulist>
                     <item>
                        <p>
												               <loc href="G55"
                                linktype="general">Linking to definitions</loc>
											             </p>
                        <ulist>
                           <item>
                              <p>
														                   <loc href="H40" linktype="html">Using definition lists</loc>
													                 </p>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <p>
														                   <loc href="H60" linktype="html">Using the link element to link to a glossary</loc>
													                 </p>
                           </item>
                        </ulist>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <p>
												               <loc href="G112"
                                linktype="general">Using inline definitions</loc>
											             </p>
                        <ulist>
                           <item>
                              <p>
														                   <loc href="H54" linktype="html">Using the dfn element to identify the defining instance of a word</loc>
													                 </p>
                           </item>
                        </ulist>
                     </item>
                  </ulist>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p> 
                     <loc href="G101"
                          linktype="general">Providing the definition of a word or phrase used in an unusual or restricted way</loc> for each occurrence of the word or phrase in a Web page using one of the following techniques:
</p>
                  <ulist>
                     <item>
                        <p>
												               <loc href="G55"
                                linktype="general">Linking to definitions</loc>
											             </p>
                        <ulist>
                           <item>
                              <p>
														                   <loc href="H40" linktype="html">Using definition lists</loc>
													                 </p>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <p>
														                   <loc href="H60" linktype="html">Using the link element to link to a glossary</loc>
													                 </p>
                           </item>
                        </ulist>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <p>
												               <loc href="G62"
                                linktype="general">Providing a Glossary</loc>
											             </p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <p>
												               <loc href="G70"
                                linktype="general">
Providing a function to search an on-line dictionary</loc>
											             </p>
                     </item>
                  </ulist>
               </item>
            </olist>
         </div5>
         <div5 role="situation">
            <head>Situation B: If the word or phrase means different things within the same Web page:</head>
            <olist>
               <item>
                  <p> 
                     <loc href="G101"
                          linktype="general">Providing the definition of a word or phrase used in an unusual or restricted way</loc> for each occurrence of the word or phrase in a Web page using one of the following techniques:
</p>
                  <ulist>
                     <item>
                        <p>
												               <loc href="G55"
                                linktype="general">Linking to definitions</loc>
											             </p>
                        <ulist>
                           <item>
                              <p>
														                   <loc href="H40" linktype="html">Using definition lists</loc>
													                 </p>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <p>
														                   <loc href="H60" linktype="html">Using the link element to link to a glossary</loc>
													                 </p>
                           </item>
                        </ulist>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <p>
												               <loc href="G112"
                                linktype="general">Using inline definitions</loc>
											             </p>
                        <ulist>
                           <item>
                              <p>
														                   <loc href="H54" linktype="html">Using the dfn element to identify the defining instance of a word</loc>
													                 </p>
                           </item>
                        </ulist>
                     </item>
                  </ulist>
               </item>
            </olist>
         </div5>
      </div4>
      <div4 role="tech-optional">
         <head>Additional Techniques (Advisory) for 3.1.3</head>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>Using markup and visual formatting to help users recognize words that have special meaning (future link)</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Providing a voice-enabled dictionary search so that users who have difficulty typing or spelling can speak the word whose definition they need (future link)</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Providing a sign language dictionary to help users who are deaf find the necessary definitions (future link)</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Providing a mechanism for finding definitions for all words in text content (future link)</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Providing a mechanism to determine the meaning of each word or phrase in text content (future link)</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Avoiding unusual foreign words (future link)
                </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Using a series of dictionaries in cascading fashion to provide meanings (future link)
            		</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </div4>
      <div4 role="failures">
         <head/>
      </div4>
   </div3>
</div2>
