<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE div2
  SYSTEM "../xmlspec.dtd">
<div2 role="extsrc" id="media-equiv-audio-desc-only">
   <head>1.2.5</head>
   <div3 role="intent">
      <head>Intent of this Success Criterion</head>
      <p>The intent of this Success Criterion is to provide people who are blind or visually impaired access to the visual information in a synchronized media presentation. The audio description augments the audio portion of the presentation with the information needed when the video portion is not available. During existing pauses in dialogue, audio description provides information about actions, characters, scene changes, and on-screen text that are important and are not described or spoken in the main sound track.</p>
      <note>
         <p>
              For 1.2.3, 1.2.5, and 1.2.7, if all of the information in the video track is already provided in the audio track, no audio description is necessary. 
              
            </p>
         <p>
              1.2.3, 1.2.5, and 1.2.8 overlap somewhat with each other. This is to give the author some choice at the minimum conformance level, and to provide additional requirements at higher levels. At Level A in Success Criterion 1.2.3, authors do have the choice of providing either an audio description or a full text alternative. If they wish to conform at Level AA, under Success Criterion 1.2.5 authors must provide an audio description - a requirement already met if they chose that alternative for 1.2.3, otherwise an additional requirement. At Level AAA under Success Criterion 1.2.8 they must provide an extended text description. This is an additional requirement if both 1.2.3 and 1.2.5 were met by providing an audio description only. If 1.2.3 was met, however, by providing a text description, and the 1.2.5 requirement for an audio description was met, then 1.2.8 does not add new requirements.</p>
      </note>
      <div4 role="benefits">
         <head>Benefits of this Success Criterion</head>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>People who are blind or have low vision as well as those with cognitive limitations who have difficulty interpreting visually what is happening benefit from audio description of visual information.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </div4>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="examples">
      <head>Examples for this Success Criterion</head>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <emph role="bold">A movie with audio description.</emph>
							     </p>
            <p> 
               <emph role="bold">Describer: </emph>A title, "Teaching Evolution Case Studies. Bonnie Chen." A teacher shows photographs of birds with long, thin beaks.</p>
            <p> 
               <emph role="bold">Bonnie Chen: </emph>"These photos were all taken at the Everglades."</p>
            <p> 
               <emph role="bold">Describer: </emph>The teacher hands each student two flat, thin wooden sticks.</p>
            <p> 
               <emph role="bold">Bonnie Chen: </emph>"Today you will pretend to be a species of wading bird that has a beak like this."</p>
            <p> 
               <emph role="bold">Describer: </emph>The teacher holds two of the sticks to her mouth making the shape of a beak.</p>
            <p>Transcript of audio based on the first few minutes of "<loc href="http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/evolution/educators/teachstuds/tvideos.html">Teaching Evolution Case Studies, Bonnie Chen</loc>" (copyright WGBH and Clear Blue Sky Productions, Inc.)</p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="resources">
      <head>Resources for this Success Criterion</head>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <loc href="http://ncam.wgbh.org/invent_build/web_multimedia/accessible-digital-media-guide/guideline-h-multimedia#techH12">NCAM Rich Media Accessibility, Accessible SMIL Templates</loc>
							     </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <loc href="http://joeclark.org/access/description/ad-principles.html">Standard Techniques in Audio Description</loc>
							     </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <loc href="http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-smil/">Synchronized Multimedia Integration Language (SMIL) 1.0</loc>
							     </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <loc href="http://www.w3.org/TR/SMIL/">Synchronized Multimedia Integration Language (SMIL 2.0)</loc>
							     </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <loc href="http://www.w3.org/TR/SMIL-access/">Accessibility Features of SMIL</loc>
							     </p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="techniques">
      <head>Techniques for Addressing Success Criterion 1.2.5</head>
      <div4 role="sufficient">
         <head/>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="G78"
                       linktype="general">G78: Providing a second, user-selectable, audio track that includes audio descriptions</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item role="silverlight">
               <p>
                  <loc href="G78"
                       linktype="general"/> 
                  <emph role="bold">AND</emph> 
                  <loc href="SL1"
                       linktype="silverlight"/>
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> 
                  <loc href="G173"
                       linktype="general">Providing a version of a movie with audio descriptions</loc> using one of the following:</p>
               <ulist>
                  <item>
                     <p>
											             <loc href="SM6" linktype="smil">Providing audio description in SMIL 1.0</loc>
										           </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
											             <loc href="SM7" linktype="smil">Providing audio description in SMIL 2.0</loc>
										           </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
											             <loc href="FLASH26"
                             linktype="flash">Applying audio descriptions to Flash video</loc>
										           </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>Using any player that supports audio and video</p>
                  </item>
               </ulist>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> 
                  <loc href="G8" linktype="general">Providing a movie with extended audio descriptions</loc> using one of the following:    </p>
               <ulist>
                  <item>
                     <p>
											             <loc href="SM1" linktype="smil">Adding extended audio description in SMIL 1.0</loc>
										           </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
											             <loc href="SM2" linktype="smil">Adding extended audio description in SMIL 2.0</loc>
										           </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
											             <loc href="FLASH26"
                             linktype="flash">Applying audio descriptions to Flash video</loc>
										           </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>Using any player that supports audio and video</p>
                  </item>
               </ulist>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc href="G203"
                       linktype="general"/>
               </p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </div4>
      <div4 role="tech-optional">
         <head>Additional Techniques (Advisory) for 1.2.4</head>
         <ulist>
                  <item>
                     <p>
			             <loc href="H96" linktype="html"/>
  		             </p>
                  </item>
            <item role="smil">
               <p>
        Providing audio description in multiple languages in SMIL 1.0 (future link)
    </p>
            </item>
            <item role="smil">
               <p>
        Providing audio description in multiple languages in SMIL 2.0 (future link)
    </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Providing 
audio description for live synchronized media (future link)  
            </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </div4>
      <div4 role="failures">
         <head/>
      </div4>
   </div3>
</div2>
