<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE div2
  SYSTEM "../xmlspec.dtd">
<div2 role="extsrc" id="media-equiv-sign">
   <head>1.2.6</head>
   <div3 role="intent">
      <head>Intent of this Success Criterion</head>
      <p>The intent of this Success Criterion is to enable people who are deaf or hard of hearing and who are fluent in a sign language to understand the content of the audio track of synchronized media presentations. Written text, such as that found in captions, is often a second language. Because sign language provides the ability to provide intonation, emotion and other audio information that is reflected in sign language interpretation, but not in captions, sign language interpretation provides richer and more equivalent access to synchronized media. People who communicate extensively in sign language are also faster in sign language and synchronized media is a time-based presentation. 
            
          </p>
      <div4 role="benefits">
         <head/>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>People whose human language is a sign language sometimes have limited reading ability. These individuals may not be able to read and comprehend the captions and thus require a sign language interpretation to gain access to the synchronized media content.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </div4>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="examples">
      <head/>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p> 
               <emph role="bold"> Example 1.</emph> A corporation is making an important announcement to all of its employees. The meeting will be held in the main headquarters and streamed to the Web. A sign language interpreter is provided at the meeting location. The live video includes a full view of the sign language interpreter as well as the person presenting.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 
               <emph role="bold"> Example 2.</emph> The same announcement described in example 1 is also Webcast to remote employees. Since there is only one display available for this, the sign language interpreter is shown in the corner of the display.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 
               <emph role="bold"> Example 3.</emph> A university is providing an on-line version of a particular lecture by creating a synchronized media presentation of the professor delivering the lecture. The presentation includes video of the professor speaking and demonstrating a science experiment. A sign language interpretation of the lecture is created and presented on the Web with the synchronized media version.</p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="resources">
      <head/>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <loc href="http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-smil/">Synchronized Multimedia Integration Language (SMIL) 1.0</loc>
							     </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <loc href="http://www.w3.org/TR/SMIL/">Synchronized Multimedia Integration Language (SMIL 2.0)</loc>
							     </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <loc href="http://www.w3.org/TR/SMIL-access/">Accessibility Features of SMIL</loc>
							     </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <loc href="http://ncam.wgbh.org/invent_build/web_multimedia/accessible-digital-media-guide/guideline-h-multimedia#techH12">NCAM Rich Media Accessibility, Accessible SMIL Templates</loc>
							     </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 
               <loc href="https://www.nidcd.nih.gov/health/american-sign-language">National Institute on Deafness and other Communication Disorders</loc>: Information on American Sign Language</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <loc href="http://www.sign-lang.uni-hamburg.de/signingbooks/sbrc/grid/d71/guide12.htm">Techniques for filming sign language interpreters</loc>
							     </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <loc href="http://www.actiononhearingloss.org.uk/">Royal National Institute for Deaf People (RNID)</loc>
							     </p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="techniques">
      <head>Techniques for Addressing Success Criterion 1.2.6</head>
      <div4 role="sufficient">
         <head/>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="G54"
                       linktype="general">Including a sign language interpreter in the corner of the video stream</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <!-- BBC: Not complete as of PR, so commented out. item>
                <p>Providing a new page that has the video with the sign language interpretation of the audio track (future link) 
                </p>
              </item-->
            <item role="smil">
               <p> 
                  <loc href="G81"
                       linktype="general">Providing a synchronized video of the sign language interpreter that can be displayed in a different viewport or overlaid on the image by the player</loc> using one of the following techniques
    </p>
               <ulist>
                  <item>
                     <p>
											             <loc href="SM13" linktype="smil">Providing sign language interpretation through synchronized video streams in SMIL 1.0</loc>
										           </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
											             <loc href="SM14" linktype="smil">Providing sign language interpretation through synchronized video streams in SMIL 2.0</loc>
										           </p>
                  </item>
               </ulist>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </div4>
      <div4 role="tech-optional">
         <head>Additional Techniques (Advisory) for 1.2.5</head>
         <div5>
            <head>Metadata Techniques</head>
            <ulist>
               <item>
                  <p> Using metadata to associate sign language alternatives of a video to enable choice of sign language (future link)</p>
                  <ulist>
                     <item>
                        <p>EXAMPLE: Providing, in metadata, URI(s) that point to  several English sign language translations (ASL, SASL, BSL, Auslan,  ISL, NZSL) of a Web page. </p>
                     </item>
                  </ulist>
               </item>
            </ulist>
         </div5>
      </div4>
      <div4 role="failures">
         <head>Common Failures Identified by the Working Group</head>
      </div4>
   </div3>
</div2>
