<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE div2
  SYSTEM "../xmlspec.dtd">
<div2 role="extsrc" id="media-equiv-live-audio-only">
   <head>1.2.9</head>
   <div3 role="intent">
      <head>Intent</head>
      <p>The intent of this Success Criterion is to make information conveyed by live audio, such as video conferencing, live speeches and radio Webcasts, accessible through the use of a text alternative. A live text caption service will enable live audio to be accessible to people who are deaf or hard of hearing, or who cannot otherwise hear the audio. Such services use a trained human operator who listens in to what is being said and uses a special keyboard to enter the text with only a small delay. They are able to capture a live event with a high degree of fidelity, and also to insert notes on any non spoken audio which is essential to understanding the event. A transcript is sometimes a possibility if the live audio is following a set script; but a live caption service is preferred because it plays out at the same pace as the audio itself, and can adapt to any deviations from the script that might occur.</p>
      <p>Using untrained operators, or providing a transcript which differs markedly from what actually happens would not be considered meeting this Success Criterion. </p>
      <p>This success criterion was intended to apply to broadcast of audio and is not intended to require that two-way audio calls between two or more individuals through web apps must be captioned regardless of the needs of users. Responsibility for providing captions would fall to the content providers (the callers) or the “host” caller, and not the application.</p>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="examples">
      <head>Examples</head>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>A public relations firm uses Web based caption services to cover live events; the output from the service is incorporated in a sub frame of the Web page which includes the streaming audio control.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>A live radio play of a fringe theatre group is being broadcast to the Web. As the actors stick largely to a set script, and the budget for the program is small, the producers provide a link (with the playwright's permission) to the script of the play.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>A streaming audio server uses a media format which can also accommodate text and graphics, such as Flash or Silverlight. A stenographer is used to create live captions at an event, and these are mixed on the fly to produce live captions in the media stream which can be viewed by the media player. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>A CEO is to give a press release by telephone to the media in response to a breaking news story, the audio is being recorded and streamed over the internet, but due to time constraints a Web captioning service cannot be set up in time. As the press release is a set statement which the CEO will be reading out, the company simultaneously provides the transcript of the release.</p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="resources">
      <head>Resources for this Success Criterion </head>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <loc href="http://www.captioningandsubtitling.com.au/work/internet/">Captioning and Subtitling International</loc>
							     </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <loc href="http://webaim.org/techniques/captions/realtime">WebAIM Real time captioning resource</loc>
							     </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <loc href="http://www.uiaccess.com/transcripts/transcript_services.html">uiAccess list of transcription services</loc>
							     </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <loc href="http://www.uiaccess.com/transcripts/transcripts_on_the_web.html">Transcripts on the Web: Getting people to your podcasts and videos</loc>
							     </p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="techniques">
      <head>Techniques for Addressing Success Criterion 1.2.9</head>
      <div4 role="sufficient">
         <head>Sufficient</head>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="G151"
                       linktype="general">Providing a link to a text transcript of a prepared statement or script if the script is followed</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="G150"
                       linktype="general">Providing text alternatives for live audio-only content</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="G157"
                       linktype="general">Incorporating a live audio captioning service into a Web page</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </div4>
      <div4 role="tech-optional">
         <head>Optional Techniques (Advisory) for 1.1.2</head>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p> Using metadata to associate text transcriptions with audio-only content (future link)</p>
               <example>
                  <p>Providing, in metadata, URI(s) that point to several text transcripts (English, French, Dutch) of an audio file.</p>
               </example>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </div4>
      <div4 role="failures">
         <head>Failures</head>
      </div4>
   </div3>
</div2>
