<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE div2
  SYSTEM "../xmlspec.dtd">
<div2 role="extsrc" id="media-equiv-extended-ad">
   <head>1.2.7</head>
   <div3 role="intent">
      <head>Intent of this Success Criterion</head>
      <p>The intent of this Success Criterion is to provide people who are blind or visually impaired access to a synchronized media presentation beyond that which can be provided by standard audio description.    This is done by periodically freezing the synchronized media presentation and playing additional audio description.  The synchronized media presentation is then resumed.  </p>
      <p>Because it disrupts viewing for those who do not need the additional description, techniques that allow you to turn the feature on and off are often provided.  Alternately, versions with and without the additional description can be provided. </p>
      <div4 role="benefits">
         <head/>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>People who are blind, people with low vision who cannot see the screen, as well as those with cognitive limitations who have difficulty interpreting visually what is happening, often use audio description of the visual information. However, if there is too much dialogue the audio description is insufficient. Extended audio description can provide the additional information needed to understand the video.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </div4>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="examples">
      <head>Examples</head>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <emph>Example 1. Video of a lecture.</emph> A physics professor is giving a lecture. He makes freehand sketches on the whiteboard, speaking rapidly as he draws. As soon as he has finished discussing one problem, he erases the drawing and makes another sketch while continuing to speak and gesture with his other hand.  The video is paused between problems, and extended audio description of the professor's drawings and gestures is provided; the video is then resumed.</p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="resources">
      <head/>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <loc href="http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-smil/">Synchronized Multimedia Integration Language (SMIL) 1.0</loc>
							     </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <loc href="http://www.w3.org/TR/SMIL/">Synchronized Multimedia Integration Language (SMIL) 2.0</loc>
							     </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <loc href="http://www.w3.org/TR/SMIL-access/">Accessibility Features of SMIL</loc>
							     </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <loc href="http://ncam.wgbh.org/invent_build/web_multimedia/accessible-digital-media-guide/guideline-h-multimedia#techH12">NCAM Rich Media Accessibility, Accessible SMIL Templates</loc>
							     </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <loc href="http://joeclark.org/access/description/ad-principles.html">Standard Techniques in Audio Description</loc>
							     </p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="techniques">
      <head>Techniques for Addressing Success Criterion 1.2.7</head>
      <div4 role="sufficient">
         <head/>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p> 
                  <loc href="G8" linktype="general">Providing a movie with extended audio descriptions</loc> using one of the following:    </p>
               <ulist>
                  <item>
                     <p>
											             <loc href="SM1" linktype="smil">Adding extended audio description in SMIL 1.0</loc>
										           </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
											             <loc href="SM2" linktype="smil">Adding extended audio description in SMIL 2.0</loc>
										           </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>Using any player that supports audio and video</p>
                  </item>
               </ulist>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </div4>
      <div4 role="tech-optional">
         <head>Additional Techniques (Advisory) for 1.2.7</head>
         <ulist>
                  <item>
                     <p>
			             <loc href="H96" linktype="html"/>
  		             </p>
                  </item>
            <item role="smil">
               <p>
        Adding extended audio description in multiple languages in SMIL 1.0 (future link)
    </p>
            </item>
            <item role="smil">
               <p>
        Adding extended audio description in multiple languages in SMIL 2.0 (future link)
    </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </div4>
      <div4 role="failures">
         <head/>
      </div4>
   </div3>
</div2>
