<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE div2
  SYSTEM "../xmlspec.dtd">
<div2 role="extsrc" id="media-equiv-text-doc">
   <head>1.2.8</head>
   <div3 role="intent">
      <head>Intent of this Success Criterion</head>
      <p>The intent of this Success Criterion is to make audio visual material available to individuals whose vision is too poor to reliably read <loc linktype="glossary"
              href="captionsdef">captions</loc> and whose hearing is too poor to reliably hear dialogue and <loc linktype="glossary"
              href="audiodescdef">audio description</loc>. This is done by providing an alternative for time-based media.
          </p>
      <p>This approach involves providing all of the information in the synchronized media (both visual and auditory) in text form. An alternative for time-based media provides a running description of all that is going on in the synchronized media content. The alternative for time-based media reads something like a book. Unlike audio description, the description of the video portion is not constrained to just the pauses in the existing dialogue. Full descriptions are provided of all visual information, including visual context, actions and expressions of actors, and any other visual material. In addition, non-speech sounds (laughter, off-screen voices, etc.) are described, and transcripts of all dialogue are included. The sequence of descriptions and dialogue transcripts is the same as the sequence in the synchronized media itself. As a result, the alternative for time-based media can provide a much more complete representation of the synchronized media content than audio description alone.</p>
      <p>If there is any interaction as part of the synchronized media presentation (e.g., "press now to answer the question") then the alternative for time-based media would provide hyperlinks or whatever is needed to provide parallel functionality.</p>
      <p>Individuals whose vision is too poor to reliably read captions and whose hearing is too poor to reliably hear dialogue can access the alternative for time-based media by using a refreshable braille display.</p>
      <note>
         <p>
              For 1.2.3, 1.2.5, and 1.2.7, if all of the information in the video track is already provided in the audio track, no audio description is necessary. 
              
            </p>
         <p>
              1.2.3, 1.2.5, and 1.2.8 overlap somewhat with each other. This is to give the author some choice at the minimum conformance level, and to provide additional requirements at higher levels. At Level A in Success Criterion 1.2.3, authors do have the choice of providing either an audio description or a full text alternative. If they wish to conform at Level AA, under Success Criterion 1.2.5 authors must provide an audio description - a requirement already met if they chose that alternative for 1.2.3, otherwise an additional requirement. At Level AAA under Success Criterion 1.2.8 they must provide an extended text description. This is an additional requirement if both 1.2.3 and 1.2.5 were met by providing an audio description only. If 1.2.3 was met, however, by providing a text description, and the 1.2.5 requirement for an audio description was met, then 1.2.8 does not add new requirements.</p>
      </note>
      <div4 role="benefits">
         <head>Benefits of this Success Criterion</head>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>People who cannot see well or at all and who also cannot hear well or at all can get access to information in audio-visual presentations.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </div4>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="examples">
      <head>Examples for this Success Criterion</head>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <emph role="bold">Example 1. alternative for time-based media for a training video</emph>
							     </p>
            <p>A community center purchases a Training video for use by its clients and puts it on the center's intranet. The video involves explaining use of a new technology and has a person talking and showing things at the same time. The community center provides <phrase>an</phrase> alternative for time-based media that all clients, including those who can neither see the demonstrations nor hear the explanations in the synchronized media, can use to better understand what is being presented. </p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="resources">
      <head>Resources for this Success Criterion </head>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <loc href="http://www.uiaccess.com/transcripts/transcript_services.html">uiAccess list of transcription services</loc>
							     </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <loc href="http://www.uiaccess.com/transcripts/transcripts_on_the_web.html">Transcripts on the Web: Getting people to your podcasts and videos</loc>
							     </p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="techniques">
      <head>Techniques for Addressing Success Criterion 1.2.8</head>
      <div4 role="sufficient">
         <head/>
         <div5 role="situation">
            <head>Situation A: If the content is prerecorded synchronized media:</head>
            <olist>
               <item>
                  <p> 
                     <loc href="G69"
                          linktype="general">Providing an alternative for time-based media including any interaction</loc> using one of the following techniques</p>
                  <ulist>
                     <item>
                        <p>
												               <loc href="G58"
                                linktype="general">Placing a link to the transcript immediately next to the non-text content</loc>
											             </p>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <p>
                           <loc href="SL17"
                                linktype="silverlight"/>
                        </p>
                     </item>
                  </ulist>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>Linking to the alternative for time-based media using one of the following techniques
									</p>
                  <ulist>
                     <item>
                        <p>
												               <loc href="H53" linktype="html">Using the body of the object element</loc>
											             </p>
                     </item>
                  </ulist>
               </item>
            </olist>
         </div5>
         <div5 role="situation">
            <head>Situation B: If the content is prerecorded video-only:</head>
            <olist>
               <item>
                  <p>
										           <loc href="G159"
                          linktype="general">Providing a full text transcript of the video content</loc>
									         </p>
               </item>
            </olist>
         </div5>
      </div4>
      <div4 role="tech-optional">
         <head>Additional Techniques (Advisory) for 1.2.7</head>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="H46" linktype="html">Using noembed with embed</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Providing a corrected script (future link)</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Adding detail to audio description (future link)</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </div4>
      <div4 role="failures">
         <head>Common Failures Identified by the Working Group</head>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="F74"
                       linktype="failure">Failure of 1.2.1 due to not labeling a synchronized media alternative to text as an alternative</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </div4>
   </div3>
</div2>
