<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE div2
  SYSTEM "../xmlspec.dtd">
<div2 id="minimize-error-context-help" role="extsrc">
   <head>3.3.5</head>
   <div3 role="intent">
      <head>Intent of this Success Criterion</head>
      <p>The intent of this Success Criterion is to help users avoid making mistakes. Some users with disabilities may be more likely to make mistakes than users without disabilities. Using context-sensitive help, users find out how to perform an operation without losing track of what they are doing.</p>
      <p>Context-sensitive help only needs to be provided when the label is not
sufficient to describe all functionality. The existence of context-sensitive help should be obvious to the user and they should be able to obtain it whenever they require it. 
          </p>
      <p>The content author may provide the help text, or the user agent may provide the help text based on technology-specific, programmatically determined information.
          </p>
      <div4 role="benefits">
         <head/>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>Assistance for text input helps individuals with writing disabilities and people with reading and intellectual disabilities who often have difficulty writing text in forms or other places that need text input.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Additionally, these kinds of assistance help people who are aging and have the same difficulty in text input and/or mouse operation.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </div4>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="examples">
      <head/>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <emph role="bold">on-line job application</emph>
							     </p>
            <p> Some of the questions may be hard for new job seekers to understand. A help link next to each question provides instructions and explanations for each question.</p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="resources">
      <head/>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="techniques">
      <head>Techniques for Addressing Success Criterion 3.3.5</head>
      <div4 role="sufficient">
         <head/>
         <div5 role="situation">
            <head>Situation A: If a form requires text input:</head>
            <olist>
               <item>
                  <p>
										           <loc href="G71"
                          linktype="general">Providing a help link on every Web page</loc>
									         </p>
               </item>
               <!-- BBC Commented out - not completed in time for PR item>
                  <p>
                    Using scripts to provide context-sensitive bubble help (future link) 
                  </p>
                </item-->
               <item>
                  <p>
										           <loc href="G193"
                          linktype="general">Providing help by an assistant in the Web page</loc>
									         </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>
										           <loc href="G194"
                          linktype="general">Providing spell checking and suggestions for text input if applicable to the language </loc>
									         </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>
										           <loc href="G184"
                          linktype="general">Providing text instructions at the beginning of a form or set of fields that describes the necessary input</loc>
									         </p>
               </item>
            </olist>
         </div5>
         <div5 role="situation">
            <head>Situation B: If a form requires text input in an expected data format:</head>
            <olist>
               <item>
                  <p>
										           <loc href="G89"
                          linktype="general">Providing expected data format and example</loc>
									         </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>
										           <loc href="G184"
                          linktype="general">Providing text instructions at the beginning of a form or set of fields that describes the necessary input </loc>
									         </p>
               </item>
            </olist>
         </div5>
      </div4>
      <div4 role="tech-optional">
         <head>Additional Techniques (Advisory) for 3.3.4</head>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="H89" linktype="html">Using the title attribute to provide context-sensitive help</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
        Checking byte of character and auto-converting to expected byte for text input if applicable (future link)
    </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </div4>
      <div4 role="failures">
         <head/>
      </div4>
   </div3>
</div2>
