<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE div2
  SYSTEM "../xmlspec.dtd">
<div2 id="minimize-error-suggestions" role="extsrc">
   <head>3.3.3</head>
   <div3 role="intent">
      <head>Intent of this Success Criterion</head>
      <p>The intent of this Success Criterion is to ensure that users receive appropriate suggestions for correction of an input error if it is possible. The WCAG 2.0 definition of "input error" says that it is "information provided by the user that is not accepted" by the system. Some examples of information that is not accepted include information that is required but omitted by the user and information that is provided by the user but that falls outside the required data format or allowed values.</p>
      <p>Success Criterion 3.3.1 provides for notification of errors. However, persons with cognitive limitations may find it difficult to understand how to correct the errors. People with visual disabilities may not be able to figure out exactly how to correct the error. In the case of an unsuccessful form submission, users may abandon the form because they may be unsure of how to correct the error even though they are aware that it has occurred. </p>
      <p>The content author may provide the description of the error, or the user agent may provide the description of the error based on technology-specific, programmatically determined information.
          </p>
      <div4 role="benefits">
         <head/>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>Providing information about how to correct input errors allows users who have learning disabilities to fill in a form successfully. Users who are blind or have impaired vision understand more easily the nature of the input error and how to correct it. People with motion impairment can reduce the number of times they need to change an input value.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </div4>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="examples">
      <head/>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <emph role="bold">Additional Help for Correcting An Input Error</emph>
							     </p>
            <p>The result of a form that was not successfully submitted describes an
input error in place in the page along with the correct input and offers additional help for the form field that caused the input error. 
              </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <emph role="bold">Suggestions from a Limited Set of Values</emph>
							     </p>
            <p> An input field requires that a month name be entered. If the user enters "12," suggestions for correction may include 
            </p>
            <ulist>
               <item>
                  <p>A list of the acceptable values, e.g., "Choose one of: January, February, March, April, May, June, July, August, September, October, November, December."</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>A description of the set of values, e.g., "Please provide the name of the month."</p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>The conversion of the input data interpreted as a different month format, e.g., "Do you mean 'December'?"</p>
               </item>
            </ulist>
         </item>
      </ulist>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="resources">
      <head/>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="techniques">
      <head>Techniques for Addressing Success Criterion 3.3.3</head>
      <note>
         <p>
              In some cases, more than one of these situations may apply. For example, when a mandatory field also requires the data to be in a specific format.
              
            </p>
      </note>
      <div4 role="sufficient">
         <head/>
         <div5 role="situation">
            <head>Situation A: If a mandatory field contains no information:</head>
            <olist>
               <item>
                  <p>
										           <loc href="G83"
                          linktype="general">Providing a text description that identifies the field as mandatory</loc>
									         </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>
										           <loc href="ARIA2" linktype="aria">ARIA2: Identifying required fields with the "required" property</loc>
									         </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>
                     <loc href="PDF5" linktype="pdf"/>
                  </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>
                     <loc href="SL35"
                          linktype="silverlight"/>
                  </p>
               </item>
            </olist>
            <!--<ednote>
								<edtext>The above two techniques seem more like 3.3.1 than 3.3.3 techniques</edtext>
							</ednote>-->
         </div5>
         <div5 role="situation">
            <head>Situation B: If information for a field is required to be in a specific data format:</head>
            <olist>
               <item>
                  <p>
                     <loc href="ARIA18"
                          linktype="aria"/>
                  </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>
										           <loc href="G85"
                          linktype="general">Providing a text description when user input falls outside the required format or values</loc>
									         </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>
										           <loc href="G177"
                          linktype="general">Providing suggested correction text</loc>
									         </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>
										           <loc href="SCR18"
                          linktype="script">SCR18: Providing client-side validation and alert</loc>
									         </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>
										           <loc href="SCR32"
                          linktype="script">Providing client-side validation and adding error text via the DOM</loc>
									         </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>
										           <loc href="FLASH12"
                          linktype="flash">Providing client-side validation and adding error text via the accessible description</loc>
									         </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>
                     <loc href="PDF22" linktype="pdf"/>
                  </p>
               </item>
            </olist>
         </div5>
         <div5 role="situation">
            <head>Situation C: Information provided by the user is required to be one of a limited set of values:</head>
            <olist>
               <item>
                  <p>
                     <loc href="ARIA18"
                          linktype="aria"/>
                  </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>
										           <loc href="G84"
                          linktype="general">Providing a text description when the user provides information that is not in list of allowed values</loc>
									         </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>
										           <loc href="G177"
                          linktype="general">Providing suggested correction text</loc>
									         </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>
										           <loc href="SCR18"
                          linktype="script">SCR18: Providing client-side validation and alert</loc>
									         </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>
										           <loc href="SCR32"
                          linktype="script">Providing client-side validation and adding error text via the DOM</loc>
									         </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>
										           <loc href="FLASH12"
                          linktype="flash">Providing client-side validation and adding error text via the accessible description</loc>
									         </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>
                     <loc href="PDF22" linktype="pdf"/>
                  </p>
               </item>
            </olist>
         </div5>
      </div4>
      <div4 role="tech-optional">
         <head>Additional Techniques (Advisory) for 3.3.2</head>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="G139"
                       linktype="general">G139: Creating a mechanism that allows users to jump to errors</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
        Making error messages easy to understand and distinguishable from other text in the Web page (future link)
    </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
        Validating form submissions on the server (future link)
    </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
        When mandatory information has not been provided, including descriptions or examples of correct information in addition to identifying the field as mandatory (future link)
    </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
        Repeating and emphasizing suggestions for correcting each input error in the context of its form field (future link)
    </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
        Providing a way for the user to skip from each item in a list of suggestions to its corresponding form field (future link)
    </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
        Providing additional contextual help for the form field requiring change (future link)
    </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Accepting input data in a variety of formats (future link) 
                </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="G199"
                       linktype="general">Providing success feedback when data is submitted successfully</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
         <div5>
            <head>Techniques for providing suggestions to the user (Advisory)</head>
            <ulist>
               <item>
                  <p>
        Providing a text description that contains information about the number of input errors, suggestions for corrections to each item, and instructions on how to proceed (future link)
    </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>
        Providing a text description that contains suggestions for correction as the first item (or one of the first items) of content, or emphasizing this information in the content (future link)
    </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>
        Displaying errors and suggestions in the context of the original form (for example, re-displaying a form where input errors and suggestions for correction are highlighted and displayed in the context of the original form) (future link)
    </p>
               </item>
            </ulist>
         </div5>
         <div5>
            <head role="html">HTML Techniques (Advisory)</head>
            <ulist>
               <item>
                  <p>Providing "correct examples" for data and data formats as initial text in mandatory form fields (future link)    </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>Providing links to suggested correction text "close to" form
fields, or providing the suggested correction text itself directly on
the Web page "next to" form fields (future link) </p>
               </item>
            </ulist>
         </div5>
         <div5>
            <head role="script">Client-Side Scripting Techniques (Advisory)</head>
            <ulist>
               <item>
                  <p>
										           <loc href="SCR18"
                          linktype="script">Providing client-side validation and alert</loc>
									         </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>
        Providing client-side validation and adding error text via the DOM (future link)
    </p>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <p>
        Calling a function from the submit action of a form to perform client side validation (future link)
    </p>
               </item>
            </ulist>
         </div5>
      </div4>
      <div4 role="failures">
         <head/>
      </div4>
   </div3>
</div2>
