<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE div2
  SYSTEM "../xmlspec.dtd">
<div2 id="minimize-error-cues" role="extsrc">
   <head>3.3.2</head>
   <div3 role="intent">
      <head/>
      <p>The intent of this success criterion is to have content authors place instructions or labels that identify the controls in a form so that users know what input data is expected. In the absence of field-specific labels, an instruction that identifies individual field or fields within a group is also sufficient to meet this success criterion.</p>
<p>The phrase "when content requires user input" refers to elements such as form controls that accept user input as distinct from other elements on a page like hyperlinks or images.</p>
<p>When the form control and its label or instruction are in the same field of vision, users of screen magnification software are likely to be well served. In other words, placing the label or instruction logically in close proximity to the related form control makes their relationship to each other obvious by presentation.</p>
<note>
    <p>When labels are provided for input objects, the input object's relationship to the label (or to redundant text serving as the label) must be programmatically determinable or available in text per <specref ref="content-structure-separation-programmatic"/>.The label or instruction can also serve as an accessible name as per SC 4.1.2 if marked up properly.</p>
<p>Supplementary instructions that indicate the expected data format or data range or whether input is mandatory for specific form controls do not by themselves identify what data is expected and are not covered by the term "instructions" as used in the success criterion. However, such instructions help users with disabilities avoid consequences that may result from making a mistake when submitting form data including unnecessary navigation. All visible instructions should be programmatically determinable in relation to the form control per <specref ref="content-structure-separation-programmatic"/>.</p>
      </note>
       <div4 role="benefits">
         <head/>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>A visible label or instruction (e.g. "Last name" or "Departure date" or "Your question") enables users to determine what data needs to be entered into a specific text box. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>A label or instruction also serves to convey the specific purpose of other controls like radio buttons, checkboxes, drop down controls, etc.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </div4>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="examples">
      <head/>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>A field for entering a given name is clearly labeled with "Given Name" and the field for family name is labeled "Family Name" to avoid confusion over which name is requested.</p>
             <p>Marking up each visible label, "Given Name:" / "Family Name:" as a label and using the for-id method (H44) to associate it with the corresponding field is one method of also satisfying SC 4.1.2 and SC 1.3.1 besides SC 3.3.2.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
             <p>A U.S. phone number separates the area code, exchange, and number into three fields. Parentheses surround the area code field, and a dash separates the exchange and number fields. These fields are all arranged to the right of the label "Your phone number:".</p>
             <p>Marking up the common label, "Your phone number:" as a <code><![CDATA[legend]]></code>, setting a title attribute to identify individual segments of the phone number and wrapping them all in a <code><![CDATA[fieldset]]></code> is one method of making the three controls satisfy SC 4.1.2 and SC 1.3.1 as well.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
<p>Instruction to identify form controls:</p>
      <code role="html401"><![CDATA[<form>
Enter first middle and last name for the first applicant in the next 3 fields:
<input type="text" name="fn1" id="fn1" /> 
<input type="text" name="mn1" id="mn1" /> 
<input type="text" name="ln1" id="ln1" /> 
Enter first middle and last name for the second applicant in the next
3 fields:
<input type="text" name="fn2" id="fn2" /> 
<input type="text" name="mn2" id="mn2" /> 
<input type="text" name="ln2" id="ln2" /> 
</form>]]>
<p>Placing an off-screen legend, like, "First Applicant" / "Second
Applicant", a <attr>title</attr> attribute to identify first middle and last name
boxes and wrapping them all in a <code><![CDATA[fieldset]]></code> is one method of making the
above satisfy SC 4.1.2 and SC 1.3.1 too.</p>        
          </item>
      </ulist>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="resources">
      <head/>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="techniques">
      <head>Techniques for Addressing Success Criterion 3.3.2</head>
      <div4 role="sufficient">
         <head/>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p> 
                  <loc href="G131"
                       linktype="general">Providing descriptive labels</loc> 
                  <emph role="bold">AND</emph> one of the following:</p>
               <ulist>
                  <item>
                     <p>
									               <loc href="ARIA1" linktype="aria">ARIA1: Using Accessible Rich Internet Application describedby property to provide a descriptive, programmatically determined label</loc>
								             </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
                        <loc href="ARIA9" linktype="aria"/>
                     </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
                        <loc href="ARIA17"
                             linktype="aria"/>
                     </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
											             <loc href="G89"
                             linktype="general">G89: Providing expected data format and example</loc>
										           </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
											             <loc href="G184"
                             linktype="general">Providing text instructions at the beginning of a form or set of fields that describes the necessary input </loc>
										           </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
											             <loc href="G162"
                             linktype="general">Positioning labels to maximize predictability of relationships</loc>
										           </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
											             <loc href="G83"
                             linktype="general">G83: Providing text descriptions to identify required fields </loc>
										           </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
											             <loc href="H90" linktype="html">Indicating required form controls</loc>
										           </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
											             <loc href="FLASH10"
                             linktype="flash">Indicating required form controls in Flash</loc>
										           </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
                        <loc href="PDF5" linktype="pdf"/>
                     </p>
                  </item>
               </ulist>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="H44" linktype="html">H44: Using label elements to associate text labels with form controls</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="FLASH32"
                       linktype="flash">Using auto labeling to associate text labels with form controls</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="FLASH29"
                       linktype="flash">Setting the label property for form components</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="FLASH25"
                       linktype="flash">Labeling a form control by setting its accessible name</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc href="PDF10" linktype="pdf"/>
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc href="SL26"
                       linktype="silverlight"/>
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="H71" linktype="html">H71: Providing a description for groups of form controls using fieldset and legend elements</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="FLASH8"
                       linktype="flash">Adding a group name to the accessible name of a form control</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="H65" linktype="html">H65: Using the title attribute to identify form controls when the label element cannot be used</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc href="SL8"
                       linktype="silverlight"/>
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="G167"
                       linktype="general">Using adjacent button to label the purpose of a field</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
         </olist>
         <note>
            <p>The techniques at the end of the above list should be considered "last resort" and only used when the other techniques cannot be applied to the page. The earlier techniques are preferred because they increase accessibility to a wider user group.
              </p>
         </note>
      </div4>
      <div4 role="tech-optional">
         <head>Additional Techniques (Advisory) for 3.3.4</head>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="G13"
                       linktype="general">G13: Describing what will happen before a change to a form control is made</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc href="SL19"
                       linktype="silverlight"/>
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Providing linear form design and grouping similar items (future link)</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </div4>
      <div4 role="failures">
         <head>Common Failures Identified by the Working Group</head>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="F82"
                       linktype="failure">Failure of Success Criterion 3.3.2 by visually formating a set of phone number fields but not including a text label</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </div4>
   </div3>
</div2>
