<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE div2
  SYSTEM "../xmlspec.dtd">
<div2 id="navigation-mechanisms-location" role="extsrc">
   <head>2.4.8</head>
   <div3 role="intent">
      <head>Intent of this Success Criterion</head>
      <p>The intent of this Success Criterion is to provide a way for the user to orient herself within a set of Web pages, a Web site, or a Web application and find related information.</p>
      <div4 role="benefits">
         <head/>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>This Success Criterion is helpful for people with a short attention span who may become confused when following a long series of navigation steps to a Web page. It is also helpful when a user follows a link directly to a page deep within a set of Web pages and needs to navigate that Web site to understand the content of that page or to find more related information.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </div4>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="examples">
      <head/>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <emph role="bold">Links to help user determine their location in a site</emph>
							     </p>
            <p>A research group is part of an educational department at a university. The group's home page links to the department home page and the university's home page.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <emph role="bold">A breadcrumb trail</emph>
							     </p>
            <p>A portal Web site organizes topics into categories. As the user navigates through categories and subcategories, a breadcrumb trail shows the current location in the hierarchy of categories. Each page also contains a link to the portal home page.</p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="resources">
      <head/>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <loc href="http://www.standards-schmandards.com/2004/title-text-separators/">The Sound of the Accessible Title Tag Separator</loc>
							     </p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="techniques">
      <head>Techniques for Addressing Success Criterion 2.4.8</head>
      <div4 role="sufficient">
         <head/>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="G65"
                       linktype="general">Providing a breadcrumb trail</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="G63"
                       linktype="general">Providing a Site Map</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="G128"
                       linktype="general">Indicating current location within navigation bars</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item role="html">
               <p> 
                  <loc href="G127"
                       linktype="general">Identifying a Web page's relationship to a larger collection of Web pages</loc>
                       </p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </div4>
      <div4 role="tech-optional">
         <head>Additional Techniques (Advisory) for 2.4.7</head>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc href="PDF14" linktype="pdf"/>
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc href="PDF17" linktype="pdf"/>
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
        Providing a link to the home page or main page (future link)
    </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Providing an easy-to-read version of information about the organization of a set of Web pages (future link) 
                </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Providing a sign language version of information about the organization of a set of Web pages
 (future link) 
                </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Providing an easy-to-read summary at the beginning of each section of content (future link) 
                </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </div4>
      <div4 role="failures">
         <head>Common Failures Identified by the Working Group</head>
      </div4>
   </div3>
</div2>
