<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE div2
  SYSTEM "../xmlspec.dtd">
<div2 id="navigation-mechanisms-descriptive" role="extsrc">
   <head>2.4.6</head>
   <div3 role="intent">
      <head>Intent of this Success Criterion</head>
      <p>The intent of this Success Criterion is to help users understand what information is contained in Web pages and how that information is organized. When headings are clear and descriptive, users can find the information they seek more easily, and they can understand the relationships between different parts of the content more easily. Descriptive labels help users identify specific components within the content.</p>
      <p>Labels and headings do not need to be lengthy. A word, or even a single character, may suffice if it provides an appropriate cue to finding and navigating content.</p>
      <note>
         <p>This success criterion does not require headings or labels. This success criterion requires that if headings or labels are provided, they be descriptive. Also note that, if headings or labels are provided, they must meet <specref ref="content-structure-separation-programmatic"/>.</p>
      </note>
      <div4 role="benefits">
         <head/>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>Descriptive headings are especially helpful for users who have disabilities that make reading slow and for people with limited short-term memory. These people benefit when section titles make it possible to predict what each section contains.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>People who have difficulty using their hands or who experience pain when doing so will benefit from techniques that reduce the number of keystrokes required to reach the content they need.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>This Success Criterion helps people who use screen readers by ensuring that labels and headings are meaningful when read out of context, for example, in a Table of Contents, or when jumping from heading to heading within a page.</p>
               <p>This Success Criterion may also help users with low vision who can see only a few words at a time. 
                </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </div4>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="examples">
      <head/>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <emph role="bold">A news site.</emph>
							     </p>
            <p>The home page of a news site lists the headlines for the top stories of the hour. Under each heading are the first 35 words of the story and a link to the full article. Each headline gives a clear idea of the article's subject.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <emph role="bold">A guide on how to write well</emph>
							     </p>
            <p>A guide on writing contains the following section titles: How To Write Well,  Cut Out Useless Words,   Identify Unnecessary Words, etc.  The section headings are clear and concise and the structure of the information is reflected in the structure of the headings.
          </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <emph role="bold">Consistent headings in different articles</emph>
							     </p>
            <p>A Web site contains papers from a conference. Submissions to the conference are required to have the following organization: Summary, Introduction, [other sections unique to this article], Conclusion, Author Biography, Glossary, and Bibliography. The title of each Web page clearly identifies the article it contains, creating a useful balance between the uniqueness of the articles and the consistency of the section headings.
              </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <emph role="bold">A form asking the name of the user</emph>
							     </p>
            <p>A form asks the name of the user. It consists of two input fields to ask for the first and last name. The first field is labeled "First name", the second is labeled "Last name"."</p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="resources">
      <head/>
      <ulist><!-- MC: removed for broken link
            <item>
              <p>
                <loc href="http://www.usability.gov/methods/collecting_writing.html">Methods for Designing Usable Web Sites</loc> Methods for collecting, writing, and revising Web content to make it easy to use.</p>
            </item>
-->
         <item>
            <p> 
               <loc href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/how-users-read-on-the-web/">How Users Read on the Web</loc> A study showing that most users scan Web pages rather than reading them word by word.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p> 
               <loc href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/applying-writing-guidelines-web-pages/">Applying Writing Guidelines to Web Pages</loc> A report on the effects of making Web sites concise, easy to scan, and objective. </p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="techniques">
      <head>Techniques for Addressing Success Criterion 2.4.6</head>
      <div4 role="sufficient">
         <head/>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="G130"
                       linktype="general">Providing descriptive headings</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="G131"
                       linktype="general">Providing descriptive labels</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
         </olist>
         <note>
            <p>
                Headings and labels must be programmatically determined, per <loc href="content-structure-separation-programmatic"
                    linktype="guideline">Success Criterion 1.3.1
                </loc>.</p>
         </note>
      </div4>
      <div4 role="tech-optional">
         <head>Additional Techniques (Advisory) for 2.4.5</head>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>
        Using unique section headings in a Web Page (future link)
    </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
        Starting section headings with unique information (future link)
    </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </div4>
      <div4 role="failures">
         <head>Common Failures Identified by the Working Group</head>
      </div4>
   </div3>
</div2>
