<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE div2
  SYSTEM "../xmlspec.dtd">
<div2 id="navigation-mechanisms-refs" role="extsrc">
   <head>2.4.4</head>
   <div3 role="intent">
      <head>Intent of this Success Criterion</head>
      <p>The intent of this Success Criterion is to help users understand the purpose of each link so they can decide whether they want to follow the link. Whenever possible, provide link text that identifies the purpose of the link without needing additional context.
             Assistive technology has the ability to provide users with a list of links that are on the Web page. Link text that is as meaningful as possible will aid users who want to choose from this list of links. Meaningful link text also helps those who wish to tab from link to link. Meaningful links help users choose which links to follow without requiring complicated strategies to understand the page.</p>
      <p>The text of, or associated with, the link is intended to describe the purpose of the link. In cases where the link takes one to a document or a web application, the name of the document or web application would be sufficient to describe the purpose of the link (which is to take you to the document or web application). Note that it is not required to use the name of the document or web application; other things may also describe the purpose of the link. </p>
      <p>
         <loc href="navigation-mechanisms-title"
              linktype="understanding">Success Criterion 2.4.2</loc> deals with the titles of pages. Here also, the name of a document or web application being presented on the page would be sufficient to describe the purpose of the page. Having the link and the title agree, or be very similar, is good practice and provides continuity between the link 'clicked on' and the web page that the user lands on. </p>
      <p>In some situations, authors may want to provide part of the description of the link in logically related text that provides the context for the link. In this case the user should be able to identify the purpose of the link without moving focus from the link. In other words, they can arrive on a link and find out more about it without losing their place. This can be achieved by putting the description of the link in the same sentence, paragraph, list item, <phrase>or table cell as the link, or in the table header cell for a link in a data table</phrase>, because these are directly associated with the link itself. <phrase>Alternatively, authors may choose to use an ARIA technique to associate additional text on the page with the link.</phrase></p>
      <p>This context will be most usable if it precedes the link. (For instance, if you must use ambiguous link text, it is better to put it at the end of the sentence that describes its destination, rather than putting the ambiguous phrase at the beginning of the sentence.) If the description follows the link, there can be confusion and difficulty for screen reader users who are reading through the page in order (top to bottom).
          </p>
      <p>It is a best practice for links with the same destination to have consistent descriptions (and this is a requirement per <loc linktype="guideline"
              href="consistent-behavior-consistent-functionality">Success Criterion 3.2.4</loc> for pages in a set). It is also a best practice for links with different purposes and destinations to have different descriptions.</p>
      <p>The Success Criterion includes an exception for links for which the purpose of the link cannot be determined from the information on the Web page. In this situation, the person with the disability is not at a disadvantage; there is no additional context available to understand the link purpose. However, whatever amount of context is available on the Web page that can be used to interpret the purpose of the link must be made available in the link text or programmatically associated with the link to satisfy the Success Criterion.</p>
      <note>
         <p>There may be situations where the purpose of the link is is supposed to be unknown or obscured. For instance, a game may have links identified only as door #1, door #2, and door #3. This link text would be sufficient because the purpose of the links is to create suspense for all users.</p>
      </note>
      <p>See also <specref ref="navigation-mechanisms-link"/>.</p>
      <div4 role="benefits">
         <head/>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>This Success Criterion helps people with motion impairment by letting them skip links that they are not interested in, avoiding the keystrokes needed to visit the referenced content and then returning to the current content.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>People with cognitive limitations will not become disoriented by multiple means of navigation to and from content they are not interested in.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
                  People with visual disabilities will be able to determine the purpose of a link by exploring the link's context. 
                  
                </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </div4>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="examples">
      <head/>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <emph role="bold">A link contains text that gives a description of the information at that URI</emph>
							     </p>
            <p>
                A page contains the sentence "There was much bloodshed during the Medieval period of history." Where "Medieval period of history" is a link.
              </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <emph role="bold">A link is preceded by a text description of the information at that URI</emph>
							     </p>
            <p>
                A page contains the sentence "Learn more about the Government of Ireland's Commission on Electronic Voting at Go Vote!" where "Go Vote!" is a link.
              </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <emph role="bold">Both an icon and text are included in the same link</emph>
							     </p>
            <p>
                An icon of a voting machine and the text "Government of Ireland's Commission of Electronic Voting" are combined to make a single link. The alt text for the icon is null, since the purpose of the link is already described by the text of the link next to the icon.
              </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <emph role="bold">A list of book titles</emph>
							     </p>
            <p>
                A list of books is available in three formats: HTML, PDF, and mp3 (a recording of a person reading the book). To avoid hearing the title of each book three times (once for each format), the first link for each book is the title of the book, the second link says "PDF" and the third says, "mp3."
              </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <emph role="bold">News article summaries</emph>
							     </p>
            <p>
                A Web page contains a collection of news articles. The main page lists the first few sentences of each article, followed by a "Read more" link. A screen reader command to read the current paragraph provides the context to interpret the purpose of the link.
                
              </p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="resources">
      <head/>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <loc href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/using-link-titles-to-help-users-predict-where-they-are-going/">Using Link Titles to Help Users Predict Where They Are Going</loc>
							     </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <loc href="http://webaim.org/techniques/hypertext/">WebAIM Techniques for Hypertext Links</loc>
							     </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
            	<loc href="http://www.rnib.org.uk/blogs/expert-series?Name=Hidden%20barriers">Hidden barriers - out of sight</loc>
							     </p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="techniques">
      <head>Techniques for Addressing Success Criterion 2.4.4</head>
      <div4 role="sufficient">
         <head/>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="G91"
                       linktype="general">Providing link text that describes the purpose of a link</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="H30" linktype="html">Providing link text that describes the purpose of a link for anchor elements</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="H24" linktype="html">Providing a text alternative for the area element</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="FLASH27"
                       linktype="flash">Providing button labels that describe the purpose of a button</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Allowing the user to choose short or long link text using one of the techniques below:</p>
               <ulist>
                  <item>
                     <p>
											             <loc href="G189"
                             linktype="general">Providing a control near the beginning of the Web page that changes the link text</loc>
										           </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
											             <loc href="SCR30"
                             linktype="script">Using scripts to change the link text</loc>
										           </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
											             <loc href="FLASH7"
                             linktype="flash">Using scripting to change control labels</loc>
										           </p>
                  </item>
               </ulist>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="G53"
                       linktype="general">Identifying the purpose of a link using link text combined with the text of the enclosing sentence</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item role="htmlorcss">
               <p>Providing a supplemental description of the purpose of a link using one of the following techniques:</p>
               <ulist>
                  <item>
                     <p>
											             <loc href="H33" linktype="html">Supplementing link text with the title attribute</loc>
										           </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
											             <loc href="C7" linktype="css">Supplementing link text with hidden text</loc>
										           </p>
                  </item>
               </ulist>
            </item>
            <item role="html">
               <p>
                  Identifying the purpose of a link using link text combined with programmatically determined link context using one of the following techniques:
                </p>
               <ulist>
                  <item>
                     <p>
                        <loc href="ARIA7" linktype="aria"/>
                     </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
                        <loc href="ARIA8" linktype="aria"/>
                     </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
											             <loc href="H77" linktype="html"/>
										           </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
											             <loc href="H78" linktype="html"/>
										           </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
											             <loc href="H79" linktype="html"/>
										           </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
											             <loc href="H81" linktype="html">Identifying the purpose of a link in a nested list using link text combined with the list item that the list is nested beneath</loc>
										           </p>
                  </item>
               </ulist>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc href="G91"
                       linktype="general">Providing link text that describes the purpose of a link</loc> 
                  <emph role="bold">AND</emph> Semantically indicating links using one of the following techniques:</p>
               <ulist>
                  <item>
                     <p>
                        <loc href="PDF11" linktype="pdf"/>
                     </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
                        <loc href="PDF13" linktype="pdf"/>
                     </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
                        <loc href="SL18"
                             linktype="silverlight"/>
                     </p>
                  </item>
               </ulist>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </div4>
      <div4 role="tech-optional">
         <head>Additional Techniques (Advisory) for 2.4.4</head>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="H2" linktype="html">Combining adjacent image and text links for the same resource</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="FLASH5"
                       linktype="flash">Combining adjacent image and text buttons for the same resource</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="H80" linktype="html">Identifying the purpose of a link using link text combined with the preceding heading element</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </div4>
      <div4 role="failures">
         <head>Common Failures Identified by the Working Group</head>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="F63"
                       linktype="failure">Failure of 2.4.4 due to providing link context only in content that is not related to the link</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item role="html">
               <p>
									         <loc href="F89"
                       linktype="failure">Failure of 2.4.4 due to using null alt on an image where the image is the only content in a link</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </div4>
   </div3>
</div2>
