<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE div2
  SYSTEM "../xmlspec.dtd">
<div2 id="navigation-mechanisms-mult-loc" role="extsrc">
   <head>2.4.5</head>
   <div3 role="intent">
      <head>Intent of this Success Criterion</head>
      <p>The intent of this Success Criterion is to make it possible for users to locate content in a manner that best meets their needs. Users may find one technique easier or more comprehensible to use than another.</p>
      <p>Even small sites should provide users some means of orientation. For a three or four page site, with all pages linked from the home page, it may be sufficient simply to provide links from and to the home page where the links on the home page can also serve as a site map.</p>
      <div4 role="benefits">
         <head/>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>Providing an opportunity to navigate sites in more than one manner can help people find information faster. Users with visual impairments may find it easier to navigate to the correct part of the site by using a search, rather than scrolling through a large navigation bar using a screen magnifier or screen reader. A person with cognitive disabilities may prefer a table of contents or site map that provides an overview of the site rather than reading and traversing through several Web pages. Some users may prefer to explore the site in a sequential manner, moving from Web page to Web page in order to best understand the concepts and layout.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Individuals with cognitive limitations may find it easier to use search features than to use a hierarchical navigation scheme that may be difficult to understand.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </div4>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="examples">
      <head/>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <emph role="bold">A search mechanism.</emph>
							     </p>
            <p>A large food processing company provides a site containing recipes created using its products. The site provides a search mechanism to search for recipes using a particular ingredient. In addition, it provides a list box that lists several categories of foods. A user may type "soup" in to the search engine or may select "soup" from the list box to go to a page with a list of recipes made from the company's soup products</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <emph role="bold">Links between Web pages.</emph>
							     </p>
            <p>A local hair salon has created a Web site to promote its services. The site contains only five Web pages. There are links on each Web page to sequentially move forward or backward through the Web pages. In addition, each Web page contains a list of links to reach each of the other Web pages.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <emph role="bold">Where content is a result of a process or task - Funds transfer confirmation.</emph>
							     </p>
            <p>An on-line banking site allows fund transfer between accounts via the Web. There is no other way to locate the confirmation of fund transfer until the account owner completes the transfer.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <emph role="bold">Where content is a result of a process or task - Search engine results.</emph>
							     </p>
            <p>A search engine provides the search results based on user input. There is no other way to locate the search results except to perform the search process itself.</p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="resources">
      <head/>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="techniques">
      <head>Techniques for Addressing Success Criterion 2.4.5</head>
      <div4 role="sufficient">
         <head/>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Using two or more of the following techniques:</p>
               <ulist>
                  <item>
                     <p>
											             <loc href="G125"
                             linktype="general">Providing links to navigate to related Web pages</loc>
										           </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
											             <loc href="G64"
                             linktype="general">Providing a Table of Contents</loc>
										           </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
                        <loc href="PDF2" linktype="pdf"/>
                     </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
											             <loc href="G63"
                             linktype="general">Providing a Site Map</loc>
										           </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
											             <loc href="G161"
                             linktype="general">Providing a search function to help users find content</loc>
										           </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
											             <loc href="G126"
                             linktype="general">Providing a list of links to all other Web pages</loc>
										           </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
											             <loc href="G185"
                             linktype="general">Linking to all of the pages on the site from the home page</loc>
										           </p>
                  </item>
               </ulist>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </div4>
      <div4 role="tech-optional">
         <head>Additional Techniques (Advisory) for 2.4.2</head>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="H59" linktype="html">Using the link element and navigation tools</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
        Including information about presentation modes in tables of contents and concept maps (future link)
    </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </div4>
      <div4 role="failures">
         <head>Common Failures Identified by the Working Group</head>
      </div4>
   </div3>
</div2>
