<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE div2
  SYSTEM "../xmlspec.dtd">
<div2 role="extsrc" id="seizure-does-not-violate">
   <head>2.3.1</head>
   <div3 role="intent">
      <head>Intent of this Success Criterion</head>
      <p>The intent of this Success Criterion is to allow users to access the full content of a site without inducing seizures due to photosensitivity.</p>
      <p>Individuals who have photosensitive seizure disorders can have a seizure triggered by content that flashes at certain frequencies for more than a few flashes. People are even more sensitive to red flashing than to other colors, so a special test is provided for saturated red flashing. These guidelines are based on guidelines for the broadcasting industry as adapted for computer screens, where content is viewed from a closer distance (using a larger angle of vision).</p>
      <p>Flashing can be caused by the display, the computer rendering the image or by the content being rendered. The author has no control of the first two. They can be addressed by the design and speed of the display and computer. The intent of this criterion is to ensure that flicker that violates the flash thresholds is not caused by the content itself. For example, the content could contain a video clip or animated image of a series of strobe flashes, or close-ups of rapid-fire explosions.
          </p>
      <p>This Success Criterion replaces a much more restrictive criterion in WCAG 1.0 that did not allow any flashing (even of a single pixel) within a broad frequency range (3 to 50 Hz). This Success Criterion is based on existing specifications in use in the UK and by others for television broadcast and has been adapted for computer display viewing. The 1024 x 768 screen is used as the reference screen resolution for the evaluation. The 341 x 256 pixel block represents a 10 degree viewport at a typical viewing distance. (The 10 degree field is taken from the original specifications and represents the central vision portion of the eye, where people are most susceptible to photo stimuli.)</p>
      <p>The combined area of flashes occurring concurrently and contiguously means the total area that is actually flashing at the same time. It is calculated by adding up the contiguous area that is flashing simultaneously within any 10 degree angle of view.</p>
      <note>
         <p>The terms "blinking" and "flashing" can sometimes refer to the same content.</p>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>"Blinking" refers to content that causes a distraction problem. Blinking can be allowed for a short time as long as it stops (or can be stopped)</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>"Flashing" refers to content that can trigger a seizure (if it is more than 3 per second and large and bright enough). This cannot be allowed even for a second or it could cause a seizure. And turning the flash off is also not an option since the seizure could occur faster than most users could turn it off.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Blinking usually does not occur at speeds of 3 per second or more, but it can. If blinking occurs faster than 3 per second, it would also be considered a flash.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </note>
      <div4 role="benefits">
         <head>Benefits of this Success Criterion</head>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>Individuals who have seizures when viewing flashing material will be able to view all of the material on a site without having a seizure and without having to miss the full experience of the content by being limited to text alternatives. This includes people with photosensitive epilepsy as well as other photosensitive seizure disorders.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </div4>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="examples">
      <head>Examples for this Success Criterion</head>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>
                A Web site has video of muzzle flash of machine gun fire, but limits the size of the flashing image to a small portion of the screen below the flash threshold size.
                
              </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>A movie with a scene involving very bright lightning flashes is edited so that the lightning only flashes three times in any one second period. 
                
              </p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="resources">
      <head>Resources for this Success Criterion</head>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <loc href="http://www.hardingfpa.com/">Harding FPA Web Site</loc>
							     </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <loc href="https://trace.umd.edu/peat/">Trace Center Photosensitive Epilepsy Analysis Tool (PEAT)</loc>
							     </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <loc href="https://trace.umd.edu/information-about-photosensitive-seizure-disorders/">Information about Photosensitive Seizure Disorders</loc>
							     </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <loc href="https://www.epilepsy.org.uk/">Epilepsy Action</loc>
							     </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
            	<loc href="http://www.epilepsy.com/learn/triggers-seizures/photosensitivity-and-seizures">Epilepsy Foundation</loc>
							     </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <loc href="http://www.ofcom.org.uk/static/archive/itc/itc_publications/codes_guidance/flashing_images/index.asp.html">ITC Guidance Note for Licensees on Flashing Images and Regular Patterns in Television</loc>
							     </p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="techniques">
      <head>Techniques for Addressing Success Criterion 2.3.1</head>
      <div4 role="sufficient">
         <head/>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="G19"
                       linktype="general">Ensuring that no component of the content flashes more than three times in any one second period</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="G176"
                       linktype="general">Keeping the flashing area small enough</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="G15"
                       linktype="general">Using a tool to ensure that content does not violate the general flash threshold or red flash threshold</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </div4>
      <div4 role="tech-optional">
         <head>Additional Techniques (Advisory) for 2.3.1</head>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>Reducing contrast for any flashing content (future link)    </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Avoiding fully saturated reds for any flashing content (future link)    </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Reducing the number of flashes even if they do not violate thresholds (future link)    </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Providing a mechanism to suppress any flashing content before it begins (future link) 
                </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Slowing down live material to avoid rapid flashes (as in flashbulbs) (future link)</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Freezing the image momentarily if 3 flashes within one second are detected (future link)</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Dropping the contrast ratio if 3 flashes within one second are detected (future link)</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Allowing users to set a custom flash rate limit (future link)</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </div4>
      <div4 role="failures">
         <head/>
      </div4>
   </div3>
</div2>
