<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE div2
  SYSTEM "../xmlspec.dtd">
<div2 role="extsrc" id="time-limits-no-exceptions">
   <head>2.2.3</head>
   <div3 role="intent">
      <head>Intent of this Success Criterion</head>
      <p>The intent of this Success Criterion is to minimize the occurrence of content that requires timed interaction. This enables people with blindness, low vision, cognitive limitations, or motor impairments to interact with content. This differs from the Level A Success Criterion in that the only exception is for real-time events.</p>
      <note>
         <p>Video only, such as sign language, is covered in <loc href="text-equiv"
                 linktype="guideline">Guideline 1.1</loc>.
            </p>
      </note>
      <div4 role="benefits">
         <head>Benefits of this Success Criterion</head>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>People with physical disabilities often need more time to react, to type and to complete activities.  People with low vision need more time to locate things on screen and to read.   People who are blind and using screen readers may need more time to understand screen layouts, to find information and to operate controls.  People who have cognitive or language limitations need more time to read and to understand.  People who are deaf and communicate in sign language may need more time to read information printed in text (which may be a second language for some).</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>In circumstances where a sign-language interpreter may be relating audio content to a user who is deaf, control over time limits is also important.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </div4>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="examples">
      <head>Examples for this Success Criterion</head>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <emph role="bold">A test is designed so that time to complete the test does not affect the scoring</emph>
							     </p>
            <p>Rather than calibrating an on-line test using a time limit, the test is calibrated based on scores when users have no time limits.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <emph role="bold">A game is designed so that users take turns rather than competing in real-time</emph>
							     </p>
            <p>One party can pause the game without invalidating the competitive aspect of it.</p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="resources">
      <head>Resources for this Success Criterion </head>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="techniques">
      <head>Techniques for Addressing Success Criterion 2.2.4</head>
      <div4 role="sufficient">
         <head/>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="G5" linktype="general">Allowing users to complete an activity without any time limit</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </div4>
      <div4 role="tech-optional">
         <head>Additional Techniques (Advisory) for 2.2.4</head>
      </div4>
      <div4 role="failures">
         <head>Common Failures Identified by the Working Group</head>
      </div4>
   </div3>
</div2>
