<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE div2
  SYSTEM "../xmlspec.dtd">
<div2 role="extsrc" id="time-limits-postponed">
   <head>2.2.4</head>
   <div3 role="intent">
      <head>Intent of this Success Criterion</head>
      <p>The intent of this Success Criterion is to allow users to turn off updates from the author/server except in emergencies. Emergencies would include civil emergency alert messages or any other messages that warn of danger to health, safety, or property, including data loss, loss of connection, etcetera.</p>
      <p>This allows access by people with cognitive limitations or attention disorders by enabling them to focus on the content. It also allows users who are blind or have low vision to keep their "viewing" focus on the content they are currently reading.</p>
      <div4 role="benefits">
         <head>Benefits of this Success Criterion</head>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>Individuals with attention deficit disorders can focus on content without distraction.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Individuals with low vision or who use screen readers will not have content updated while they are viewing it (which can lead to discontinuity and misunderstanding if they start reading in one topic and finish in another).</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </div4>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="examples">
      <head>Examples for this Success Criterion</head>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>
								       <emph role="bold">Example 1. Setting user preferences</emph>
							     </p>
            <p>The preferences page of a Web portal includes an option to postpone all updates and alerts until the end of the current session, except for alerts concerning emergencies. </p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="resources">
      <head>Resources for this Success Criterion </head>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="techniques">
      <head>Techniques for Addressing Success Criterion 2.2.5</head>
      <div4 role="sufficient">
         <head/>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="G75"
                       linktype="general">Providing a mechanism to postpone any updating of content</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="G76"
                       linktype="general">G76: Providing a mechanism to request an update of the content instead of updating automatically</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="SCR14"
                       linktype="script">Using scripts to make non-essential alerts optional</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </div4>
      <div4 role="tech-optional">
         <head>Additional Techniques (Advisory) for 2.2.5</head>
      </div4>
      <div4 role="failures">
         <head>Common Failures Identified by the Working Group</head>
         <ulist>
            <item role="html">
               <p>
									         <loc href="F40"
                       linktype="failure">Failure due to using meta redirect with a time limit
                  </loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item role="html">
               <p>
									         <loc href="F41"
                       linktype="failure">Failure due to using meta refresh with a time limit
                  </loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </div4>
   </div3>
</div2>
