<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE div2
  SYSTEM "../xmlspec.dtd">
<div2 id="visual-audio-contrast-dis-audio" role="extsrc">
   <head>1.4.2</head>
   <div3 role="intent">
      <head>Intent of this Success Criterion</head>
      <p>Individuals who use screen reading software can find it hard to hear the speech output if there is other audio playing at the same time. This difficulty is exacerbated when the screen reader's speech output is software based (as most are today) and is controlled via the same volume control as the sound. Therefore, it is important that the user be able to turn off the background sound. Note: Having control of the volume includes being able to reduce its volume to zero.</p>
      <note>
         <p>Playing audio automatically when landing on a page may affect a screen reader user's ability to find the mechanism to stop it because they navigate by listening and automatically started sounds might interfere with that navigation. Therefore, we discourage the practice of automatically starting sounds (especially if they last more than 3 seconds), and encourage that the sound be <emph>started</emph> by an action initiated by the user after they reach the page, rather than requiring that the sound be <emph>stopped</emph> by an action of the user after they land on the page.</p>
      </note>
      <p>See also <specref ref="visual-audio-contrast-noaudio"/>.</p>
      <div4 role="benefits">
         <head/>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>Individuals who use screen reading technologies can hear the screen reader without other sounds playing. This is especially important for those who are hard of hearing and for those whose screen readers use the system volume (so they cannot turn sound down and screen reader up).</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>This Success Criterion also benefits people who have difficulty focusing on visual content (including text) when audio is playing.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </div4>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="examples">
      <head/>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>An audio file begins playing automatically when a page is opened. However, the audio can be stopped by the user by selecting a "silent" link at the top of the page.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
                A Flash splash page with sound that plays and then stops in less than 3 seconds.
 
                
              </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
                A Flash splash page with sound that plays automatically includes a control at the top that allows users to turn the sound off. 
                
              </p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="resources">
      <head/>
   </div3>
   <div3 role="techniques">
      <head>Techniques for Addressing Success Criterion 1.4.2</head>
      <div4 role="sufficient">
         <head/>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="G60"
                       linktype="general">Playing a sound that turns off automatically within three seconds</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="G170"
                       linktype="general">Providing a control near the top of the Web page that turns off sounds that play automatically</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="G171"
                       linktype="general">Playing sounds only on user request</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc href="SL24"
                       linktype="silverlight"/>
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="FLASH18"
                       linktype="flash">Providing a control to turn off sounds that play automatically in Flash</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="FLASH34"
                       linktype="flash">Using screen reader detection to turn off sounds that play automatically</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc href="SL3"
                       linktype="silverlight"/>
               </p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </div4>
      <div4 role="tech-optional">
         <head>Additional Techniques (Advisory) for 1.4.2</head>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>
        Providing a site-wide preference to turn off audio in addition to providing a control near the top of the Web page that turns off sounds that play automatically (future link)
    </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </div4>
      <div4 role="failures">
         <head>Common Failures Identified by the Working Group</head>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc href="F23"
                       linktype="failure">Failure due to playing a sound longer than 3 seconds where there is no mechanism to turn it off</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
				    <loc href="F93" linktype="failure"/>
               </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </div4>
   </div3>
</div2>
