<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="H2">
   <short-name>Combining adjacent image and text links for the same resource</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>HTML and XHTML documents that contain links.</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="text-equiv-all" relationship="sufficient"/>
      <success-criterion idref="navigation-mechanisms-refs" relationship="sufficient"/>
      <success-criterion idref="navigation-mechanisms-link" relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to avoid unnecessary duplication that occurs when
            adjacent text and iconic versions of a link are contained in a document. </p>
      <p>Many kinds of links have both a text and iconic link adjacent to each other. Often the
            text and the icon link are rendered in separate links, in part to create a slight visual
            separation from each other. Visually they appear to be the same link, but they are
            experienced by many people as two identical links and this can be confusing. To avoid
            this, some authors omit alternative text from the image, but this would fail <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
              href="text-equiv-all"
              linktype="guideline">Success Criterion 1.1.1</loc> because the
            text alternative would not serve the same purpose as the graphical link. The preferred
            method to address this is to put the text and image together in one link, and provide
            null alternative text on the image to eliminate duplication of text. </p>
      <p>Sometimes the text and the icon link are rendered in separate, adjacent table cells to
            facilitate page layout. Although WCAG 2 does not prohibit the use of layout tables,
            CSS-based layouts are recommended in order to retain the defined semantic meaning of the
            HTML table elements and to conform to the coding practice of separating presentation
            from content. If CSS is used, this technique can be applied to combine the links. </p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <description>
            <p>The icon and text are contained in the same <el>a</el> element.</p>
         </description>
         <code role="html401"><![CDATA[ <a href="products.html">
   <img src="icon.gif" alt="" />
   Products page
 </a>      ]]></code>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <description>
            <p>A link contains an icon and text, and the site help refers to the icon. The
                  <el>img</el> has a text alternative which is the name used for the icon in the
                site help, which describes clicking the home page icon.</p>
         </description>
         <code role="html401"><![CDATA[<a href="foo.htm">
  <img src="house.gif" alt="home page icon"/>
  Go to the home page
</a>     ]]></code>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group role="failure">
         <description>
            <p>This example demonstrates a failure to apply this technique. An icon and text link
                are side by side. The text alternative for the image is the same as the text link
                beside it, leading to a "stutter" effect as the link is read twice.</p>
         </description>
         <code role="html401"><![CDATA[<a href="products.html">
   <img src="icon.gif" alt="Products page" />
 </a>
 <a href="products.html">
   Products page
 </a>  ]]></code>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group role="failure">
         <description>
            <p>This example demonstrates a failure to apply this technique. An icon and text link
                are side by side. In an attempt to remove the "stutter" the text alternative for the
                image is null. However, now one of the links has an unknown destination, which is
                its own link text problem.</p>
         </description>
         <code role="html401"><![CDATA[<a href="products.html">
   <img src="icon.gif" alt="" />
 </a>
 <a href="products.html">
   Products page
 </a>     ]]></code>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group role="failure">
         <description>
            <p>This example demonstrates an incorrect implementation of this technique. The icon
                and text are contained in the same a element. However, the text alternative for the
                icon is a duplicate of the link text, leading to a "stutter" effect as the
                description is read twice. </p>
         </description>
         <code role="html401"><![CDATA[<a href="products.html">
  <img src="products.gif" alt="Products page"/>
  Products page
</a>    
            ]]></code>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.w3.org/TR/html401/struct/objects.html#h-13.8">HTML 4.01 -
                    how to specify alt text</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </see-also>
   </resources>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="G91"/>
      <relatedtech idref="G94"/>
      <relatedtech idref="H30"/>
      <relatedtech idref="C9"/>
      <relatedtech idref="F89"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <p>For each <el>a</el> applying this technique:</p>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Check that every <el>img</el> element contained within the <el>a</el> element has a null value set for its <att>alt</att> attribute.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Check that the <el>a</el> element contains text that is a description of the image</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
         <p>For each <el>a</el> in the content that is contained in a table: </p>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>All checks above are true.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
