<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="H24">
   <short-name> Providing text alternatives for the <el>area</el> elements of image maps </short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>HTML and XHTML Documents that contain <el>area</el> elements.</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="text-equiv-all" relationship="sufficient"/>
      <success-criterion idref="navigation-mechanisms-refs" relationship="sufficient"/>
      <success-criterion idref="navigation-mechanisms-link" relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <ua-issues>
      <ua-issue name="" version="">
         <p>The HTML 4.01 specification explains that the text of the <att>alt</att> attribute
              is to be displayed when the element cannot be rendered normally. User Agents will
              display the <att>alt</att> attribute text when images are not displayed. However,
              currently, visual User Agents do not display the <att>alt</att> attribute text for area elements
              of image maps when accessed by keyboard or when images are not displayed, and may clip
              the area elements if the intrinsic size of the image is not used. In addition, the
              display of <att>alt</att> attribute text in response to mouse-hover does not display in the font
              size or color combination set in the User Agent. </p>
         <p>The <att>title</att> attribute is meant to provide additional information. However,
              current implementation in User Agents is access to either the title or <att>alt</att> attribute,
              but not both. User Agents generally will display the <att>title</att> attribute text
              when the mouse is placed over the element containing the <att>title</att> attribute.
              </p>
         <p>Therefore, when using image maps, successful implementation of this technique would
              require either:</p>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>Ensuring the area element <att>alt</att> attribute value is displayed in response to
                  attaining focus (including keyboard focus), and that this applies both to
                  situations where images are loaded and not loaded. OR</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>A redundant mechanism serving the same purpose as the area elements is present in
                  the Web Page.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </ua-issue>
   </ua-issues>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to provide text alternatives that serve the same
            purpose as the selectable regions of an image map. An image map is an image divided into
            selectable regions defined by <el>area</el> elements. Each area is a link to another
            Web page or another part of the current Web page. The <att>alt</att> attribute of each
              <el>area</el> element serves the same purpose as the selectable area of the
          image.</p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <description>
            <p>This example uses the <att>alt</att> attribute of the <el>area</el> element
                to provide text that describes the purpose of the image map areas.</p>
         </description>
         <code role="html401"><![CDATA[<img src="welcome.gif" usemap="#map1" 
    alt="Areas in the library. Select an area for
more information on that area." /> 
<map id="map1" name="map1">
  <area shape="rect" coords="0,0,30,30"
    href="reference.html" alt="Reference" />
  <area shape="rect" coords="34,34,100,100"
    href="media.html" alt="Audio visual lab" />
</map>   ]]></code>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.w3.org/TR/html401/struct/objects.html#h-13.6.1">HTML 4.01
                    client-side image maps</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.w3.org/TR/html401/struct/objects.html#h-13.8">HTML 4.01 -
                    how to specify alt text</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </see-also>
   </resources>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="G91"/>
      <relatedtech idref="H30"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <p>For each <el>area</el> element in an image map: </p>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Check that the <el>area</el> element has an <att>alt</att> attribute.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Check that the text alternative specified by the <att>alt</att> attribute serves the same
                  purpose as the part of image map image referenced by the <el>area</el> element
                  of the imagemap.</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>The above checks are true.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
