<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="H28">
   <short-name>Providing definitions for abbreviations by using the abbr element</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>HTML and XHTML</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="meaning-located" relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <ua-issues>
      <ua-issue name="" version="">
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>Assistive technologies provide different levels of support for speaking abbreviations and acronyms, often dependent upon specific customization settings. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>This technique is only sufficient if the <el>abbr</el> element's <att>title</att> attribute is accessibility supported. The content of the <att>title</att> attribute needs to be available to all keyboard users (not only those with text-to-speech software) for this attribute to be accessibility  supported.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>JAWS 6.2 and higher and WindowEyes 5.0 and higher support the abbr elements. They can all be set to speak the title attribute when these elements are encountered, but this is not the default setting and is often not turned on by users. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Many graphical user agents render text enclosed within an <el>abbr</el> element with a dotted line below or surrounding it. In addition, when the mouse hovers over the element, the expansion is displayed as a tool tip.
                      </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>In Internet Explorer 7 and below, items marked using the <el>abbr</el> element are not displayed with any additional formatting. For IE 6 and below, the expanded version does not display as a tooltip when the mouse hovers over the item. </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </ua-issue>
   </ua-issues>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to provide expansions or definitions for
            abbreviations by using the <el>abbr</el> element</p>
      <p>It is always appropriate to use the <el>abbr</el> element for any abbreviation,
            including acronyms and initialisms. When using HTML 4 and XHTML,
            initialisms and acronyms may be marked up using the <el>acronym</el> element. 
          	In HTML5 and newer versions of HTML the <el>acronym</el> element was marked as obsolete in favor of the more general
              <el>abbr</el> element.</p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <head> Using <el>abbr</el> element to expand abbreviations. </head>
         <code role="html401"><![CDATA[<p>Sugar is commonly sold in 5 <abbr title="pound">lb.</abbr> bags.</p>
<p>Welcome to the <abbr title="World Wide Web">WWW</abbr>!</p>              ]]></code>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <head> Using <el>abbr</el> element to define abbreviations. </head>
         <code role="html401"><![CDATA[<p>Tasini <abbr title="and others">et al.</abbr> <abbr title="versus">v.</abbr>
The New York Times <abbr title="and others">et al.</abbr> is the landmark lawsuit 
brought by members of the National Writers Union against ......</p>  ]]></code>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <head> Using the <el>abbr</el> element to expand an acronym </head>
         <code role="html401"><![CDATA[ <p>The use of <abbr title="Keep It Simple Stupid">KISS</abbr> became popular in ...</p>        
            ]]></code>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <head> Using the <el>abbr</el> element to expand an initialism </head>
         <code role="html401"><![CDATA[ <p><abbr title="World Wide Web">WWW</abbr></p>]]></code>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.w3.org/TR/html401/struct/text.html#edef-ABBR">HTML 4.01 ABBR
                    element</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="https://www.w3.org/TR/html5/textlevel-semantics.html#the-abbr-element">HTMl5 abbr
                    element</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                  	href="https://www.paciellogroup.com/blog/2010/11/using-the-html-title-attribute/">HTML title attribute</loc>
               </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </see-also>
   </resources>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="G102"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Check that an expansion or definition is provided for each abbreviation via
                    <el>abbr</el>. </p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>Check #1 is true.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
