<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="H33">
   <short-name>Supplementing link text with the title attribute</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>HTML and XHTML</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="navigation-mechanisms-refs" relationship="sufficient"/>
      <success-criterion idref="navigation-mechanisms-link" relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <ua-issues>
      <ua-issue name="" version="">
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p> Current user agents and assistive technology provide no feedback to the user
                  when links have <att>title</att> attribute content available. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Some graphical user agents will display a tool tip when the mouse hovers above
                  an anchor element containing a <att>title</att> attribute. However, current user
                  agents do not provide access to <att>title</att> attribute content via the
                  keyboard. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> The tool tip in some common user agents disappears after a short period of time
                  (approximately 5 seconds). This can cause difficulty accessing <att>title</att>
                  attribute content for those users who can use a mouse but have fine motor skill
                  impairment, and may result in difficulties for users who need more time to read
                  the tool tip. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Current graphical user agents do not provide mechanisms to control the
                  presentation of <att>title</att> attribute content. The user cannot resize the
                  tool tip text or control the foreground and background colors. The placement and
                  location of the tool tip cannot be controlled by users, causing some screen
                  magnifier users to be unable to access meaningful portions of the
                  <att>title</att> attribute content because the tool tip cannot be fully
                  displayed within the viewport. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Some user agents allow access to supplementary information through the context
                  menu. For example, the keystroke combination Shift+F10 followed by P will display
                  the <att>title</att> attribute content, along with other supplementary
                  information in Mozilla/Firefox. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>The HTML 4.01 specification explains that the text of the <att>alt</att>
                  attribute is to be displayed when the element cannot be rendered normally. Thus,
                  visual User Agents will display the <att>alt</att> attribute text when images
                  are not displayed. The <att>title</att> attribute is meant to provide additional
                  information. User Agents generally will display the <att>title</att> attribute
                  text when the mouse is placed over the element containing the <att>title</att>
                  attribute. Internet Explorer will display the <att>alt</att> text on mouse-over
                  if there is no <att>title</att> text. The Firefox and Opera browsers only
                  display the <att>title</att> text on mouse-over and do not use the
                  <att>alt</att> attribute text for this purpose. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Assistive technologies provide different levels of support for speaking title attributes. Some do not include features that allow users to access information provided via the title attribute.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>JAWS 7.0 and above will speak the value of title attributes depending upon a JAWS setting. This setting can be changed temporarily or permanently within JAWS.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>WindowEyes 5.5 and above has a hot key, ins-E, that will speak additional information, including the title attribute, for the item with focus. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Implementing this technique with the <att>title</att> attribute is only sufficient if the <att>title</att> attribute is accessibility supported. If the value of the <att>title</att> is essential to understanding the purpose of the link for all users, then the content of this attribute needs to be available to all keyboard users (not only those with text-to-speech software) for this technique to be accessibility supported.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </ua-issue>
   </ua-issues>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to demonstrate how to use a <att>title</att>
            attribute on an anchor element to provide additional text describing a link. The
              <att>title</att> attribute is used to provide additional information to help clarify
            or further describe the purpose of a link. If the supplementary information provided
            through the <att>title</att> attribute is something the user should know before
            following the link, such as a warning, then it should be provided in the link text
            rather than in the <att>title</att> attribute. </p>
      <p>Because of the extensive user agent limitations in supporting access to the title attribute, authors should use caution in applying this technique. For this reason, it is preferred that the author use technique <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" href="C7" linktype="css">C7: Using CSS to hide a portion of the link text</loc> or <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
              href="H30"
              linktype="techniques">H30: Providing link text that describes the purpose of a link for anchor elements</loc>.</p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Clarifying the purpose of a link</head>
         <code role="html401"><![CDATA[<a href="http://example.com/WORLD/africa/kenya.elephants.ap/index.html" 
   title="Read more about failed elephant evacuation">
   Evacuation Crumbles Under Jumbo load
</a>]]></code>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.brothercake.com/site/resources/scripts/tooltips/">Displaying tooltips when elements receive focus</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </see-also>
   </resources>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="C7"/>
      <relatedtech idref="H30"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <p>Examine the source code for anchor elements. </p>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>For each anchor element that has a <att>title</att> attribute, check that the
                    <att>title</att> attribute together with the link text describes the purpose
                  of the link.</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>Check #1 is true.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
