<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="H35">
   <short-name> Providing text alternatives on <el>applet</el> elements </short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p> HTML and XHTML Documents that load Java applets where <el>applet</el> is not deprecated.
          </p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="text-equiv-all" relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <ua-issues>
      <ua-issue name="" version="">
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>This technique is not supported well by assistive technologies. The HTML specification explains that text alternatives for applets are to be displayed when the element cannot be rendered. Therefore, text alternatives that are included in the body of <el>applet</el> elements may not be available to users unless the user agent either does not support or has been configured not to render applets. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>IE 6 for Windows and Firefox 1.5 and Opera 9 on Windows treat alternative text for the applet element differently. IE will display the body text of the applet element and not the <att>alt</att> attribute. Firefox and Opera will display the <att>alt</att> attribute but not the body text. </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </ua-issue>
   </ua-issues>
   <description>
      <p> Provide a text alternative for an applet by using the <att>alt</att> attribute to label an applet
            and providing the text alternative in the body of the applet element. In this technique, both mechanisms
            are required due to the varying support of the <att>alt</att> attribute and applet body text by
            user agents. </p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <head>An applet to play the tic-tac-toe game. </head>
         <code><![CDATA[<applet code="tictactoe.class" width="250" height="250" alt="tic-tac-toe game">
   tic-tac-toe game
</applet>  ]]></code>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="G94"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p> View the source code of the applet element </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Check that the applet element contains an <att>alt</att> attribute with a text alternative
                  for the applet </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Check that the applet element contains a text alternative for the applet in the
                  body of the applet element </p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p> Checks #2 and #3 are true. </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
