<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="H39">
   <short-name>Using caption elements to associate data table captions with data tables</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>HTML and XHTML data tables </p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="content-structure-separation-programmatic"
                         relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to programmatically associate captions for data
            tables where captions are provided in the presentation. The caption for a table is a
            table identifier and acts like a title or heading for the table. </p>
      <p>The <el>caption</el> element is the appropriate markup for such text and it ensures
            that the table identifier remains associated with the table, including visually (by
            default). In addition, using the <el>caption</el> element allows screen reading software
            to navigate directly to the caption for a table if one is present.</p>
      <p>The <el>caption</el> element may be used whether or not the table includes a
              <att>summary</att> attribute. The <el>caption</el> element identifies the table
            whereas the <att>summary</att> attribute gives an overview of the purpose or explains
            how to navigate the table. If both are used, the <el>caption</el> should not duplicate
            information in the <att>summary</att>.</p>
      <p>Although WCAG 2.0 does not prohibit the use of layout tables, CSS-based layouts are
            recommended in order to retain the defined semantic meaning of the HTML and XHTML
            <el>table</el> elements and to conform to the coding practice of separating
            presentation from content. If a table is used for layout, the <el>caption</el> element
            is not used. The purpose of a layout table is simply to control the placement of
            content; the table itself is “transparent" to the user. A <el>caption</el> would "break"
            this transparency by calling attention to the table. </p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <head>An appointment calendar with a <el>caption</el>
						   </head>
         <code role="html401"><![CDATA[<table>
<caption>Schedule for the week of March 6</caption>
...</table> ]]></code>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>HTML 4.01 <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.w3.org/TR/html4/struct/tables.html#h-11.2.2">Table Captions: The CAPTION element</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </see-also>
   </resources>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="H43"/>
      <relatedtech idref="H63"/>
      <relatedtech idref="H73"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Check for layout tables: determine whether the content has a relationship with
                  other content in both its column and its row. </p>
               <olist>
                  <item>
                     <p>If “no," the table is a layout table.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>If “yes," the table is a data table.</p>
                  </item>
               </olist>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>If the table is a layout table, check that the table does not include a
                    <el>caption</el> element.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>If the table is a data table and it includes a <el>caption</el> element, check
                  that the <el>caption</el> identifies the table</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>If both a <att>summary</att> attribute and a <el>caption</el> element are present
                  for this data table, check that the <att>summary</att> does not duplicate the
                    <el>caption</el>.</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>For layout tables, #2 is true.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>For data tables, #3 and #4 are true.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
