<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="H4">
   <short-name>Creating a logical tab order through links, form controls, and objects</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>HTML and XHTML</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="navigation-mechanisms-focus-order" relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to provide a logical tab order when the default tab
            order does not suffice. Often, <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
              href="G59"
              linktype="general">placing the
              interactive elements in an order that follows sequences and relationships within the
              content</loc> is sufficient and this technique is not necessary. It can be very easy
            to introduce usability bugs when setting the tab order explicitly.</p>
      <p>In some cases, the author may want to specify a tab order that follows relationships in
            the content without following the order of the interactive elements in the code. In
            these cases, an alternative order can be specified using the <att>tabindex</att>
            attribute of the interactive element. The <att>tabindex</att> is given a value between
            0 and 32767. </p>
      <p>When the interactive elements are navigated using the tab key, the elements are given
            focus in increasing order of the value of their <att>tabindex</att> attribute.
            Elements that have a <att>tabindex</att> value higher than zero will receive focus
            before elements without a <att>tabindex</att> or a <att>tabindex</att> of 0. After
            all of the elements with a tabindex higher than 0 have received focus, the rest of the
            interactive elements are given focus in the order in which they appear in the Web
          page.</p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <description>
            <p>A genealogical search form searches for marriage records. The search form includes
                several input fields for the bride and the groom. The form is marked up using a data
                table that includes the fields of the groom in the first column and the fields of
                the bride in the second column. The order in the content is row by row but the
                author feels it is more logical to navigate the form column by column. This way, all
                the groom's criteria can be filled in before moving on to the bride's criteria. The
                  <att>tabindex</att> attributes of the input fields are used to specify a tab
                order that navigates column by column.</p>
         </description>
         <code role="html401"><![CDATA[<form action="#" method="post">
 <table summary="the first column contains the search criteria 
  of the groom, the second column the search criteria of 
  of the bride">
 <caption>Search for marriage records</caption>
 <tr>
   <th>Search criteria</th>
   <th>Groom</th>
   <th>Bride</th>
 </tr>
 <tr>
  <th>First name</th>
  <td><input type="text" size="30" value="" name="groomfirst" 
      title="First name of the groom" tabindex="1"></td>
  <td><input type="text" size="30" value="" name="bridefirst" 
       title="First name of the bride" tabindex="4"></td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
  <th>Last name</th>
  <td><input type="text" size="30" value="" name="groomlast" 
      title="Last name of the groom" tabindex="2"></td>
  <td><input type="text" size="30" value="" name="bridelast" 
      title="Last name of the bride" tabindex="5"></td>
 </tr>
 <tr>
  <th>Place of birth</th>
  <td><input type="text" size="30" value="" name="groombirth" 
      title="Place of birth of the groom" tabindex="3"></td>
  <td><input type="text" size="30" value="" name="bridebirth" 
      title="Place of birth of the bride" tabindex="6"></td>
 </tr>
</table>
</form>      ]]></code>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <description>
            <p>A Web page contains a search field in the upper right corner. The field is given
                tabindex="1" so that it will occur first in the tab order, even though it is not
                first in the content order.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <description>
            <p>
								       <att>Tabindex</att> values need not be sequential nor must they begin with any
                particular value. The values do not have to be unique. Elements that have identical
                  <att>tabindex</att> values are navigated in the order they appear in the
                character stream. </p>
         </description>
         <description>
            <p>In sections of the content where the tab order follows the content order, it can be
                less error prone to give all elements the same tabindex value rather than specifying
                a different number for each element. Then it is easy to rearrange those elements or
                add new elements and maintain a logical tab order.</p>
         </description>
         <code role="html401"><![CDATA[ <a href="xxx" tabindex = "1">First link in list</a>
<a href="xxx" tabindex = "1">Second link in list</a>
<a href="xxx" tabindex = "1">Link that was added long 
  after the original list was created</a>
<a href="xxx" tabindex = "1">Third link in list</a>
  ...
<a href="xxx" tabindex = "1">Twentieth link in list</a>      ]]></code>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.w3.org/TR/html4/interact/forms.html#adef-tabindex">Tabbing
                    navigation in the HTML 4.01 specification</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </see-also>
   </resources>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="G59"/>
      <relatedtech idref="F44"/>
      <relatedtech idref="F85"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Check if <att>tabindex</att> is used</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>If <att>tabindex</att> is used, check that the tab order specified by the
                    <att>tabindex</att> attributes follows relationships in the content.</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>Check #2 is true.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
