<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="H40">
   <short-name>Using description lists</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>HTML and XHTML</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="meaning-idioms" relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to provide the description of names or terms by
            presenting them in a description list. The list is marked up using the <el>dl</el>
            element. Within the list, each term is put in a separate <el>dt</el> element, and
            its description goes in the <el>dd</el> element directly following it. Multiple terms can be associated with a single description, as can a single term with multiple descriptions, provided that semantic sequence is maintained. The
              <att>title</att> attribute can be used to provide additional information about the
            description list. Usage of description lists ensures that terms and their descriptions are semantically related even as presentation format changes, as well as ensuring that these terms and descriptions are semantically grouped as a unit.</p>
      <p>Description lists are easiest to use when the descriptions are ordered alphabetically. A common use for description lists is a glossary of terms.</p>
      <note><p>In HTML5 the name "Description list" was introduced. In previous versions these lists were referred to as "Definition lists".</p></note>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <description>
            <p>A list of descriptions of nautical terms used on a Website about sailing.</p>
         </description>
         <code role="html401"><![CDATA[<dl title="Nautical terms">
  <dt>Knot</dt>
  <dd>
    <p>A <em>knot</em> is a unit of speed equaling 1 
      nautical mile per hour (1.15 miles per hour or 1.852 
      kilometers per hour).</p>
  </dd>
  <dt>Port</dt>
  <dd>
    <p><em>Port</em> is the nautical term (used on 
      boats and ships) that refers to the left side
      of a ship, as perceived by a person facing towards 
      the bow (the front of the vessel).</p>
  </dd>
  <dt>Starboard</dt>
  <dd>
    <p><em>Starboard</em> is the nautical term (used 
      on boats and ships) that refers to the right 
      side of a vessel, as perceived by a person 
      facing towards the bow (the front of the vessel).</p>
  </dd>
</dl>        ]]></code>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also>
        <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="https://www.w3.org/TR/html5/grouping-content.html#the-dl-element">HTML5 Description lists</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-html40/struct/lists.html#edef-DL">HTML 4 Definition
                    lists: the DL, DT, and DD elements</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </see-also>
   </resources>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="G62"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <p>For any set of terms and their associated descriptions: </p>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Check that the list is contained within a <el>dl</el> element. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Check that each term in the list being described is contained within a <el>dt</el>
                  element. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Check that when there is more than one term that shares the same decription that the <el>dt</el> elements immediately follow each other.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p>Check that the description for each term is contained in one or more <el>dd</el> elements.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p>Check that the one or more <el>dd</el> elements immediately follow the one or more <el>dt</el> elements containing the term being described.</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>All checks above are true.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
