<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="H43">
   <short-name>Using id and headers attributes to associate data cells with header cells in
          data tables</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>HTML and XHTML</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="content-structure-separation-programmatic"
                         relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to associate each data cell (in a data table) with
            the appropriate headers. This technique adds a <att>headers</att> attribute to each
            data cell (<el>td</el> element). It also adds an <att>id</att> attribute to any
            cell used as a header for other cells. The <att>headers</att> attribute of a cell
            contains a list of the <att>id</att> attributes of the associated header cells. If
            there is more than one <att>id</att>, they are separated by spaces.</p>
      <p>This technique is used when data cells are associated with more than one row and/or one
            column header. This allows screen readers to speak the headers associated with each data
            cell when the relationships are too complex to be identified using the <el>th</el>
            element alone or the <el>th</el> element with the <att>scope</att> attribute.
            Using this technique also makes these complex relationships perceivable when the
            presentation format changes.</p>
      <p>This technique is not recommended for layout tables since its use implies a
            relationship between cells that is not meaningful when tables are used for layout.</p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <head>A table with multiple rows of headers</head>
         <code role="html401"><![CDATA[<table>
   <tr>
     <th rowspan="2" id="h">Homework</th>
     <th colspan="3" id="e">Exams</th>
     <th colspan="3" id="p">Projects</th>
   </tr>
   <tr>
     <th id="e1" headers="e">1</th>
     <th id="e2" headers="e">2</th>
     <th id="ef" headers="e">Final</th>
     <th id="p1" headers="p">1</th>
     <th id="p2" headers="p">2</th>
     <th id="pf" headers="p">Final</th>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td headers="h">15%</td>
    <td headers="e e1">15%</td>
    <td headers="e e2">15%</td>
    <td headers="e ef">20%</td>
    <td headers="p p1">10%</td>
    <td headers="p p2">10%</td>
    <td headers="p pf">15%</td>
   </tr>
  </table>]]></code>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>HTML 4.01 <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.w3.org/TR/html4/struct/tables.html#h-11.4.1">header information with data cells</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </see-also>
   </resources>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="H39"/>
      <relatedtech idref="H51"/>
      <relatedtech idref="H63"/>
      <relatedtech idref="H73"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Check for layout tables: determine whether the content has a relationship with
                  other content in both its column and its row. If “no," the table is a layout
                  table. If “yes," the table is a data table.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>For data tables, check that any cell that is associated with more than one row
                  and/or one column header contains a <att>headers</att> attribute that lists the
                    <att>id</att> for all headers associated with that cell.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>For data tables where any cell contains an <att>id</att> or
                  <att>headers</att> attribute, </p>
               <olist>
                  <item>
                     <p>Check that each <att>id</att> listed in the <att>headers</att> attribute
                      of the data cell matches the <att>id</att> attribute of a cell that is used
                      as a header element</p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>Check that the <att>headers</att> attribute of a data cell contains the
                        <att>id</att> attribute of all headers associated with the data cell</p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>Check that all ids are unique (that is, no two elements in the page have the
                      same id)</p>
                  </item>
               </olist>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>If table is a layout table, no cells contain <att>headers</att> or
                  <att>id</att> attributes</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>If table is a data table and any cell contains an <att>id</att> attribute,
                  checks #3.a, #3.b, and #3.c are true.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>If table is a data table and any cell is associated with more than one row and/or
                  one column header, check #2 is true.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
