<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="H45">
   <short-name>Using longdesc</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>HTML and XHTML documents that include images that cannot be
          described in a short text alternative. </p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="text-equiv-all" relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <ua-issues>
      <ua-issue name="" version="">
         <p>User Agent support for <att>longdesc</att> varies, but overall support is improving. Screen readers such as JAWS, NVDA, and Window-Eyes support <att>longdesc</att>, but Voiceover 4.0, Orca 2.32.0, and screen magnifier Zoomtext 10.0 do not yet support the <att>longdesc</att> attribute. Browsers including Internet Explorer, Firefox, Opera, and Chrome all support longdesc.</p>
      </ua-issue>
   </ua-issues>
   <description>
      <p> The objective of this technique is to provide information in a file designated by the
            <att>longdesc</att> attribute when a short text alternative does not adequately convey the function
            or information provided in the image. The <att>longdesc</att> attribute is a <abbr expansion="Uniform Resource Identifier">URI</abbr>, the target of
            which contains a long description of the non-text content. </p>
      <p>Authors can provide a description for an image by including text in a separate resource or within the text of the page containing the image.  An advantage of using a separate resource for the description is that it is easily reusable for multiple instances of the same image, it does not add on-page visual clutter to the original document, and the description's end-point is apparent to the user. An advantage of providing the description within the same page as the image is that all users can access the description.  A limitation of the on-page method, as well as in providing multiple descriptions on a single separate page, is that current implementations supporting longdesc do not identify the long description's end-point. Authors can solve this by providing a well-formed description, which identifies the where the description ends.</p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Using longdesc to refer to a long description contained on a separate resource.</head>
         <code><![CDATA[<p><img src="chart.gif" alt="a complex chart" longdesc="chartdesc.html"/></p>]]></code>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Using longdesc to refer to a long description within the same page.</head>
         <code><![CDATA[<img longdesc="thispage.html#desc" alt="Line graph of the number of subscribers" src="http://www.company/images/graph.png">
<div id="desc">
<h3>Long Description: Line graph of the number of subscribers</h3>
<!-- Full Description of Graph -->
<p>Long description ends.</p>
<div>]]></code>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="https://www.w3.org/TR/html-longdesc/">HTML5 Image Description Extension</loc>
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.d.umn.edu/itss/training/online/moodle_downloads/accessibility_104/longdesc_tools.html">University of Minnesota Duluth listing of londesc Tools</loc>
               </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </see-also>
   </resources>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="G73"/>
      <relatedtech idref="G74"/>
      <relatedtech idref="G92"/>
      <relatedtech idref="G94"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Check that the <el>img</el> element has a longdesc attribute. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Check that the value of the <att>longdesc</att> attribute is a valid URI of an existing resource.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Check that the content at the target of that URI contains a long description describing the original non-text content associated with it.</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p> #1 through #3 are all true </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
