<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="H54">
   <short-name>Using the <el>dfn</el> element to identify the defining instance of a word</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>HTML and XHTML</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="meaning-idioms" relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to use the <el>dfn</el> to mark the use of a
            word or phrase where it is defined. The <el>dfn</el> element is used to indicate the
            defining instance of the enclosed term. In other words, it marks the occurrence of the
            term where the term is defined. Note that it encloses the term, not the definition. This
            technique would be used in combination with <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
              href="G112"
              linktype="general">Using
              inline definitions</loc> to provide the definition.</p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <description>
            <p>The following code snippet demonstrates the use of the <el>dfn</el>
              element.</p>
         </description>
         <code role="html401"><![CDATA[<p>The Web Content Accessibility Guidelines require that non-text content
has a text alternative. <dfn>Non-text content</dfn> is content that is not a sequence
of characters that can be programmatically determined or where the sequence is
not expressing something in human language; this includes ASCII Art (which is a
pattern of characters), emoticons, leetspeak (which is character substitution), and
images representing text .</p> ]]></code>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>HTML 4.01 <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.w3.org/TR/html4/struct/text.html#edef-DFN">DFN
                    Element</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </see-also>
   </resources>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="G112"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Identify all words that are defined inline in the text, that is, where the
                  definition occurs in a sentence near an occurrence of the word. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Check that each word that is defined inline is contained in a <el>dfn</el>
                  element. </p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>Check #2 is true.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
