<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="H57">
   <short-name> Using language attributes on the html element </short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>HTML and XHTML</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="meaning-doc-lang-id" relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <ua-issues>
      <ua-issue name="subtags" version="">
         <p>Additional subtags for region, script, variant or other aspects may lead to errors in language switching in older versions of some screenreaders.</p>
      </ua-issue>
      <ua-issue name="jaws" version="8">
         <p>JAWS 8.0 can be configured to change language automatically on the basis of the lang attribute. However, it only switches amongst major languages as indicated by the primary code. If a regional language variant is indicated with a language subcode, JAWS will use the default variant for which it is configured.</p>
      </ua-issue>
   </ua-issues>
   <description>
      <p> The objective of this technique is to identify the default language of a document by
            providing the <att>lang</att> and/or <att>xml:lang</att> attribute on the <el>html</el>
            element. </p>
      <p>Identifying the language of the document is important for a number of reasons: </p>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>It allows braille translation software to substitute control codes for accented
                characters, and insert control codes necessary to prevent erroneous creation of
                Grade 2 braille contractions. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>Speech synthesizers that support multiple languages will be able to orient and
                adapt to the pronunciation and syntax that are specific to the language of the page,
                speaking the text in the appropriate accent with proper pronunciation. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>Marking the language can benefit future developments in technology, for example
                users who are unable to translate between languages themselves will be able to use
                machines to translate unfamiliar languages. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>Marking the language can also assist user agents in providing definitions using a
                dictionary. </p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
      <p>HTML 4.01 uses the <el>lang</el> attribute of the <el>html</el> element. XHTML served
            as text/html uses the <att>lang</att> attribute and the <att>xml:lang</att> attribute of
            the <el>html</el> element, in order to meet the requirements of XHTML and provide
            backward compatibility with HTML. XHTML served as application/xhtml+xml uses the
              <att>xml:lang</att> attribute of the <el>html</el> element. Both the <att>lang</att>
            and the <att>xml:lang</att> attributes can take only one value. </p>
      <note>
         <p> HTML only offers the use of the <att>lang</att> attribute, while XHTML 1.0 (as a
              transitional measure) allows both attributes, and XHTML 1.1 allows only
              <att>xml:lang</att>. </p>
         <!-- Same note in H58 -->
         <p>Allowed values for the lang and xml:lang attributes are indicated in the resources referenced below. Language tags use a primary code to indicate the language, and optional subcodes (separated by hyphen characters) to indicate variants of the language. For instance, English is indicated with the primary code "en"; British English and American English can be distinguished by using "en-GB" and "en-US", respectively. Use of the primary code is important for this technique. Use of subcodes is optional but may be helpful in certain circumstances.</p>
      </note>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <description>
            <p>This example defines the content of an HTML document to be in the French language.
              </p>
         </description>
         <code role="html401"><![CDATA[<!DOCTYPE HTML PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD HTML 4.01//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/html4/strict.dtd">
<html lang="fr"> 
<head>
  <title>document écrit en français</title>
  <meta http-equiv="content-type" content="text/html; charset=utf-8" />
</head>  
<body>     
	...document écrit en français...   
</body>
</html>]]></code>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <description>
            <p>This example defines the content of an XHTML 1.0 document with content type of
                text/html to be in the French language. Both the <att>lang</att> and
                <att>xml:lang</att> attributes are specified in order to meet the requirements of
                XHTML and provide backward compatibility with HTML.</p>
         </description>
         <code role="html401"><![CDATA[<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" 
  "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" lang="fr" xml:lang="fr">
<head>
  <title>document écrit en français</title>
  <meta http-equiv="content-type" content="text/html; charset=utf-8" />
</head>
<body> 
...document écrit en français...      
</body>
</html>  ]]></code>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <description>
            <p>This example defines the content of an XHTML 1.1 document with content type of
                application/xhtml+xml to be in the French language. Only the <att>xml:lang</att>
                attribute is specified.</p>
         </description>
         <code role="html401"><![CDATA[<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.1//EN" 
   "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml11/DTD/xhtml11.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="fr">
<head>
  <title>document écrit en français</title>
	<meta http-equiv="content-type" content="application/xhtml+xml; charset=utf-8" />
</head>
<body> 
	...document écrit en français... 
</body>
</html>]]></code>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.w3.org/TR/html401/struct/dirlang.html#h-8.1">HTML 4.01
                    "lang" attribute</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/bcp/bcp47.txt">BCP 47: Tags for the
                    Identification of Languages</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.w3.org/TR/1999/REC-html401-19991224/struct/dirlang.html#h-8.1.2">Inheritance of language codes</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.w3.org/International/tutorials/language-decl/">Declaring
                    Language in XHTML and HTML</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.w3.org/TR/i18n-html-tech-lang/">Authoring Techniques for
                    XHTML &amp; HTML Internationalization: Specifying the language of content
                    1.0</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.w3.org/International/articles/language-tags/Overview.en.php">Language tags in HTML and XML</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </see-also>
   </resources>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="H58"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Examine the <el>html</el> element of the document.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Check that the <el>html</el> element has a <att>lang</att> and/or
                    <att>xml:lang</att> attribute. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Check that the value of the <att>lang</att> attribute conforms to <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/bcp/bcp47.txt">BCP 47: Tags for the
                    Identification of Languages</loc> or its successor and reflects the primary language used by the Web page. </p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>The above checks are all true.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
