<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="H58">
   <short-name>Using language attributes to identify changes in the human language </short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>HTML and XHTML</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="meaning-other-lang-id" relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <ua-issues>
      <ua-issue name="subtags" version="">
         <p>Additional subtags for region, script, variant or other aspects may lead to errors in language switching in older versions of some screenreaders.</p>
      </ua-issue>
      <ua-issue name="jaws" version="8">
         <p>JAWS 8.0 can be configured to change language automatically on the basis of the lang attribute. However, it only switches amongst major languages as indicated by the primary code. If a regional language variant is indicated with a language subcode, JAWS will use the default variant for which it is configured.</p>
      </ua-issue>
   </ua-issues>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to clearly identify any changes in language on a
            page by using the <att>lang</att> or <att>xml:lang</att> attribute, as appropriate
            for the HTML or XHTML version you use.</p>
      <p>HTML 4.01 uses the <att>lang</att> attribute on elements. XHTML served as text/html
            uses the <att>lang</att> attribute and the <att>xml:lang</att> attribute on
            elements, in order to meet the requirements of XHTML and provide backward compatibility
            with HTML. XHTML served as application/xhtml+xml uses the <att>xml:lang</att>
            attribute on elements.</p>
      <note>
         <p> HTML only offers the use of the <att>lang</att> attribute, while XHTML 1.0 (as a
              transitional measure) allows both attributes, and XHTML 1.1 allows only
              <att>xml:lang</att>. </p>
      </note>
      <!-- Same note in H57 -->
      <p>Allowed values for the lang and xml:lang attributes are indicated in the resources referenced below. Language tags use a primary code to indicate the language, and optional subcodes (separated by hyphen characters) to indicate variants of the language. For instance, English is indicated with the primary code "en"; British English and American English can be distinguished by using "en-GB" and "en-US", respectively. Use of the primary code is important for this technique. Use of subcodes is optional but may be helpful in certain circumstances.</p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <description>
            <p>This example demonstrates the use of the <att>xml:lang</att> attribute defining a
                quote written in German. This snippet could be included by an XHTML 1.1 document
                where <att>lang</att> is not allowed.</p>
         </description>
         <code role="html401"><![CDATA[<blockquote xml:lang="de">
  <p>
    Da dachte der Herr daran, ihn aus dem Futter zu schaffen,
    aber der Esel merkte, daß kein guter Wind wehte, lief fort
    und machte sich auf den Weg nach Bremen: dort, meinte er,
    könnte er ja Stadtmusikant werden.
  </p>
</blockquote>   
            ]]></code>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.w3.org/TR/html401/struct/dirlang.html#adef-lang">HTML 4.01
                    lang attribute</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-xml/#sec-lang-tag">XML 1.0 xml:lang
                  attribute</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.w3.org/TR/1999/REC-html401-19991224/struct/dirlang.html#h-8.1.2">Inheritance of language codes</loc>. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/bcp/bcp47.txt">BCP 47: Tags for the
                    Identification of Languages</loc> . </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.w3.org/International/articles/language-tags/">Language tags
                    in HTML and XML</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </see-also>
   </resources>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="H57"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <p>For each element in the document: </p>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Check that the human language of the content of the element is the same as the
                  inherited language for the element as specified in <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.w3.org/TR/1999/REC-html401-19991224/struct/dirlang.html#h-8.1.2">HTML 4.01, Inheritance of language codes</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
         </olist>
         <p>For each <att>lang</att> attribute in the document: </p>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Check that the value of the <att>lang</att> attribute conforms to <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/bcp/bcp47.txt">BCP 47: Tags for the
                    Identification of Languages</loc> or its successor </p>
            </item>
         </olist>
         <p>For each xml:lang attribute in the document: </p>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p> Check that the value of the <att>xml:lang</att> attribute conforms to <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/bcp/bcp47.txt">BCP 47: Tags for the
                    Identification of Languages</loc> or its successor </p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>All checks above are true.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
