<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="H63">
   <short-name>Using the scope attribute to associate header cells and data cells in data
          tables</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>HTML and XHTML</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="content-structure-separation-programmatic"
                         relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <ua-issues>
      <ua-issue name="" version="">
         <p>The <att>row</att> and <att>col</att> values of the <att>scope</att> attribute are
              currently supported to a large extent by most current versions of JAWS. However, there
              are still some problems and WindowEyes support for <att>scope</att> is inconsistent.
              The same is true for Japanese versions of these screen readers. Versions of JAWS prior
              to version 5 and older versions of Window-Eyes have inconsistent support for
                <att>scope</att>.</p>
         <p>At the current time, those who want to ensure consistent support across Assistive
              Technologies for tables where the headers are not in the first row/column may want to
              use the technique for complex tables <specref ref="H43"/>. For simple tables that have
              headers in the first column or row we recommend the use of the <el>th</el> and
              <el>td</el> elements. </p>
      </ua-issue>
   </ua-issues>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to associate header cells with data cells in complex tables using the
              <att>scope</att> attribute. The <att>scope</att> attribute may be used to clarify
            the scope of any cell used as a header. The scope identifies whether the cell is a
            header for a row, column, or group of rows or columns. The values <code><![CDATA[row]]></code>,
              <code><![CDATA[col]]></code>, <code><![CDATA[rowgroup]]></code>, and <code><![CDATA[colgroup]]></code> identify these
            possible scopes respectively.</p>
      <p>For simple data tables where the header is not in the first row or column, like the one
            in Example 1, this technique can be used. Based on screen reader support today, its use
            is suggested in two situations both relating to simple tables:</p>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>data cells marked up with <el>td</el> that also function as row header or column
                header </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>header cells marked up with <el>td</el> instead of <el>th</el>. Sometimes, authors
                use this to avoid the display characteristics associated with <el>th</el> and also
                do not choose to use CSS to control the display for <el>th</el>. </p>
         </item>
      </ulist>
      <note>
         <p>For simple tables that have the headers in the first row or column then it is
              sufficient to simply use the TH elements without scope. </p>
         <p>For complex tables use ids and headers as in <specref ref="H43"/>. </p>
         <p>Some users may find it easier to work with several simple tables than one more complex table. Authors may wish to consider whether they can convert complex tables to one or more simple tables.</p>
      </note>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <head>A simple schedule</head>
         <description>
            <p>In the following example, column #1 contains serial numbers for rows in the table
                and the second column contains the key value for the row. The cells in the second
                column may then use <code><![CDATA[
									]]><att>scope</att><![CDATA[="row"]]></code>. The cells in the first row too are
                marked up with <el>td</el> and use <code><![CDATA[
									]]><att>scope</att><![CDATA[="col"]]></code>. </p>
         </description>
         <code role="html401"><![CDATA[ <table border="1">
  <caption>Contact Information</caption>
  <tr>
    <td></td>
    <th scope="col">Name</th>
    <th scope="col">Phone#</th>
    <th scope="col">Fax#</th>
    <th scope="col">City</th>
  </tr><tr>
    <td>1.</td>
    <th scope="row">Joel Garner</th>
    <td>412-212-5421</td>
    <td>412-212-5400</td>
    <td>Pittsburgh</td>
  </tr><tr>
    <td>2.</td>
    <th scope="row">Clive Lloyd</th>
    <td>410-306-1420</td>
    <td>410-306-5400</td>
    <td>Baltimore</td>
  </tr><tr>
    <td>3.</td>
    <th scope="row">Gordon Greenidge</th>
    <td>281-564-6720</td>
    <td>281-511-6600</td>
    <td>Houston</td>
  </tr>
</table> ]]></code>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>HTML 4.01 <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.w3.org/TR/1999/REC-html401-19991224/struct/tables.html#adef-scope ">Table Cells: scope attribute</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>HTML 4.01 <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.w3.org/TR/html401/struct/tables.html#h-11.2.6">Table cells: The TH and TD elements</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.eramp.com/david/tablesample2.htm">Assistive technology
                    reading tables</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </see-also>
   </resources>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="H43"/>
      <relatedtech idref="H51"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <p>For each data table: </p>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Check that all <el>th</el> elements have a <att>scope</att> attribute.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Check that all <el>td</el> elements that act as headers for other elements
                  have a <att>scope</att> attribute.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Check that all <att>scope</att> attributes have the value <code><![CDATA[row]]></code>,
                    <code><![CDATA[col]]></code>, <code><![CDATA[rowgroup]]></code>, or <code><![CDATA[colgroup]]></code>.</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>All checks above are true.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
