<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="H64">
   <short-name>Using the <att>title</att> attribute of the <el>frame</el> and <el>iframe</el> elements</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>HTML and XHTML documents that use frames or iframes </p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="navigation-mechanisms-skip" relationship="cosufficient"/>
      <success-criterion idref="ensure-compat-rsv" relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <ua-issues>
      <ua-issue name="" version="">
         <p>The use of the <att>longdesc</att> attribute in HTML 4 on <el>frame</el> and <el>iframe</el> elements to specify a link to a long description of a frame is not supported well by assistive technologies. The use of <att>title</att> as described in this technique is recommended instead.</p>
      </ua-issue>
   </ua-issues>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to demonstrate the use of the <att>title</att>
            attribute of the <el>frame</el> or <el>iframe</el> element to describe the contents
            of each frame. This provides a label for the frame so users can determine which frame to
            enter and explore in detail. It does not label the individual page (frame) or inline
            frame (iframe) in the frameset.</p>
      <p>Note that the <att>title</att> attribute labels frames, and is different from the
              <el>title</el> element which labels documents. Both should be provided, since the
            first facilitates navigation among frames and the second clarifies the user's current
            location.</p>
      <p>The <att>title</att> attribute is not interchangeable with the <att>name</att>
            attribute. The <att>title</att> labels the frame for users; the <att>name</att>
            labels it for scripting and window targeting. The <att>name</att> is not presented to
            the user, only the <att>title</att> is.</p>
      <p>In HTML5 the <el>frame</el> element is marked as obsolete. The <el>iframe</el> element remains part of the HTML5 specification.</p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <description>
            <p>This example shows how to use the <att>title</att> attribute with
                <el>frame</el> to describe the frames containing the navigation bar and the
                document.</p>
         </description>
         <code role="html401"><![CDATA[<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <head>
    <title>A simple frameset document</title>
  </head>
  <frameset cols="10%, 90%">
    <frame src="nav.html" title="Main menu" />
    <frame src="doc.html" title="Documents" />
    <noframes>
      <body>
        <a href="lib.html" title="Library link">Select to
        go to the electronic library</a>
      </body>
    </noframes>
  </frameset>
</html> ]]></code>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <description>
            <p>This example shows how to use the title attribute with <el>iframe</el> to
                describe the contents of an inline frame. The example also includes an alternative
                link to the page included by the iframe element for older browsers, which may not
                understand the <el>iframe</el>element.</p>
         </description>
         <code role="html401"><![CDATA[ <html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <head>
    <title>A document using iframe</title>
  </head>
...
<iframe src="banner-ad.html" id="testiframe" 
  name="testiframe" title="Advertisement">
    <a href="banner-ad.html">Advertisement</a>
</iframe>
...
</html>  ]]></code>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.w3.org/TR/html4/present/frames.html#h-16.2.2"> HTML 4.01
                    FRAME element</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.w3.org/TR/html4/present/frames.html#h-16.5">HTML 4.0.1
                    Inline frames: the IFRAME element</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.jimthatcher.com/webcourse4.htm">Accessible Navigation,
                    "Implementing Frame Titles"</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </see-also>
   </resources>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Check each frame and iframe element in the HTML or XHTML source code for the presence of a
                  title attribute.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Check that the title attribute contains text that identifies the frame.</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>Checks #1 and #2 are true.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
