<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="H65">
   <short-name>Using the title attribute to identify form controls when the label element
          cannot be used</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>HTML and XHTML form controls that are not identified using <att>value</att>,
            <att>alt</att>, or element content </p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="text-equiv-all" relationship="sufficient"/>
      <success-criterion idref="content-structure-separation-programmatic"
                         relationship="sufficient"/>
      <success-criterion idref="minimize-error-cues" relationship="sufficient"/>
      <success-criterion idref="ensure-compat-rsv" relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <ua-issues>
      <ua-issue name="" version="">
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>User agents will display a tool tip when the mouse hovers above an
                  <el>input</el> element containing a <att>title</att> attribute. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>If no <el>label</el> is available, JAWS and Window-Eyes speak the
                  <att>title</att> attribute when the form control receives focus </p>
               <ulist>
                  <item>
                     <p>JAWS 6.0 and later can be set to speak both <el>label</el> and
                        <att>title</att> when the two items are different; however, very few users
                      are aware of this setting.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>WindowEyes 5.5 has a hot key, ins-E, that will display additional
                      information, including the title attribute, for the item with focus. </p>
                  </item>
               </ulist>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </ua-issue>
   </ua-issues>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to use the <att>title</att> attribute to label
            form controls when the visual design cannot accommodate the label (for example, if there
            is no text on the screen that can be identified as a label) or where it might be
            confusing to display a label. User agents, including assistive technology, can speak the
              <att>title</att> attribute.</p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <head>A pulldown menu that limits the scope of a search</head>
         <description>
            <p>A search form uses a pulldown menu to limit the scope of the search. The pulldown
                menu is immediately adjacent to the text field used to enter the search term. The
                relationship between the search field and the pulldown menu is clear to users who
                can see the visual design, which does not have room for a visible label. The
                  <att>title</att> attribute is used to identify the <el>select</el> menu. The
                  <att>title</att> attribute can be spoken by screen readers or displayed as a
                tool tip for people using screen magnifiers.</p>
         </description>
         <code role="html401"><![CDATA[<label for="searchTerm">Search for:</label>
<input id="searchTerm" type="text" size="30" value="" name="searchTerm">
<select title="Search in" id="scope">
…
</select> ]]></code>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Input fields for a phone number</head>
         <description>
            <p>A Web page contains controls for entering a phone number in the United States, with
                three fields for area code, exchange, and last four digits.</p>
         </description>
         <code role="html401"><![CDATA[<fieldset><legend>Phone number</legend>
<input id="areaCode" name="areaCode" title="Area Code" 
type="text" size="3" value="">
<input id="exchange" name="exchange" title="First three digits of phone number" 
type="text" size="3" value="">
<input id="lastDigits" name="lastDigits" title="Last four digits of phone number" 
type="text" size="4" value="">
</fieldset> ]]></code>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <head> A Search Function</head>
         <description>
            <p>A Web page contains a text field where the user can enter search terms and a button labeled "Search" for performing the search. The <att>title</att> attribute is used to identify the form control and the button is positioned right after the text field so that it is clear to the user that the text field is where the search term should be entered.</p>
         </description>
         <code role="html401"><![CDATA[
<input type="text" title="Type search term here"/> <input type="submit" value="Search"/>
]]></code>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <head>A data table of form controls</head>
         <description>
            <p>A data table of form controls needs to associate each control with the column and row headers for that cell. Without a title (or off-screen LABEL) it is difficult for non-visual users to pause and interrogate for corresponding row/column header values using their assistive technology  while tabbing through the form.</p>
            <p>For example, a survey form has four column headers in first row: Question, Agree, Undecided, Disagree. Each following row contains a question and a radio button in each cell 			corresponding to answer choice in the three columns. The title attribute for every radio button is a concatenation of the answer choice (column header) and the text of the question (row header) with a hyphen or colon as a separator.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>HTML 4.01 <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.w3.org/TR/html4/struct/global.html#h-7.4.3">The
                    title attribute</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.jimthatcher.com/webcourse8.htm">Accessible Forms</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://usability.com.au/2008/09/accessible-forms-using-wcag-2-0/">Accessible Forms using WCAG 2.0</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </see-also>
   </resources>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="H44"/>
      <relatedtech idref="H71"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Identify each form control that is not associated with a <el>label</el>
                  element </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Check that the control has a <att>title</att> attribute</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Check that the <att>title</att> attribute identifies the purpose of the
                control</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>All checks above are true.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
