<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="H69">
   <short-name>Providing heading elements at the beginning of each section of content</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>HTML and XHTML</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="navigation-mechanisms-skip" relationship="sufficient"/>
      <success-criterion idref="navigation-mechanisms-headings" relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <ua-issues>
      <ua-issue name="" version="">
         <p>Most screen readers provide navigation via headings and provide information
              about the level of the heading. The Opera browser provides a mechanism to navigate by
              headings. Additional plugins support navigation by headings in other user agents. See the Resources section for references to some of these plugins.</p>
         <ednote id="H69_note">
            <edtext>There is an <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    href="http://lists.w3.org/Archives/Public/w3c-wai-ig/2011JulSep/0177.html">action to update user agent notes</loc>, but not yet a precise edit.</edtext>
         </ednote>
      </ua-issue>
   </ua-issues>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to use section headings to convey the structure of
        		the content. Heading markup can be used:</p>
      <ulist>
         <item>
            <p>to indicate start of main content</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>to mark up section headings within the main content area</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>to demarcate different navigational sections like top or main navigation, left or
        				secondary navigation and footer navigation</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>to mark up images of text that are used as headings</p>
         </item>
		 <item><p>to allow users the ability to navigate a page by sections or skip repeated blocks of information</p></item>
      </ulist>
      <p>Headings are designed to convey logical hierarchy. Skipping
        		levels in the sequence of headings may create the impression that the structure of the
        		document has not been properly thought through or that specific headings have been
        		chosen for their visual rendering rather than their meaning. Authors are encouraged to
        		nest headings hierarchically. When headings are nested hierarchically, the most important information is given the highest logical level, and subsections are given subsequent logical levels.(i.e., h2 is a subsection of h1). <phrase>Providing this type of structure will help users understand the overall organization of the content more easily.</phrase></p>
      <p>Since headings indicate the start of important sections of content, it is possible for
        		users with assistive technology to jump directly to the appropriate heading and begin
        		reading the content. This significantly speeds interaction for users who would otherwise
        		access the content slowly. Headings create chunks of information that can be found easily by people with disabilities, such as a blind person using a screen reader, or a person with a cognitive disability who uses assistive technology that delineates groups of information, or someone with a communication disability or illiteracy, who uses a screen reader to assist them in their reading.
					</p>
      <note>
         <p>All of our techniques assume that people needing special user agents (including AT or special plug-ins) will get and be using that type user agent (eg screen reader, or plug-in that allows keyboard navigation of properly marked up content, etc).</p>
      </note>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <description>
            <p>This example organizes the sections of a search page by marking each section
                heading using <el>h2</el> elements.</p>
         </description>
         <code role="html401"><![CDATA[<h1>Search Technical Periodicals</h1>
 <h2>Search</h2>
 <form action="search.php">
  <p><label for="searchInput">Enter search topic: </label>
  <input type="text" size="30" id="searchInput">
  <input type="submit" value="Go"></p>
 </form>
 <h2>Available Periodicals</h2>
 <div class="jlinks">
  <a href="pcoder.com">Professional Coder</a> |
  <a href="algo.com">Algorithms</a> |
  <a href="jse.com">Journal of Software Engineering</a>
 </div>
 <h2>Search Results</h2>
 ... search results are returned in this section ...   ]]></code>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Headings show the overall organization of the content</head>
         <description>
            <p>In this example, heading markup is used to make the navigation and main content
                sections perceivable.</p>
         </description>
         <code role="html401"><![CDATA[<!-- Logo, banner graphic, search form, etc.  -->
  <h2>Navigation</h2>
    <ul>
      <li><a href="about.htm">About us</a></li>
      <li><a href="contact.htm">Contact us</a></li>
       ...
    </ul>
  <h2>All about headings</h2>
   <!-- Text, images, other material making up the main content... --> 
            ]]></code>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Headings show the organization of material within the main content</head>
         <description>
            <p>Note that in HTML 4.01 and XHTML 1.x, heading elements only mark the beginning of
              	sections. Because there is no markup to associate a heading element with the section content explicitly, users will assume that the heading applies to all following content until the next heading element is encountered.</p>
         </description>
         <code role="html401"><![CDATA[ <html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <head>
    <title>Cooking techniques</title>  
  </head>   
  <body>     
    <h1>Cooking techniques</h1>     
    <p>       
      ... some text here ...     
    </p>           
    <h2>Cooking with oil</h2> 
    <p> 
        ... text of the section ...     
    </p>           
    <h2>Cooking with butter</h2>       
    <p>
        ... text of the section ...     
    </p>   
  </body> 
</html>    ]]></code>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.w3.org/TR/html401/struct/global.html#h-7.5.5">HTML 4.01
                    H1-H6 elements</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://meyerweb.com/eric/thoughts/2004/07/21/pick-a-heading/">Pick a
                    Heading</loc> Eric Meyer</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://webaim.org/techniques/semanticstructure/">WebAIM: Semantic Structure</loc>
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://accessibility.psu.edu/headingshtml/">Heading Tags</loc>
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.456bereastreet.com/archive/201003/heading_navigation_in_web_browsers/">Heading navigation in web browsers</loc>
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>For Firefox, the following plugins provide header navigation via the keyboard:</p>
               <ulist>
                  <item>
                     <p>
                        <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                             href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/accessibility-evaluation-toolb/">Accessibility Evaluation Toolbar</loc>
                     </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p>
                        <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                             href="http://juicystudio.com/article/heading-navigation-greasemonkey-user-script.php">Heading Navigation Greasemonkey User Script</loc>
                     </p>
                  </item>
               </ulist>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </see-also>
   </resources>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="H42"/>
      <relatedtech idref="F2"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
			<item><p>Check that the content is divided into separate sections</p></item>
            <item>
               <p>Check that each section <phrase>on the page</phrase> starts with a heading.</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>For 2.4.1 check #2 is true.</p>
            </item>
			<item><p>For 2.4.10 checks #1 and #2 are true.</p></item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
