<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="H70">
   <short-name>Using frame elements to group blocks of repeated material</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>HTML and XHTML documents that use frames </p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="navigation-mechanisms-skip" relationship="cosufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to demonstrate how framesets can be used to group
            blocks of repeated material. Since most user agents and assistive technology provide a
            way to navigate from frame to frame, using frames to organize elements can provide a
            mechanism for easily bypassing blocks of repeated content. If the site uses framesets,
            organize the blocks of content into separate frames. Make certain that the repeated
            blocks of content appear in the same frame within the frameset of each Web page. In
            addition, each frame element must have a title attribute to describe the content of the
            frame. When frames are properly titled, users can use frame navigation to easily
            navigate between blocks of content.</p>
      <p>This technique is appropriate when framesets are already used to organize the content
            of the page; other techniques are preferred for pages that are not already using
            framesets, because many people using assistive technology have trouble with frames . An
            advisory technique about using noframes is available in <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
              href="text-equiv-all"
              linktype="understanding">Success Criterion 1.1.1</loc>. </p>
      <p>In HTML5 the <el>frame</el> element is marked as obsolete.</p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <description>
            <p>The following example shows the use of two frames to organize content. The source
                of the first frame is the Web page, navigation.html, which contains the HTML for the
                navigation. This frame has a title attribute which identifies it as a navigation
                bar. The second frame contains the main content of the site as indicated by the
                source parameter of main.html and the title attribute, "Main News Content" which
                identifies its function.</p>
         </description>
         <code role="html401"><![CDATA[<frameset cols="20%, *">
  <frame src="navigation.html" name="navbar" title="Navigation Bar" />
  <frame src="main.html" name="maincontent" title="Main News Content" />
  <noframes>
    <p>View <a href="noframe.html">no frame version</a>.</p>
  </noframes>
</frameset>   ]]></code>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p> HTML 4.01 <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.w3.org/TR/html4/present/frames.html#h-16.2.1">
                    The FRAMESET element</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> HTML 4.01 <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.w3.org/TR/html4/present/frames.html#h-16.2.2">    The FRAME element</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.jimthatcher.com/webcourse4.htm">Accessible Navigation</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </see-also>
   </resources>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="H64"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <p>If the Web page uses frames to organize content: </p>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Check if repeated blocks of content are organized into separate frames.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Check that the frames with repeated content appear in the same location within
                  each frameset.</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>Checks #1 and #2 are true.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
