<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="H74">
   <short-name>Ensuring that opening and closing tags are used according to specification</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p> HTML and XHTML</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="ensure-compat-parses" relationship="cosufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p> The objective of this technique is to avoid key errors that are known to cause
            problems for assistive technologies when they are trying to parse content which involve
            having opening and closing tags that are not used according to specification. These
            errors can be avoided by using the HTML or XHTML mechanism to specify the technology and
            technology version, and making sure the Web page does not have these types of errors in
            it. There are several validators that the developer can use: validation reports
            generally mention these types of errors. This technique deals only with errors related
            to incorrectly formed opening and closing tags. The document type declaration is not
            strictly necessary for this type of evaluation, but specifying the document type
            declaration makes it easier to use a validator. </p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <head> HTML</head>
         <description>
            <p> HTML pages include a document type declaration (sometimes referred to as
                  <code><![CDATA[!DOCTYPE]]></code> statement). The developer can use offline or online
                validators (see Resources below) to check that all id attribute values are unique
                and that opening and closing tags are used according to the specification. </p>
                <note><p>The specification for which tags require closing elements has changed with the introduction of HTML5.</p></note>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <head>XHTML</head>
         <description>
            <p> Like other other XML-based documents, XHTML documents reference a Document Type
                Definition (DTD) or other type of XML schema. The developer can use online or
                offline validators (including validation tools built into editors) to check that
                opening and closing tags are used according to the specification. </p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <head>Using test frameworks</head>
         <description>
            <p> When a Website generates HTML or XHTML dynamically instead of serving only static pages, a
                developer can use <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    href="http://xhtmlunit.sourceforge.net/">XHTMLUnit</loc>,
                  <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    href="http://xmltestsuite.sourceforge.net/">XML Test Suite</loc> or a similar
                framework to test the generated XHTML code. </p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.w3.org/QA/Tips/Doctype">Do not forget to add a doctype</loc>
                  by the W3C Quality Assurance Initiative explains what doctypes are and why you
                  should use them. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.w3.org/QA/2002/04/valid-dtd-list.html">Recommended DTDs to
                    use in your Web document</loc> by the W3C Quality Assurance Initiative is a list
                  of commonly used declarations. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.chami.com/html-kit/faq/pages/validate_tools.html">How do I
                    validate my code or check for possible errors?</loc> describes the tools in the
                  free editor HTML-Kit for checking HTML, CSS and XML. </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
         <p> For other resources, see <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                 href="G134"
                 linktype="general">Validating Web
              pages</loc>. </p>
      </see-also>
   </resources>
   <related-techniques/>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p> Check that there are closing tags for all elements with required closing tags.
                </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Check that there are no closing tags for all elements where closing tags are
                  forbidden. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Check that opening and closing tags for all elements are correctly nested. </p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <p> Steps 1, 2, and 3 are true.</p>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
