<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="H75">
   <short-name>Ensuring that Web pages are well-formed</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p> Any XML-based markup languages. </p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="ensure-compat-parses" relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p> The objective of this technique is to avoid key errors that are known to cause
            problems for assistive technologies when they are trying to parse contents.
            Well-formedness is checked by parsing the document with a conforming XML parser and
            checking if the validation report mentions well-formedness errors. Every conforming XML
            parser is required to check well-formedness and stop normal processing when a
            well-formedness error is found (a conforming XML parser does not need to support
            validation).</p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <head/>
         <description>
            <p>XML files include a document type declaration, a xsi:schemaLocation attribute or
                other type of reference to a schema. The developer can use off-line or online
                validators, an XML editor or an IDE with XML support (see Resources below) to check
                well-formedness. </p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <head/>
         <description>
            <p> When XML files do not include a document type declaration, a xsi:schemaLocation
                attribute or a processing instruction referencing a schema even though there is a
                schema for them, the relevant schema is specified by a command line instruction, a
                user dialog or a configuration file, and the XML files are checked against the
                schema.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <head/>
         <description>
            <p>When XML files do not include a document type declaration, a xsi:schemaLocation
                attribute or a processing instruction referencing a schema even though there is a
                schema for them, the namespace is dereferenced to retrieve a schema document or
                resource directory (Resource Directory Description Language: <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" href="http://www.rddl.org/">RDDL</loc>), and the XML files are checked against the
                schema.</p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
      <eg-group>
         <head/>
         <description>
            <p>When a Website generates XML dynamically instead of serving only static documents,
                a developer can use <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    href="http://xmlunit.sourceforge.net/">XMLUnit</loc>, <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    href="http://xmltestsuite.sourceforge.net/">XML Test Suite</loc> or a similar
                framework to test the generated XML code. </p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2004/REC-xml-20040204/Overview.html#sec-well-formed">Well-Formed XML Documents</loc> in Extensible Markup Language (XML) 1.0 (Third
                  Edition), W3C Recommendation 04 February 2004. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2004/REC-xml11-20040204/#sec-well-formed">Well-Formed XML Documents</loc> in Extensible Markup Language (XML) 1.1, W3C
                  Recommendation 04 February 2004. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-xml/#wf-entities">4.3.2 Well-Formed Parsed
                    Entities</loc> in Extensible Markup Language (XML) 1.1, W3C Recommendation 04
                  February 2004.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
         <p> For other resources, see <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                 href="G134"
                 linktype="general">Validating Web
              pages</loc>. </p>
      </see-also>
   </resources>
   <related-techniques/>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p> Load each file into a validating XML parser. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p> Check that there are no well-formedness errors. </p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <p>Step 2 is true.</p>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
