<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="H83">
   <short-name>Using the target attribute to open a new window on user request and indicating this in link text</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>HTML5, HTML 4.01 Transitional, and XHTML 1.0 Transitional</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="consistent-behavior-no-extreme-changes-context"
                         relationship="sufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to avoid confusion that may be caused by the appearance of new windows that were not requested by the user. Suddenly opening new windows can disorient users or be missed completely by some. In HTML5, HTML 4.01 Transitional, and XHTML 1.0 Transitional, the <att>target</att> attribute can be used to open a new window, instead of automatic pop-ups. (The <att>target</att> attribute is deleted from HTML 4.01 Strict and XHTML 1.0 Strict.) Note that not using the <att>target</att> allows the user to decide whether a new window should be opened or not. Use of the <att>target</att> attribute provides an unambiguously machine-readable indication that a new window will open. User agents can inform the user, and can also be configured not to open the new window. For those not using assistive technology, the indication would also be available from the link text.</p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <description>
            <p>The following example illustrates  the use of the <att>target</att> attribute in a link that indicates it will open in a new window.</p>
         </description>
         <code role="HTML4"><![CDATA[<a href="help.html" target="_blank">Show Help (opens new window)</a>]]></code>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.w3.org/TR/html5/links.html#attr-hyperlink-target">HTML5 target attribute</loc>
								       </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </see-also>
   </resources>
   <related-techniques>
      <relatedtech idref="SCR24"/>
   </related-techniques>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p>Activate each link in the document to check if it opens a new window.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>For each link that opens a new window, check that it uses the <att>target</att> attribute.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Check that the link text contains information indicating that the link will open in a new window.</p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>Checks #2 and #3 are true.</p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
