<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE technique
  SYSTEM "../../xmlspec.dtd">
<technique id="H94">
   <short-name>Ensuring that elements do not contain duplicate attributes</short-name>
   <applicability>
      <p>All HTML pages</p>
   </applicability>
   <applies-to>
      <success-criterion idref="ensure-compat-parses" relationship="cosufficient"/>
   </applies-to>
   <description>
      <p>The objective of this technique is to avoid key errors that are known
    				to cause problems for assistive technologies when they are trying to
    				parse content that has duplicate attributes on the same element. This
    				can be checked manually, or by using HTML's mechanism to specify the
    				technology and technology version and validating the document for this
    				condition. There are several validators that the developer can use;
    				validation reports generally mention this type of error. The document
    				type declaration is not strictly necessary for this type of evaluation,
    				but specifying the document type declaration makes it easier to use
    				a validator. </p>
   </description>
   <examples>
      <eg-group>
         <head>HTML Validators</head>
         <description>
            <p>HTML pages include a document type declaration (sometimes referred
    						to as !DOCTYPE statement). The developer can use offline or online
    						validators (see Resources below) to check that attributes are only
    						used once on an element. The W3C validador, for example, will report   "duplicate
    						specification of attribute X" when it encounters the second definition
    						of the same attribute on an element. </p>
         </description>
      </eg-group>
   </examples>
   <resources>
      <see-also>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.w3.org/QA/Tips/Doctype">Do
    					not forget to add a doctype by the W3C Quality Assurance Initiative
    					explains what doctypes are and why you should use them</loc>. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.w3.org/QA/2002/04/valid-dtd-list.html">Recommended
    						DTDs to use in your Web document by the W3C Quality Assurance Initiative
    						is a list of commonly used declarations</loc>. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
									         <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                       href="http://www.chami.com/html-kit/faq/pages/validate_tools.html">How
    							do I validate my code or check for possible errors? describes the
    							tools in the free editor HTML-Kit for checking HTML, CSS and XML</loc>. </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
         <p>For other resources, see <loc xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                 href="G134"
                 linktype="general">G134:
    					Validating Web pages</loc>. </p>
      </see-also>
   </resources>
   <tests>
      <procedure>
         <olist>
            <item>
               <p> Check that no attribute occurs more than once on any element </p>
            </item>
         </olist>
      </procedure>
      <expected-results>
         <ulist>
            <item>
               <p> Check 1 is true. </p>
            </item>
         </ulist>
      </expected-results>
   </tests>
</technique>
